b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n\n<workbook_page id="p0_thermo_unit_intro" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Introduction to Thermochemistry</title>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n        <image src="../webcontent/match.jpg" alt="A match held in a person\xe2\x80\x99s hand is ignited as it is scratched along the rough surface of a match box." width="500">\n            <caption>Sliding a match head along a rough surface initiates a combustion reaction that\n                produces energy in the form of heat and light. (credit: modification of work by\n                Laszlo Ilyes)</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>Chemical reactions, such as those that occur when you light a match, involve changes in\n            energy as well as matter. Societies at all levels of development could not function\n            without the energy released by chemical reactions. In 2012, about 85% of US energy\n            consumption came from the combustion of petroleum products, coal, wood, and garbage. We\n            use this energy to produce electricity (38%); to transport food, raw materials,\n            manufactured goods, and people (27%); for industrial production (21%); and to heat and\n            power our homes and businesses (10%). While these combustion reactions help us meet our\n            essential energy needs, they are also recognized by the majority of the scientific\n            community as a major contributor to global climate change.</p>\n        <p>Useful forms of energy are also available from a variety of chemical reactions other than\n            combustion. For example, the energy produced by the batteries in a cell phone, car, or\n            flashlight results from chemical reactions. This unit introduces many of the basic\n            ideas necessary to explore the relationships between chemical changes and energy, with a\n            focus on thermal energy.</p>\n\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n                href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'