b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p10_molecular_compounds" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title> Molecular Compounds </title>\n        <objref idref="chemical_formulas"/>\n        <objref idref="name_compounds"/>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>Many compounds do not contain ions but instead consist solely of discrete, neutral\n            molecules. These molecular compounds (covalent compounds) result when atoms share,\n            rather than transfer (gain or lose), electrons. Covalent bonding is an important and\n            extensive concept in chemistry, and it will be treated in considerable detail later in\n            this course. We can often identify molecular compounds on the basis of their physical\n            properties. Under normal conditions, molecular compounds often exist as gases,\n            low-boiling liquids, and low-melting solids, although many important exceptions\n            exist.</p>\n        <p>Whereas ionic compounds are usually formed when a metal and a nonmetal combine, covalent\n            compounds are usually formed by a combination of nonmetals. Thus, the periodic table can\n            help us recognize many of the compounds that are covalent. While we can use the\n            positions of a compound\xe2\x80\x99s elements in the periodic table to predict whether it is ionic\n            or covalent at this point in our study of chemistry, you should be aware that this is a\n            very simplistic approach that does not account for a number of interesting exceptions.\n            Shades of gray exist between ionic and molecular compounds, and you\xe2\x80\x99ll learn more about\n            those later.</p>\n          <wb:inline idref="molecular_ionic_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n        <section>\n            <title>Nomenclature of Binary Molecular Compounds</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>The bonding characteristics of inorganic molecular compounds are different from\n                    ionic compounds, and they are named using a different system as well. The\n                    charges of cations and anions dictate their ratios in ionic compounds, so\n                    specifying the names of the ions provides sufficient information to determine\n                    chemical formulas. However, because covalent bonding allows for significant\n                    variation in the combination ratios of the atoms in a molecule, the names for\n                    molecular compounds must explicitly identify these ratios.</p>\n                <p>When two nonmetallic elements form a molecular compound, several combination\n                    ratios are often possible. For example, carbon and oxygen can form the compounds\n                    CO and CO<sub>2</sub>. Since these are different substances with different\n                    properties, they cannot both have the same name (they cannot both be called\n                    carbon oxide). To deal with this situation, we use a naming method that is\n                    somewhat similar to that used for ionic compounds, but with added prefixes to\n                    specify the numbers of atoms of each element. The name of the more metallic\n                    element (the one farther to the left and/or bottom of the periodic table) is\n                    first, followed by the name of the more nonmetallic element (the one farther to\n                    the right and/or top) with its ending changed to the suffix \xe2\x80\x93ide. The numbers of\n                    atoms of each element are designated by the Greek prefixes shown in the table\n                    below.</p>\n                <table>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Number</em></td>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Prefix</em></td>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Number</em></td>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Prefix</em></td>\n\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>1 (sometimes omitted)</td>\n                        <td>mon-</td>\n                        <td>6</td>\n                        <td>hexa-</td>\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>2</td>\n                        <td>di-</td>\n                        <td>7</td>\n                        <td>hepta-</td>\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>3</td>\n                        <td>tri-</td>\n                        <td>8</td>\n                        <td>octa-</td>\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>4</td>\n                        <td>tetra-</td>\n                        <td>9</td>\n                        <td>nona-</td>\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>5</td>\n                        <td>penta-</td>\n                        <td>10</td>\n                        <td>deca-</td>\n                    </tr>\n                </table>\n                <p>When only one atom of the first element is present, the prefix mono- is usually\n                    deleted from that part. Thus, CO is named carbon monoxide, and CO<sub>2</sub> is\n                    called carbon dioxide. When two vowels are adjacent, the "a" in the Greek prefix\n                    is usually dropped. Some other examples are shown in table below.</p>\n                <table>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Compound</em></td>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Name</em></td>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Compound</em></td>\n                        <td align="center"><em style="bold">Name</em></td>\n\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>SO<sub>2</sub></td>\n                        <td>sulfur dioxide</td>\n                        <td>BCl<sub>3</sub></td>\n                        <td>boron trichloride</td>\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td>\n                        <td>dinitrogen pentoxide</td>\n                        <td>P<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub></td>\n                        <td>tetraphosphorus decoxide</td>\n                    </tr>\n                    <tr>\n                        <td>SF<sub>6</sub></td>\n                        <td>sulfur hexafluoride</td>\n                        <td>IF<sub>7</sub></td>\n                        <td>iodine heptafluoride</td>\n                    </tr>\n                </table>\n                <p>There are a few common names that you will encounter as you continue your study\n                    of chemistry. For example, although NO is often called nitric oxide, its proper\n                    name is nitrogen monoxide. Similarly, N<sub>2</sub>O is known as nitrous oxide even though\n                    our rules would specify the name dinitrogen monoxide. (And H<sub>2</sub>O is usually called\n                    water, not dihydrogen monoxide.) You should commit to memory the common names of\n                    compounds as you encounter them.</p>\n                  <wb:inline idref="molecular_names_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline> \n                <wb:inline idref="molec_comp_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n              \n            </body>\n        </section>\n\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'