b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p10O_summary" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n    \n    \n    <head>\n        <title>Measurements: Summary</title>\n    </head>\n    <body>\n        \n        <section><title></title>\n            <body>\n                <p>Measurements provide quantitative information that is critical in studying and practicing chemistry. \n                    Each measurement has an amount, a unit for comparison, and an uncertainty. Measurements can be \n                    represented in either decimal or scientific notation. Scientists primarily use the SI (International System) \n                    or metric systems. We use base SI units such as meters, seconds, and kilograms, as well as derived units, \n                    such as liters (for volume) and g/cm<sup>3</sup> (for density). In many cases, we find it convenient to use unit prefixes \n                    that yield fractional and multiple units, such as microseconds (10<sup>-6</sup> seconds) and megahertz (10<sup>6</sup> hertz), \n                    respectively.</p>\n                <p>Quantities can be exact or measured. Measured quantities have an associated uncertainty that is represented by the number \n                    of significant figures in the measurement. The uncertainty of a calculated value depends on the uncertainties in \n                    the values used in the calculation and is reflected in how the value is rounded. Measured values can be accurate \n                    (close to the true value) and/or precise (showing little variation when measured repeatedly).</p>\n                <p>Measurements are made using a variety of units. It is often useful or necessary to convert a measured \n                    quantity from one unit into another. These conversions are accomplished using unit conversion factors, \n                    which are derived by simple applications of a mathematical approach called the factor-label method or \n                    dimensional analysis. This strategy is also employed to calculate sought quantities using measured \n                    quantities and appropriate mathematical relations.</p>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n       \n        \n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>   \n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n\n\n\n'