b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p10O_quantum_summary" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n    \n    \n    <head>\n        <title>Quantum Theory: Summary</title>\n        \n    </head>\n    \n    <body>\n        <section>\n            <title></title>\n            <body>\n                <p>Macroscopic objects act as particles. Microscopic objects (such as electrons)\n                    have properties of both a particle and a wave. Their exact trajectories cannot\n                    be determined. The quantum mechanical model of atoms describes the\n                    three-dimensional position of the electron in a probabilistic manner according\n                    to a mathematical function called a wavefunction, often denoted as \xcf\x88. Atomic\n                    wavefunctions are also called orbitals. The squared magnitude of the\n                    wavefunction describes the distribution of the probability of finding the\n                    electron in a particular region in space. Therefore, atomic orbitals describe\n                    the areas in an atom where electrons are most likely to be found.</p>\n                <p>An atomic orbital is characterized by three quantum numbers. The principal\n                    quantum number, n, can be any positive integer. The general region for value of\n                    energy of the orbital and the average distance of an electron from the nucleus\n                    are related to n. Orbitals having the same value of n are said to be in the same\n                    shell. The angular momentum quantum number, l, can have any integer value from 0\n                    to n \xe2\x80\x93 1. This quantum number describes the shape or type of the orbital.\n                    Orbitals with the same principle quantum number and the same l value belong to\n                    the same subshell. The magnetic quantum number, ml, with 2l + 1 values ranging\n                    from \xe2\x80\x93l to +l, describes the orientation of the orbital in space. In addition,\n                    each electron has a spin quantum number, ms, that can be equal to \xc2\xb112. No two\n                    electrons in the same atom can have the same set of values for all the four\n                    quantum numbers.</p>\n                <p>The relative energy of the subshells determine the order in which atomic orbitals\n                    are filled (1s, 2s, 2p, 3s, 3p, 4s, 3d, 4p, and so on). Electron configurations\n                    and orbital diagrams can be determined by applying the Pauli exclusion principle\n                    (no two electrons can have the same set of four quantum numbers) and Hund\xe2\x80\x99s rule\n                    (whenever possible, electrons retain unpaired spins in degenerate orbitals).</p>\n                <p>Electrons in the outermost orbitals, called valence electrons, are responsible\n                    for most of the chemical behavior of elements. In the periodic table, elements\n                    with analogous valence electron configurations usually occur within the same\n                    group. There are some exceptions to the predicted filling order, particularly\n                    when half-filled or completely filled orbitals can be formed. The periodic table\n                    can be divided into three categories based on the orbital in which the last\n                    electron to be added is placed: main group elements (s and p orbitals),\n                    transition elements (d orbitals), and inner transition elements (f\n                    orbitals).</p>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n      \n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0\n                License</link>. </p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312</link>.</p>\n        \n        \n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n\n'