b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p1_equil_calc_intro" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Introduction to Equilibrium Calculations</title>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>We know that at equilibrium, the value of the reaction quotient of any reaction is equal\n            to its equilibrium constant. Thus, we can use the mathematical expression for Q to\n            determine a number of quantities associated with a reaction at equilibrium or\n            approaching equilibrium. While we have learned to identify in which direction a reaction\n            will shift to reach equilibrium, we want to extend that understanding to quantitative\n            calculations. We do so by evaluating the ways that the concentrations of products and\n            reactants change as a reaction approaches equilibrium, keeping in mind the\n            stoichiometric ratios of the reaction. This algebraic approach to equilibrium\n            calculations will be explored in this module.</p>\n        <p>Changes in concentrations or pressures of reactants and products occur as a reaction\n            system approaches equilibrium. In this module we will see that we can relate these\n            changes to each other using the coefficients in the balanced chemical equation\n            describing the system. We use the decomposition of ammonia as an example.</p>\n        <p>On heating, ammonia reversibly decomposes into nitrogen and hydrogen according to this\n            equation:</p>\n        <formula>$$2\\;{\\mathrm{NH}}_3(g)\\;\\;\\rightleftharpoons\\;\\;{\\mathrm N}_2(g)\\;+\\;3\\;{\\mathrm H}_2(g)$$</formula>\n        \n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'