b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p1_ionicBond" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Ionic Bond Formation</title>\n        <objref idref="ionic_bond"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n        <p><activity_link idref="Periodic_Table" target="new"><em>Reference: The Periodic Table of Elements</em></activity_link></p>\n        <section>\n            <title>Chemical Bonding and the Octet Rule</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>Chemical bonding is the force of attraction that holds two or more atoms\n                    together. Chemical bonding is the result of atoms gaining, losing, or sharing\n                    valence electrons. <extra><anchor>Ionic bonds</anchor><meaning><material><p>electrostatic forces of attraction between the oppositely charged ions of an ionic compound</p></material></meaning></extra> form from the transfer of electrons from one atom\n                    to another to form positively and negatively charged ions. <extra><anchor>Covalent bonds</anchor><meaning><material><p>bond formed when electrons are shared between atoms</p></material></meaning></extra> form\n                    when two or more atoms share electrons. But why do atoms have this tendency to\n                    gain, lose, or share electrons to form compounds? The answer has to do with the\n                    stability of electron configurations. The most stable arrangement of electrons\n                    is when the outer shell is full. With the exception of the  first shell which\n                    is full with two electrons, all of the other shells are full with eight\n                    electrons. It is important to recognize that when the outer shell is full this\n                    corresponds to the electron configuration of a noble gas. From this general\n                    observation comes a very important concept of chemical bonding the <extra><anchor>Octet Rule</anchor><meaning><material><p>guideline that states main group atoms will form structures in which eight valence electrons interact with each nucleus, counting bonding electrons as interacting with both atoms connected by the bond</p></material></meaning></extra>.\n                    Main group elements will gain, lose, or share electrons in order to obtain the\n                    electron configuration of a noble gas. </p>\n                <p>Previously, we discussed the basic concepts of ionic and covalent bonding. In\n                    this unit, we will look at chemical bonding in more detail, beginning here with\n                    ionic bonding.</p>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <section>\n            <title>Ionic Bonds</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>As you have learned, ions are atoms or molecules bearing an electrical charge. A\n                    cation (a positive ion) forms when a neutral atom loses one or more electrons\n                    from its valence shell, and an anion (a negative ion) forms when a neutral atom\n                    gains one or more electrons in its valence shell. </p>\n                <p>Compounds composed of ions are called ionic compounds (or salts), and their\n                    constituent ions are held together by <extra><anchor>ionic bonds</anchor><meaning><material><p>electrostatic forces of attraction between the oppositely charged ions of an ionic compound</p></material></meaning></extra>: electrostatic forces of\n                    attraction between oppositely charged cations and anions. The properties of\n                    ionic compounds shed some light on the nature of ionic bonds. Ionic solids\n                    exhibit a crystalline structure and tend to be rigid and brittle; they also tend\n                    to have high melting and boiling points, which suggests that ionic bonds are\n                    very strong. Ionic solids are also poor conductors of electricity for the same\n                    reason\xe2\x80\x94the strength of ionic bonds prevents ions from moving freely in the solid\n                    state. Most ionic solids, however, dissolve readily in water. Once dissolved or\n                    melted, ionic compounds are excellent conductors of electricity and heat because\n                    the ions can move about freely.</p>\n                <p>Neutral atoms and their associated ions have very different physical and chemical\n                    properties. Sodium atoms form sodium metal, a soft, silvery-white metal that\n                    burns vigorously in air and reacts explosively with water. Chlorine atoms form\n                    chlorine gas, Cl<sub>2</sub>, a yellow-green gas that is extremely corrosive to\n                    most metals and very poisonous to animals and plants. The vigorous reaction\n                    between the elements sodium and chlorine forms the white, crystalline compound\n                    sodium chloride, common table salt, which contains sodium cations and chloride\n                    anions. The compound composed of these ions exhibits properties entirely\n                    different from the properties of the elements sodium and chlorine. Chlorine is\n                    poisonous, but sodium chloride is essential to life; sodium atoms react\n                    vigorously with water, but sodium chloride simply dissolves in water.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/ionic_bond.jpg" alt="Three pictures are shown and labeled \xe2\x80\x9ca,\xe2\x80\x9d \xe2\x80\x9cb,\xe2\x80\x9d and \xe2\x80\x9cc,\xe2\x80\x9d from left to right. Image a shows a glass jar with a lid that is full of a clear, colorless liquid in which a silver solid is suspended. Image b depicts a glass bottle with a blue lid that is full of a yellow-green gas. Image c shows a black dish that is full of a white, crystalline solid." width="700">\n                    <caption>(a) Sodium is a soft metal that must be stored in mineral oil to\n                        prevent reaction with air or water. (b) Chlorine is a pale yellow-green gas.\n                        (c) When combined, they form white crystals of sodium chloride (table salt).\n                        (credit a: modification of work by \xe2\x80\x9cJurii\xe2\x80\x9d/Wikimedia Commons)</caption>\n                </image>\n                <p>Binary ionic compounds are composed of just two elements: a metal (which forms\n                    the cations) and a nonmetal (which forms the anions). For example, NaCl is a\n                    binary ionic compound. We can think about the formation of such compounds in\n                    terms of the periodic properties of the elements. Many metallic elements have\n                    relatively low ionization energies and lose electrons easily. The lower the IE\n                    the more easily the atom loses electrons and the more chemically reactive. The\n                    most chemically reactive metals are in the lower left of the periodic table.\n                    Nonmetal atoms have relatively high electron affinities and thus readily gain\n                    electrons lost by metal atoms, thereby filling their valence shells. The most\n                    chemically reactive nonmetals are found in the upper-right corner of the\n                    periodic table not including the noble gases. The noble gases have very high\n                    ionization energies and very low electron affinities. With only a few\n                    exceptions, the noble gases do not form chemical bonds and are extremely\n                    unreactive.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/periodic_table+.png" width="800">\n                    <caption>Fr is the most reactive metal. F is the most reactive nonmetal. The\n                        noble gases are extremely unreactive. </caption>\n                </image>\n                <p>As all substances must be electrically neutral, the total number of positive\n                    charges on the cations of an ionic compound must equal the total number of\n                    negative charges on its anions. The formula of an ionic compound represents the\n                    simplest ratio of the numbers of ions necessary to give identical numbers of\n                    positive and negative charges. For example, the formula for aluminum oxide,\n                        Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, indicates that this ionic compound contains two\n                    aluminum cations, Al<sup>3+</sup>, for every three oxide anions, O<sup>2\xe2\x88\x92</sup>\n                    [thus, (2 \xc3\x97 +3) + (3 \xc3\x97 \xe2\x80\x932) = 0].</p>\n                <p>It is important to note, however, that the formula for an ionic compound does not\n                    represent the physical arrangement of its ions. It is incorrect to refer to a\n                    sodium chloride (NaCl) \xe2\x80\x9cmolecule\xe2\x80\x9d because there is not a single ionic bond, per\n                    se, between any specific pair of sodium and chloride ions. The attractive forces\n                    between ions are isotropic\xe2\x80\x94the same in all directions\xe2\x80\x94meaning that any\n                    particular ion is equally attracted to all of the nearby ions of opposite\n                    charge. This results in the ions arranging themselves into a tightly bound,\n                    three-dimensional lattice structure. Sodium chloride, for example, consists of a\n                    regular arrangement of equal numbers of Na<sup>+</sup> cations and\n                        Cl<sup>\xe2\x80\x93</sup> anions. </p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/nacl_structure.jpg" alt="Two diagrams are shown and labeled \xe2\x80\x9ca\xe2\x80\x9d and \xe2\x80\x9cb.\xe2\x80\x9d Diagram a shows a cube made up of twenty-seven alternating purple and green spheres. The purple spheres are smaller than the green spheres. Diagram b shows the same spheres, but this time, they are spread out and connected in three dimensions by white rods. The purple spheres are labeled \xe2\x80\x9cN superscript postive sign\xe2\x80\x9d while the green are labeled \xe2\x80\x9cC l superscript negative sign.\xe2\x80\x9d" width="500">\n                    <caption>The atoms in sodium chloride (common table salt) are arranged to (a)\n                        maximize opposite charges interacting. The smaller spheres represent sodium\n                        ions, the larger ones represent chloride ions. In the expanded view (b), the\n                        geometry can be seen more clearly. Note that each ion is \xe2\x80\x9cbonded\xe2\x80\x9d to all of\n                        the surrounding ions\xe2\x80\x94six in this case.</caption>\n                </image>\n                <wb:inline idref="ionic_form_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'