b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p1_km_theory" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>The Kinetic-Molecular Theory</title>\n        <objref idref="km_theory"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n        <p><activity_link idref="Periodic_Table" target="new"><em>Reference: The Periodic Table of Elements</em></activity_link></p>\n        <p>The gas laws that we have seen to this point, as well as the ideal gas equation, are\n            empirical, that is, they have been derived from experimental observations. The\n            mathematical forms of these laws closely describe the macroscopic behavior of most gases\n            at pressures less than about 1 or 2 atm. Although the gas laws describe relationships\n            that have been verified by many experiments, they do not tell us why gases follow these\n            relationships.</p>\n        <p>The kinetic molecular theory (KMT) is a simple microscopic model that effectively\n            explains the gas laws described in previous modules of this chapter. This theory is\n            based on the following five postulates described here. (Note: The term \xe2\x80\x9cmolecule\xe2\x80\x9d will\n            be used to refer to the individual chemical species that compose the gas, although some\n            gases are composed of atomic species, for example, the noble gases.)</p>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        <dl>\n            <dt><em>Postulates of the Kinetic Molecular Theory</em></dt>\n            <dd/>\n        </dl>\n        <ol>\n            <li>Gases are composed of molecules that are in continuous motion, travelling in\n                straight lines and changing direction only when they collide with other molecules or\n                with the walls of a container. </li>\n            <li>The molecules composing the gas are negligibly small compared to the distances\n                between them.</li>\n            <li>The pressure exerted by a gas in a container results from collisions between the gas\n                molecules and the container walls.</li>\n            <li>Gas molecules exert no attractive or repulsive forces on each other or the container\n                walls; therefore, their collisions are elastic (do not involve a loss of\n                energy).</li>\n            <li>The average kinetic energy of the gas molecules is proportional to the kelvin\n                temperature of the gas.</li>\n        </ol>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        <p>The test of the KMT and its postulates is its ability to explain and describe the\n            behavior of a gas. The various gas laws can be derived from the assumptions of the KMT,\n            which have led chemists to believe that the assumptions of the theory accurately\n            represent the properties of gas molecules. We will first look at the individual gas laws\n            (Boyle\xe2\x80\x99s, Charles\xe2\x80\x99s, Gay-Lussac\'s, Avogadro\xe2\x80\x99s, and Dalton\xe2\x80\x99s laws) conceptually to see\n            how the KMT explains them. Then, we will more carefully consider the relationships\n            between molecular masses, speeds, and kinetic energies with temperature, and explain\n            Graham\xe2\x80\x99s law. </p>\n        <p>Recalling that gas pressure is exerted by rapidly moving gas molecules and depends\n            directly on the number of molecules hitting a unit area of the wall per unit of time, we\n            see that the KMT conceptually explains the behavior of a gas. In the following series of\n            activities use your knowledge of the gas laws to answer the following questions, thereby\n            making the connection as to how the KMT explains the observations that result in the gas\n            laws.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/kmt_gas_laws.jpg" alt="This figure shows 3 pairs of pistons and cylinders. In a, which is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cCharles\xe2\x80\x99s Law,\xe2\x80\x9d the piston is positioned for the first cylinder so that just over half of the available volume contains 6 purple spheres with trails behind them. The trails indicate movement. Orange dashes extend from the interior surface of the cylinder where the spheres have collided. This cylinder is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cBaseline.\xe2\x80\x9d In the second cylinder, the piston is in the same position, and the label, \xe2\x80\x9cHeat\xe2\x80\x9d is indicated in red capitalized text. Four red arrows with wavy stems are pointing upward to the base of the cylinder. The six purple spheres have longer trails behind them and the number of orange dashes indicating points of collision with the container walls has increased. A rectangle beneath the diagram states, \xe2\x80\x9cTemperature increased, Volume constant equals Increased pressure.\xe2\x80\x9d In b, which is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cBoyle\xe2\x80\x99s Law,\xe2\x80\x9d the first, baseline cylinder shown is identical to the first cylinder in a. In the second cylinder, the piston has been moved, decreasing the volume available to the 6 purple spheres to half of the initial volume. The six purple spheres have longer trails behind them and the number of orange dashes indicating points of collision with the container walls has increased. This second cylinder is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cVolume decreased.\xe2\x80\x9d A rectangle beneath the diagram states, \xe2\x80\x9cVolume decreased, Wall area decreased equals Increased pressure.\xe2\x80\x9d In c, which is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cAvogadro\xe2\x80\x99s Law,\xe2\x80\x9d the first, baseline cylinder shown is identical to the first cylinder in a. In the second cylinder, the number of purple spheres has changed from 6 to 12 and volume has doubled. This second cylinder is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cIncreased gas.\xe2\x80\x9d A rectangle beneath the diagram states, \xe2\x80\x9cAt constant pressure, More gas molecules added equals Increased volume.\xe2\x80\x9d" width="700">\n            <caption>(a) When gas temperature increases, gas pressure increases due to increased\n                force and frequency of molecular collisions. (b) When volume decreases, gas pressure\n                increases due to increased frequency of molecular collisions. (c) When the amount of\n                gas increases at a constant pressure, volume increases to yield a constant number of\n                collisions per unit wall area per unit time.</caption>\n        </image>\n\n        <wb:inline idref="kmt_digt_p1" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n                href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'