b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p1_phase_change" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Phase Changes</title>\n        <objref idref="phase_change_imf"/>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n        <p><activity_link idref="Periodic_Table" target="new"><em>Reference: The Periodic Table of Elements</em></activity_link></p>\n        <section>\n            <title>Vaporization and Condensation</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>When a liquid is heated the kinetic energy of its atoms, molecules, or ions\n                    increases. At some point the KE is great enough to overcome the forces holding\n                    the substance together in the liquid phase and the particles escape into the gas\n                    phase. This is called vaporization. If a gaseous substance is cooled, at some\n                    point, it will change into its liquid phase. This is known as condensation.</p>\n\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <section>\n            <title>Melting and Freezing</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>When we heat a crystalline solid, we increase the average energy of its atoms,\n                    molecules, or ions and the solid gets hotter. At some point, the added energy\n                    becomes large enough to partially overcome the forces holding the molecules or\n                    ions of the solid in their fixed positions, and the solid begins the process of\n                    transitioning to the liquid state, or melting. If we cool a liquid, the kinetic\n                    energy decreases. At some point, the IMFs will become greater than the KE and\n                    the substance will be held tightly together in a fixed position, which we call\n                    freezing. </p>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n\n        <section>\n            <title>Sublimation and Deposition</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>Some solids can transition directly into the gaseous state, bypassing the liquid\n                    state, via a process known as sublimation. At room temperature and standard\n                    pressure, a piece of dry ice (solid CO<sub>2</sub>) sublimes, appearing to\n                    gradually disappear without ever forming any liquid. \n                    When solid iodine is warmed, the solid sublimes and a vivid purple vapor forms\n                    as seen in the image below. The reverse of sublimation is called deposition, a process in which\n                    gaseous substances condense directly into the solid state, bypassing the liquid\n                    state. The formation of frost is an example of deposition.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_10_03_Sublimtn.jpg" alt="This figure shows a test tube. In the bottom is a dark substance which breaks up into a purple gas at the top." width="200">\n                    <caption>Sublimation of solid iodine in the bottom of the tube produces a purple\n                        gas that subsequently deposits as solid iodine on the colder part of the\n                        tube above. (credit: modification of work by Mark Ott)</caption>\n                </image>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <wb:inline idref="phase_change_dnd_question" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry </link>under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n        \n             \n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'