b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\r\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\r\n<workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/"\r\n\txmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\r\n\txmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\r\n\txmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\r\n\txmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="p2_classMatter">\r\n\t<head>\r\n\t\t<title>Classification of Matter</title>\r\n\t\t<objref idref="classify_matter"/>\r\n\t</head>\r\n\t<body>\r\n\t\t<section id="eb3fc9320e9b441db93d320b938c27b4">\r\n\t\t\t<title>Atoms and Molecules</title>\r\n\t\t\t<body>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="d136e6c3c82049fe8b3445e3acd2ac0d">An <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>atom</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>The smallest particle of an element that retains the properties\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tof that element.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra> is the smallest particle of an element that has the properties of that\r\n\t\t\t\t\telement and can enter into a chemical combination. Consider the element gold,\r\n\t\t\t\t\tfor example. Imagine cutting a gold nugget in half, then cutting one of the\r\n\t\t\t\t\thalves in half, and repeating this process until a piece of gold remained that\r\n\t\t\t\t\twas so small that it could not be cut in half (regardless of how tiny your knife\r\n\t\t\t\t\tmay be). This minimally sized piece of gold is an atom (from the Greek atomos,\r\n\t\t\t\t\tmeaning \xe2\x80\x9cindivisible\xe2\x80\x9d). This atom would no longer be gold if it were divided any\r\n\t\t\t\t\tfurther.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<image id="ca5d2d8a2f28433eb6be7adba27a4390" src="../webcontent/gold_atom.jpg"\r\n\t\t\t\t\talt="Figure A shows a gold nugget as it would appear to the naked eye. The gold nugget is very irregular, with many sharp edges. It appears gold in color. The microscope image of a gold crystal shows many similarly sized gold stripes that are separated by dark areas. Looking closely, one can see that the gold stripes are made of many, tiny, circular atoms."\r\n\t\t\t\t\tstyle="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600">\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<caption>(a) This photograph shows a gold nugget. (b) A scanning-tunneling\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tmicroscope (STM) can generate views of the surfaces of solids, such as this\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\timage of a gold crystal. Each sphere represents one gold atom. (credit a:\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tmodification of work by United States Geological Survey; credit b:\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tmodification of work by \xe2\x80\x9cErwinrossen\xe2\x80\x9d/Wikimedia Commons)</caption>\r\n\t\t\t<!--<popout enable="true"/>-->\r\n\t\t\t\t</image>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="ca1ff76db26b432e93106be4291520ff">An atom is so small that its size is\r\n\t\t\t\t\tdifficult to imagine. One of the smallest things we can see with our unaided eye\r\n\t\t\t\t\tis a single thread of a spider web: These strands are about 1/10,000 of a\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcentimeter (0.0001 cm) in diameter. Although the cross-section of one strand is\r\n\t\t\t\t\talmost impossible to see without a microscope, it is huge on an atomic scale. A\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsingle carbon atom in the web has a diameter of about 0.000000015 centimeter,\r\n\t\t\t\t\tand it would take about 7000 carbon atoms to span the diameter of the strand. To\r\n\t\t\t\t\tput this in perspective, if a carbon atom were the size of a dime, the\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcross-section of one strand would be larger than a football field, which would\r\n\t\t\t\t\trequire about 150 million carbon atom \xe2\x80\x9cdimes\xe2\x80\x9d to cover it.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="c136e7ea924c4ab3b1f783225eaa8fed"> The mass of an atom is also difficult to\r\n\t\t\t\t\timagine. A billion lead atoms (1,000,000,000 atoms) weigh about 3 \xc3\x97 10\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<sup>-13</sup> grams, a mass that is far too light to be weighed on even the\r\n\t\t\t\t\tworld\xe2\x80\x99s most sensitive balances. It would require over 300,000,000,000,000 lead\r\n\t\t\t\t\tatoms (300 trillion, or 3 \xc3\x97 10 <sup>14</sup> ) to be weighed, and they would\r\n\t\t\t\t\tweigh only 0.0000001 gram. </p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="d60758ce159b47588eeec4f436eafd02">It is rare to find collections of\r\n\t\t\t\t\tindividual atoms. Only a few elements, such as the gases helium, neon, and\r\n\t\t\t\t\targon, consist of a collection of individual atoms that move about independently\r\n\t\t\t\t\tof one another. Other elements, such as the gases hydrogen, nitrogen, oxygen,\r\n\t\t\t\t\tand chlorine, are composed of units that consist of pairs of atoms. One form of\r\n\t\t\t\t\tthe element phosphorus consists of units composed of four phosphorus atoms. The\r\n\t\t\t\t\telement sulfur exists in various forms, one of which consists of units composed\r\n\t\t\t\t\tof eight sulfur atoms. These units are called molecules. A <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>molecule</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>Two or more atoms joined together by chemical bonds.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra> consists of two or more atoms joined by strong forces called chemical\r\n\t\t\t\t\tbonds. The atoms in a molecule move around as a unit, much like the cans of soda\r\n\t\t\t\t\tin a six-pack or a bunch of keys joined together on a single key ring. A\r\n\t\t\t\t\tmolecule may consist of two or more identical atoms, as in the molecules found\r\n\t\t\t\t\tin the elements hydrogen, oxygen, and sulfur, or it may consist of two or more\r\n\t\t\t\t\tdifferent atoms, as in the molecules found in water. Each water molecule is a\r\n\t\t\t\t\tunit that contains two hydrogen atoms and one oxygen atom. Each glucose molecule\r\n\t\t\t\t\tis a unit that contains 6 carbon atoms, 12 hydrogen atoms, and 6 oxygen atoms.\r\n\t\t\t\t\tLike atoms, molecules are incredibly small and light. If an ordinary glass of\r\n\t\t\t\t\twater were enlarged to the size of the earth, the water molecules inside it\r\n\t\t\t\t\twould be about the size of golf balls.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<image id="e40d87bb90994035949a27ffc1f006b5" src="../webcontent/molecules.jpg"\r\n\t\t\t\t\talt="The hydrogen molecule, H subscript 2, is shown as two small, white balls bonded together. The oxygen molecule O subscript 2, is shown as two red balls bonded together. The phosphorous molecule, P subscript 4, is shown as four orange balls bonded tightly together. The sulfur molecule, S subscript 8, is shown as 8 yellow balls linked together. Water molecules, H subscript 2 O, consist of one red oxygen atom bonded to two smaller white hydrogen atoms. The hydrogen atoms are at an angle on the oxygen molecule. Carbon dioxide, C O subscript 2, consists of one carbon atom and two oxygen atoms. One oxygen atom is bonded to the carbon\xe2\x80\x99s right side and the other oxygen is bonded to the carbon\xe2\x80\x99s left side. Glucose, C subscript 6 H subscript 12 O subscript 6, contains a chain of carbon atoms that have attached oxygen or hydrogen atoms."\r\n\t\t\t\t\tstyle="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600">\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<caption>The elements hydrogen, oxygen, phosphorus, and sulfur form molecules\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tconsisting of two or more atoms of the same element. The compounds water,\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tcarbon dioxide, and glucose consist of combinations of atoms of different\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\telements.</caption>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<!--<popout enable="true"/>-->\r\n\t\t\t\t</image>\r\n\t\t\t\t<wb:inline idref="atoms_molecules_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\r\n\t\t\t</body>\r\n\t\t</section>\r\n\t\t<section id="f0feae5457fc4e0fa3b16e99463dc64e">\r\n\t\t\t<title>Classifying Matter</title>\r\n\t\t\t<body>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="c25bcc1c07854bcb8027e1e27b5ee6cd">We can classify matter into several\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcategories. Two broad categories are mixtures and pure substances. A <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>pure substance</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>A substance that has a constant composition.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra> has a constant composition. All specimens of a pure substance have\r\n\t\t\t\t\texactly the same makeup and properties. Any sample of sucrose (table sugar)\r\n\t\t\t\t\tconsists of 42.1% carbon, 6.5% hydrogen, and 51.4% oxygen by mass. Any sample of\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsucrose also has the same physical properties, such as melting point, color, and\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsweetness, regardless of the source from which it is isolated.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="ab2e4f6b305d4eb6ad39e8efce633b44">We can divide pure substances into two\r\n\t\t\t\t\tclasses: elements and compounds. Pure substances that cannot be broken down into\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsimpler substances by chemical changes are called <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>elements</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>Pure substances that cannot be broken down into simpler\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tsubstances by chemical changes.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra>. Iron, silver, gold, aluminum, sulfur, oxygen, and copper are familiar\r\n\t\t\t\t\texamples of the more than 100 known elements, of which about 90 occur naturally\r\n\t\t\t\t\ton the earth, and two dozen or so have been created in laboratories. All\r\n\t\t\t\t\telements are listed on the Periodic Table of Elements as seen below. It is\r\n\t\t\t\t\tlikely that you are familiar with many of these elements, but not all. We will\r\n\t\t\t\t\tdiscuss the Periodic Table in much more detail a little later in this\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcourse.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<image id="b2d78c18b60144628f9be91bcdd5c6cf" src="../webcontent/periodic_table.jpg"\r\n\t\t\t\t\talt="On this depiction of the periodic table, the metals are indicated with a yellow color and dominate the left two thirds of the periodic table. The nonmetals are colored peach and are largely confined to the upper right area of the table, with the exception of hydrogen, H, which is located in the extreme upper left of the table. The metalloids are colored purple and form a diagonal border between the metal and nonmetal areas of the table. Group 13 contains both metals and metalloids. Group 17 contains both nonmetals and metalloids. Groups 14 through 16 contain at least one representative of a metal, a metalloid, and a nonmetal. A key shows that, at room temperature, metals are solids, metalloids are liquids, and nonmetals are gases."\r\n\t\t\t\t\tstyle="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600">\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<caption/>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<!--<popout enable="true"/>-->\r\n\t\t\t\t</image>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="d7c4abea16e540b2a0d6a4b6c9a2ca8d">Pure substances that can be broken down by\r\n\t\t\t\t\tchemical changes are called <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>compounds</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>Pure substances that can be broken down into simpler substances\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tby chemical changes.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra>. This breakdown may produce either elements or other compounds, or\r\n\t\t\t\t\tboth. Mercury(II) oxide, an orange, crystalline solid, can be broken down by\r\n\t\t\t\t\theat into the elements mercury and oxygen as seen below. When heated in the\r\n\t\t\t\t\tabsence of air, the compound sucrose is broken down into the element carbon and\r\n\t\t\t\t\tthe compound water.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<image id="d06da83e26e54c36b5913367007b55ec"\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsrc="../webcontent/mercury_breakdown.jpg"\r\n\t\t\t\t\talt="This figure shows a series of three photos labeled a, b, and c. Photo a shows the bottom of a test tube that is filled with an orange-red substance. A slight amount of a silver substance is also visible. Photo b shows the substance in the test tube being heated over a flame. Photo c shows a test tube that is not longer being heated. The orange-red substance is almost completely gone, and small, silver droplets of a substance are left."\r\n\t\t\t\t\tstyle="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600">\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<caption>(a)The compound mercury(II) oxide, (b)when heated, (c) decomposes into\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tsilvery droplets of liquid mercury and invisible oxygen gas. (credit:\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tmodification of work by Paul Flowers)</caption>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<!--<popout enable="true"/>-->\r\n\t\t\t\t</image>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="be0f1f4d6b3a400bb48299b4e6c832bd">The properties of combined elements are\r\n\t\t\t\t\tdifferent from those in the free, or uncombined, state. For example, white\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcrystalline sugar (sucrose) is a compound resulting from the chemical\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcombination of the element carbon, which is a black solid in one of its\r\n\t\t\t\t\tuncombined forms, and the two elements hydrogen and oxygen, which are colorless\r\n\t\t\t\t\tgases when uncombined. Free sodium, an element that is a soft, shiny, metallic\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsolid, and free chlorine, an element that is a yellow-green gas, combine to form\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsodium chloride (table salt), a compound that is a white, crystalline solid.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<wb:inline idref="element_compound_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\r\n\t\t\t</body>\r\n\t\t</section>\r\n\t\t<section id="aeafad84f01640acb6081d144f083974">\r\n\t\t\t<title>Mixtures</title>\r\n\t\t\t<body>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="e9ddedfc061242269dad5a8fe20feb56">A <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>mixture</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>Substance composed of two or more types of matter that can be\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tpresent in varying amounts and can be separated by physical\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tchanges.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra> is composed of two or more types of matter that can be present in\r\n\t\t\t\t\tvarying amounts and can be separated by physical changes, such as evaporation\r\n\t\t\t\t\t(you will learn more about this later). A mixture with a composition that varies\r\n\t\t\t\t\tfrom point to point is called a <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>heterogeneous mixture</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>A mixture with a composition that varies from point to point and\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\ttherefore has visibly different parts.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra>. Italian dressing is an example of a heterogeneous mixture, as seen in\r\n\t\t\t\t\tthe image on left below. Its composition can vary because we can make it from\r\n\t\t\t\t\tvarying amounts of oil, vinegar, and herbs. It is not the same from point to\r\n\t\t\t\t\tpoint throughout the mixture\xe2\x80\x94one drop may be mostly vinegar, whereas a different\r\n\t\t\t\t\tdrop may be mostly oil or herbs because the oil and vinegar separate and the\r\n\t\t\t\t\therbs settle to the bottom of the container. Other examples of heterogeneous mixtures are chocolate chip\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcookies (we can see the separate bits of chocolate, nuts, and cookie dough) and\r\n\t\t\t\t\tgranite (we can see the quartz, mica, feldspar, and more).</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="e6a8599a81fb43939eff641c1cb04728">A <extra>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<anchor>homogeneous mixture</anchor>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t<meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t<p>A mixture that has a uniform composition and appears visually the\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tsame throughout.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</material>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\t</meaning>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t</extra>, also called a solution, exhibits a uniform composition and appears\r\n\t\t\t\t\tvisually the same throughout. An example of a solution is a sports drink,\r\n\t\t\t\t\tconsisting of water, sugar, coloring, flavoring, and electrolytes mixed together\r\n\t\t\t\t\tuniformly. Each drop of a sports drink tastes the same because each drop\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcontains the same amounts of water, sugar, and other components. Note that the\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcomposition of a sports drink can vary\xe2\x80\x94it could be made with somewhat more or\r\n\t\t\t\t\tless sugar, flavoring, or other components, and still be a sports drink. Other\r\n\t\t\t\t\texamples of homogeneous mixtures include air, maple syrup, gasoline, and a\r\n\t\t\t\t\tsolution of salt in water.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<image id="ce0ff54abd5a4376ae466a6beb811dbc" src="../webcontent/mixtures.jpg"\r\n\t\t\t\t\talt="Diagram A shows a glass containing a red liquid with a layer of yellow oil floating on the surface of the red liquid. A zoom in box is magnifying a portion of the red liquid that contains some of the yellow oil. The zoomed in image shows that oil is forming round droplets within the red liquid. Diagram B shows a photo of Gatorade G 2. A zoom in box is magnifying a portion of the Gatorade, which is uniformly red."\r\n\t\t\t\t\tstyle="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600">\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<caption>(a) Oil and vinegar salad dressing is a heterogeneous mixture because\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tits composition is not uniform throughout. (b) A commercial sports drink is\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\ta homogeneous mixture because its composition is uniform throughout. (credit\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\ta \xe2\x80\x9cleft\xe2\x80\x9d: modification of work by John Mayer; credit a \xe2\x80\x9cright\xe2\x80\x9d: modification\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tof work by Umberto Salvagnin; credit b \xe2\x80\x9cleft: modification of work by Jeff\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tBedford)</caption>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<!--<popout enable="true"/>-->\r\n\t\t\t\t</image>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="d8725048257b431b96e4971c1460a864">Although there are just over 100 elements,\r\n\t\t\t\t\ttens of millions of chemical compounds result from different combinations of\r\n\t\t\t\t\tthese elements. Each compound has a specific composition and possesses definite\r\n\t\t\t\t\tchemical and physical properties by which we can distinguish it from all other\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcompounds. And, of course, there are innumerable ways to combine elements and\r\n\t\t\t\t\tcompounds to form different mixtures.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<composite_activity>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<p>Drag the terms from the bottom of the activity into their appropriate\r\n\t\t\t\t\t\tposition in the flowchart below.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t\t<iframe src="https://h5p.org/h5p/embed/196512" width="800" height="509"/>\r\n\r\n\t\t\t\t</composite_activity>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="d75a90e7e82a4218b08a46b515383c1c">Eleven elements make up about 99% of the\r\n\t\t\t\t\tearth\xe2\x80\x99s crust and atmosphere. Oxygen constitutes nearly one-half and silicon\r\n\t\t\t\t\tabout one-quarter of the total quantity of these elements. A majority of\r\n\t\t\t\t\telements on earth are found in chemical combinations with other elements; about\r\n\t\t\t\t\tone-quarter of the elements are also found in the free state.</p>\r\n\t\t\t\t<p id="ab69e71192b6f4e1c94d5462c501738ce"/>\r\n\t\t\t\t<wb:inline idref="compound_mixture_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\r\n\t\t\t\t<wb:inline idref="compound_mixture_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\r\n\t\t\t</body>\r\n\t\t</section>\r\n\t\t<p id="b4f08e5e35e9473caa7920af45f1dc6a"> Adapted from <link\r\n\t\t\t\thref="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface" target="self"\r\n\t\t\t\tinternal="false">Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\r\n\t\t\t\thref="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" target="self" internal="false"\r\n\t\t\t\t>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License.</link>\r\n\t\t</p>\r\n\t\t<p id="b1d9f0120f4c4c9dab1a9089a20f5127"> Download for free at <link\r\n\t\t\t\thref="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\r\n\t\t\t\ttarget="self" internal="false"\r\n\t\t\t\t>http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link>\r\n\t\t</p>\r\n\t\t<p id="ae2f1b79e51dc40ffad9d9fbf4ba5ad2f"/>\r\n\t</body>\r\n</workbook_page>\r\n'