b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p2_quantum_mech" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n    \n    \n    <head>\n        <title>Quantum Mechanics</title>\n        <objref idref="quantum_model"/>\n        \n    </head>\n    \n    <body>\n        <section>\n            <title>The Uncertainty Principle</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>Werner Heisenberg considered the limits of how accurately we can measure\n                    properties of an electron or other microscopic particles. He determined that\n                    there is a fundamental limit to how accurately one can measure both a particle\xe2\x80\x99s\n                    position and its momentum simultaneously. The more accurately we measure the\n                    momentum of a particle, the less accurately we can determine its position at\n                    that time, and vice versa. This is summed up in what we now call the Heisenberg\n                    uncertainty principle.</p>\n                <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"/>\n                <dl>\n                    <dt><em>The Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle</em></dt>\n                    <dd/>\n                </dl>\n                <p> It is fundamentally impossible to determine simultaneously and exactly both the\n                    momentum and the position of a particle.</p>\n                <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"/>\n                \n                <p>For a particle of mass m moving with velocity <em style="italic"\n                    >v</em><sub>x</sub> in the x direction (or equivalently with momentum <em\n                        style="italic">p</em><sub>x</sub>), the product of the uncertainty in the\n                    position, \xce\x94x, and the uncertainty in the momentum, \xce\x94p<sub>x</sub>, must be\n                    greater than or equal to \\(\\frac{\\mathit\xe2\x84\x8f}{\\mathit2}\\) (recall that\n                    \\(\\mathit\xe2\x84\x8f=\\;\\frac h{2\\pi}\\), the value of Planck\xe2\x80\x99s constant divided by 2\xcf\x80).</p>\n                <p><formula>$$\\Delta x \\times \\Delta p_x = (\\Delta x)(m \\Delta v) \\geq\n                    \\frac{\\hbar}2$$</formula></p>\n                <p>This equation allows us to calculate the limit to how precisely we can know both\n                    the simultaneous position of an object and its momentum. For example, if we\n                    improve our measurement of an electron\xe2\x80\x99s position so that the uncertainty in the\n                    position (\xce\x94<em style="italic">x</em>) has a value of, say, 1 pm\n                    (10<sup>-12</sup> m, about 1% of the diameter of a hydrogen atom), then our\n                    determination of its momentum must have an uncertainty with a value of at\n                    least</p>\n                <p><formula>$$\\left[ \\Delta p = m \\Delta v = \\frac{h}{2 \\Delta x} \\right] =\n                    \\frac{(1.055 \\times 10^{-34} \\mathrm{kg}\\\n                    \\mathrm{m}^2/\\mathrm{s})}{(2\\times1\\times10^{-12}\\mathrm{m})} = 5 \\times\n                    10^{-23} \\mathrm{kg}\\ \\mathrm{m/s}$$</formula></p>\n                <p>The value of h is not large, so the uncertainty in the position or momentum of a\n                    macroscopic object like a baseball is too insignificant to observe. However, the\n                    mass of a microscopic object such as an electron is small enough that the\n                    uncertainty can be large and significant.</p>\n                <p>Heisenberg\xe2\x80\x99s principle imposes ultimate limits on what is knowable in science.\n                    The uncertainty principle can be shown to be a consequence of wave\xe2\x80\x93particle\n                    duality, which lies at the heart of what distinguishes modern quantum theory\n                    from classical mechanics. Recall that the equations of motion obtained from\n                    classical mechanics are trajectories where, at any given instant in time, both\n                    the position and the momentum of a particle can be determined exactly.\n                    Heisenberg\xe2\x80\x99s uncertainty principle implies that such a view is untenable in the\n                    microscopic domain and that there are fundamental limitations governing the\n                    motion of quantum particles. This does not mean that microscopic particles do\n                    not move in trajectories, it is just that measurements of trajectories are\n                    limited in their precision. In the realm of <extra>\n                        <anchor>quantum mechanics</anchor>\n                        <meaning>\n                            <material>\n                                <p>field of study that includes quantization of energy,\n                                    wave-particle duality, and the Heisenberg uncertainty principle\n                                    to describe matter</p>\n                            </material>\n                        </meaning>\n                    </extra>, measurements introduce changes into the system that is being\n                    observed.</p>\n                <wb:inline idref="heisenberg_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <section>\n            <title>The Quantum\xe2\x80\x93Mechanical Model of an Atom</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>Shortly after de Broglie published his ideas that the electron in a hydrogen atom\n                    could be better thought of as being a circular standing wave instead of a\n                    particle moving in quantized circular orbits, as Bohr had argued, Erwin\n                    Schr\xc3\xb6dinger extended de Broglie\xe2\x80\x99s work by incorporating the de Broglie relation\n                    into a wave equation, deriving what is today known as the Schr\xc3\xb6dinger equation.\n                    When Schr\xc3\xb6dinger applied his equation to hydrogen-like atoms, he was able to\n                    reproduce Bohr\xe2\x80\x99s expression for the energy and, thus, the Rydberg formula\n                    governing hydrogen spectra, and he did so without having to invoke Bohr\xe2\x80\x99s\n                    assumptions of stationary states and quantized orbits, angular momenta, and\n                    energies; quantization in Schr\xc3\xb6dinger\xe2\x80\x99s theory was a natural consequence of the\n                    underlying mathematics of the wave equation.</p>\n                <p>Like de Broglie, Schr\xc3\xb6dinger initially viewed the electron in hydrogen as being a\n                    physical wave instead of a particle, but where de Broglie thought of the\n                    electron in terms of circular stationary waves, Schr\xc3\xb6dinger properly thought in\n                    terms of three-dimensional stationary waves, or wavefunctions, represented by\n                    the Greek letter psi, \xcf\x88. A few years later, Max Born proposed an interpretation\n                    of the <extra>\n                        <anchor>wavefunction \xcf\x88</anchor>\n                        <meaning>\n                            <material>\n                                <p>mathematical description of an atomic orbital that describes the\n                                    shape of the orbital; it can be used to calculate the\n                                    probability of finding the electron at any given location in the\n                                    orbital, as well as dynamical variables such as the energy and\n                                    the angular momentum</p>\n                            </material>\n                        </meaning>\n                    </extra> that is still accepted today: Electrons are still particles, and so the\n                    waves represented by \xcf\x88 are not physical waves but, instead, are complex\n                    probability amplitudes. The square of the magnitude of a wavefunction\n                    \xe2\x88\xa3\xcf\x88\xe2\x88\xa3<sup>2</sup> describes the probability of the quantum particle being\n                    present near a certain location in space. This means that wavefunctions can be\n                    used to determine the distribution of the electron\xe2\x80\x99s density with respect to the\n                    nucleus in an atom. The general form of the Schr\xc3\xb6dinger equation is seen\n                    below.</p>\n                <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"/>\n                <dl>\n                    <dt><em>The Schr\xc3\xb6dinger Equation</em></dt>\n                    <dd> $$\\overbrace H\\psi=\\;E\\psi$$ <p>\\(\\overbrace H\\) is the Hamiltonian\n                        operator, a set of mathematical operations representing the total energy\n                        of the quantum particle (such as an electron in an atom), \xcf\x88 is the\n                        wavefunction of this particle that can be used to find the special\n                        distribution of the probability of finding the particle, and <em style="italic">E</em> is the\n                        actual value of the total energy of the particle.</p>\n                    </dd>\n                </dl>\n                \n                <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"/>\n                \n                <p>Schr\xc3\xb6dinger\xe2\x80\x99s work, as well as that of Heisenberg and many other scientists\n                    following in their footsteps, is generally referred to as quantum mechanics.</p>\n                <wb:inline idref="quantum_mech_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="http://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0\n                License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'