b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p2_the_mole" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>The Mole</title>\n        <objref idref="convert_moles"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <section id="p2_the_mole_DE1">\n           <title></title>\n           <body> <p>The <extra><anchor>mole</anchor><meaning><material><p>amount of substance containing the same number of atoms, molecules, ions, or other entities as the number of atoms in exactly 12 grams of C-12</p></material></meaning></extra> is an amount unit similar to familiar units like pair, dozen, gross, etc. It\n            provides a specific measure of the number of atoms or molecules in a bulk sample of\n            matter. A mole is defined as the amount of substance containing the same number of\n            discrete entities (such as atoms, molecules, and ions) as the number of atoms in a\n            sample of pure <sup>12</sup>C weighing exactly 12 g. <em style="bold">The mole provides\n                a link between an easily measured macroscopic property, bulk mass, and an extremely\n                important fundamental property, number of atoms, molecules, and so forth.</em>\n        </p>\n\n        <p>The number of entities composing a mole is defined to be\n            6.02214179&times;10<sup>23</sup>, a fundamental constant named <extra><anchor>Avogadro\xe2\x80\x99s number\n                (N<sub>A</sub>)</anchor><meaning><material><p>defined value of the number of entities comprising 1 mole of substance, equal to 6.022 \xc3\x97 10<sup>23</sup> per mole</p></material></meaning></extra> or the Avogadro constant in honor of Italian scientist Amedeo\n            Avogadro. This constant is properly reported with an explicit unit of \xe2\x80\x9cper mole,\xe2\x80\x9d a\n            conveniently rounded version being 6.022&times;10<sup>23</sup>/mol. </p>\n\n        <p> Consistent with its definition as an amount unit, 1 mole of any element contains the\n            same number of atoms as 1 mole of any other element. For example 1 mole of carbon\n            contains 6.022&times;10<sup>23</sup> atoms of carbon and 1 mole of phosphorus contains 6.022&times;10<sup>23</sup>\n             atoms of phosphorus. The masses of 1 mole of different elements,\n            however, are different, since the masses of the individual atoms are drastically\n            different. The <extra><anchor>molar mass</anchor><meaning><material><p>mass in grams of 1 mole of a substance</p></material></meaning></extra> of an element (or compound) is the mass in grams of 1 mole of\n            that substance, a property expressed in units of grams per mole (g/mol). Because the\n            definitions of both the mole and the atomic mass unit are based on the same reference\n            substance, <sup>12</sup>C, the molar mass of any substance is numerically equivalent to\n            its atomic or formula weight in amu. The molar mass of carbon is 12.01 g/mol (same value\n            as its atomic mass) and the molar mass of phosphorus is 30.97 g/mol (same value as its\n            atomic mass).</p></body></section>\n\n        <wb:inline idref="mole_lbd_1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n\n        <section id="p2_the_mole_DE2">\n          <title></title>\n          <body>  <p>While atomic mass and molar mass are numerically equivalent, keep in mind that they are\n            vastly different in terms of scale, as represented by the vast difference in the\n            magnitudes of their respective units (amu versus g). To appreciate the enormity of the\n            mole, consider a small drop of water weighing about 0.03 g. Although this represents\n            just a tiny fraction of 1 mole of water (approximately 18 g), it contains more water\n            molecules than can be clearly imagined. If the molecules were distributed equally among\n            the roughly seven billion people on earth, each person would receive more than 100\n            billion molecules.</p></body></section>\n\n        <section id="p2_the_mole_DE3">\n            <title>Molar Mass of Compounds</title>\n            <body>\n\n                <p>As we discussed, the molar mass of an element is numerically the same value as\n                    the atomic mass of that element listed on the periodic table. Likewise, the\n                    molar mass of a compound is numerically the same value as the formula mass for\n                    that compound. For example, the formula mass of NaCl is 58.44 amu. Therefore the\n                    molar mass of NaCl is 58.44 g and the number of NaCl units is 6.022&times;10<sup>23</sup>.\n                         The formula mass of water H<sub>2</sub>O is 18.02 amu.\n                    Therefore the molar mass of water is 18.02 g and the number of water molecules\n                    in one mole of water is 6.022&times;10<sup>23</sup>. </p>\n\n                <p>*Note that one unit of a molecular(covalent) compound is referred to as a\n                    molecule. However, one unit of a ionic compound is referred to as a formula\n                    unit. </p>\n                \n                <wb:inline idref="mole_lbd_2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n                \n                <wb:inline idref="mole_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n                \n                <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                    >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                        href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                        4.0 License. </link></p>\n                <p>Download for free at <link\n                    href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                    >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n\n\n            </body>\n        </section>\n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'