b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p3_imf_intro" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Intermolecular Forces Introduction</title>\n        <objref idref="describe_imf"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n      \n          \n\n                <p> We saw on the previous page that the conditions under which phase changes occur\n                    for ionic compounds are determined by the strength of the ionic bond that holds\n                    the ions together. For molecular compounds, it is strength of intermolecular forces (IMFs) that affect the\n                    conditions under which phase changes occur. In the rest of this module, we will explore three types of intermolecular forces:\n                <ul>\n                    <li>Dispersion Forces</li>\n                    <li>Dipole-dipole Attractions</li>\n                    <li>Hydrogen Bonding</li>\n                </ul>\n                </p>\n                    \n             \n            \n\n        <section>\n            <title>Intermolecular forces and Covalent Bonds</title>\n\n            <body>\n\n                <p> Under appropriate conditions, the attractions between all gas molecules will\n                    cause them to form liquids or solids. This is due to <em>inter</em>molecular forces, not\n                    <em>intra</em>molecular forces. Intramolecular forces are those within the molecule that\n                    keep the molecule together, the covalent bonds between the atoms discussed\n                    previously in this course. Intermolecular forces are the attractions between\n                    molecules, which determine many of the physical properties of a substance. The\n                    diagram below illustrates these different molecular forces. The IMFs that exist\n                    between molecules are weak compared to the intramolecular forces (covalent\n                    bonds) that bond atoms together within a molecule. For example, to overcome the\n                    IMFs in one mole of liquid HCl and convert it into gaseous HCl requires only\n                    about 17 kilojoules. However, to break the covalent bonds between the hydrogen\n                    and chlorine atoms in one mole of HCl requires about 25 times more energy\xe2\x80\x94430\n                    kilojoules.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/interVintra.jpg"\n                    alt="An image is shown in which two molecules composed of a green sphere labeled \xe2\x80\x9cC l\xe2\x80\x9d connected on the right to a white sphere labeled \xe2\x80\x9cH\xe2\x80\x9d are near one another with a dotted line labeled \xe2\x80\x9cIntermolecular force ( weak )\xe2\x80\x9d drawn between them. A line connects the two spheres in each molecule and the line is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cIntramolecular force ( strong ).\xe2\x80\x9d" width="500">\n                    <caption>Intramolecular forces keep a molecule intact. Intermolecular forces\n                        hold multiple molecules together and determine many of a substance\xe2\x80\x99s\n                        properties.</caption>\n                </image>\n                <p>The conditions under which a phase change occurs for a molecular substance is\n                    determined by the strength of its IMF(s). The relative strengths of the covalent\n                    bonds of a molecular substance have no impact on melting point or boiling\n                    point.</p>\n\n\n\n\n                <composite_activity purpose="learnbydoing">\n                    <p>Watch the videos. For each of the processes that is occurring,\n                        determine which type of attractive force is being broken and the energy\n                        required to overcome that force.</p>\n                    <materials>\n                       \n                        <material>\n                            <video src="../webcontent/electrolysis.mp4" width="300" height="200">\n                                <title>Electrolysis of Water</title>\n                            </video>\n                        </material>\n                        <material>\n                            <video src="../webcontent/boil.mp4" width="300" height="200">\n                                <title>Boiling of Water</title>\n                            </video>\n                        </material>\n                    </materials>\n                    <wb:inline idref="imf_dnd_question"/>\n\n                </composite_activity>\n\n            </body>\n        </section>\n\n\n\n\n\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                >Openstax Chemistry </link>under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n                href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'