b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p3_vapor_pressure" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Vapor Pressure</title>\n        <objref idref="phase_diagram"/>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>We witness and utilize changes of physical state, or phase transitions, in a great number\n            of ways. As one example of global significance, consider the evaporation, condensation,\n            freezing, and melting of water. These changes of state are essential aspects of our\n            earth\xe2\x80\x99s water cycle as well as many other natural phenomena and technological processes\n            of central importance to our lives. </p>\n        <p>When a liquid vaporizes in a closed container, gas molecules cannot escape. As these gas\n            phase molecules move randomly about, they will occasionally collide with the surface of\n            the condensed phase, and in some cases, these collisions will result in the molecules\n            re-entering the condensed phase. When the rate of condensation becomes equal to the rate\n            of vaporization, neither the amount of the liquid nor the amount of the vapor in the\n            container changes. The vapor in the container is then said to be in equilibrium with the\n            liquid. Keep in mind that this is not a static situation, as molecules are continually\n            exchanged between the condensed and gaseous phases. Such is an example of a dynamic\n            equilibrium, the status of a system in which reciprocal processes (for example,\n            vaporization and condensation) occur at equal rates. The pressure exerted by the vapor\n            in equilibrium with a liquid in a closed container at a given temperature is called the\n            liquid\xe2\x80\x99s vapor pressure (or equilibrium vapor pressure). We can measure the vapor\n            pressure of a liquid by placing a sample in a closed container, like that illustrated\n            below, and using a manometer to measure the increase in pressure that is due to the\n            vapor in equilibrium with the condensed phase.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_10_03_VapPress1.jpg" alt="Three images are shown and labeled \xe2\x80\x9ca,\xe2\x80\x9d \xe2\x80\x9cb,\xe2\x80\x9d and \xe2\x80\x9cc.\xe2\x80\x9d Each image shows a round bulb connected on the right to a tube that is horizontal, then is bent vertically, curves, and then is vertical again to make a u-shape. A valve is located in the horizontal portion of the tube. Image a depicts a liquid in the bulb, labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cLiquid,\xe2\x80\x9d and upward-facing arrows leading away from the surface of the liquid. The phrase, \xe2\x80\x9cMolecules escape surface and form vapor\xe2\x80\x9d is written below the bulb, and a gray liquid in the u-shaped portion of the tube is shown at equal heights on the right and left sides. Image b depicts a liquid in the bulb, labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cLiquid,\xe2\x80\x9d and upward-facing arrows leading away from the surface of the liquid to molecules drawn in the upper portion of the bulb. A gray liquid in the u-shaped portion of the tube is shown slightly higher on the right side than on the left side. Image c depicts a liquid in the bulb, labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cLiquid,\xe2\x80\x9d and upward-facing arrows leading away from the surface of the liquid to molecules drawn in the upper portion of the bulb. There are more molecules present in c than in b. The phrase \xe2\x80\x9cEquilibrium reached, vapor pressure determined,\xe2\x80\x9d is written below the bulb and a gray liquid in the u-shaped portion of the tube is shown higher on the right side. A horizontal line is drawn level with each of these liquid levels and the distance between the lines is labeled with a double-headed arrow. This section is labeled with the phrase, \xe2\x80\x9cVapor pressure.\xe2\x80\x9d" width="700">\n            <caption>In a closed container, dynamic equilibrium is reached when (a) the rate of\n                molecules escaping from the liquid to become the gas (b) increases and eventually\n                (c) equals the rate of gas molecules entering the liquid. When this equilibrium is\n                reached, the vapor pressure of the gas is constant, although the vaporization and\n                condensation processes continue.</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>The chemical identities of the molecules in a liquid determine the types (and strengths)\n            of intermolecular attractions possible; consequently, different substances will exhibit\n            different equilibrium vapor pressures. Relatively strong intermolecular attractive\n            forces will serve to impede vaporization as well as favoring \xe2\x80\x9crecapture\xe2\x80\x9d of gas-phase\n            molecules when they collide with the liquid surface, resulting in a relatively low vapor\n            pressure. Weak intermolecular attractions present less of a barrier to vaporization, and\n            a reduced likelihood of gas recapture, yielding relatively high vapor pressures. The\n            following example illustrates this dependence of vapor pressure on intermolecular\n            attractive forces.</p>\n        <example>\n            <p>Given the shown structural formulas for these four compounds, explain their relative\n                vapor pressures in terms of types and extents of IMFs:</p>\n            <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_10_03_Ethanol_img.jpg" alt="Four Lewis structures are shown. The first structure, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cethanol,\xe2\x80\x9d shows a carbon bonded to three hydrogen atoms that is single bonded to a second carbon that is bonded to two hydrogen atoms and a hydroxyl group. The second structure, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cethylene glycol, shows two carbon atoms, single bonded to one another, single bonded each to two hydrogen atoms, and each single bonded to a hydroxyl group. The third image, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cdiethyl ether,\xe2\x80\x9d shows an oxygen atom single bonded on both sides to a carbon that is bonded to two hydrogens, and a second carbon, that is itself bonded to three hydrogen atoms. The fourth image, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cwater,\xe2\x80\x9d shows an oxygen atom that is single bonded on both sides to hydrogen atoms." width="550"/>\n            <ul>\n                <li>Diethyl ether has a very small dipole and most of its intermolecular attractions\n                    are London dispersion forces. Although this molecule is the largest of the four\n                    under consideration, its IMFs are the weakest and, as a result, its molecules\n                    most readily escape from the liquid. It also has the highest vapor\n                    pressure.</li>\n                <li>Due to its smaller size, ethanol exhibits weaker dispersion forces than diethyl\n                    ether. However, ethanol is capable of hydrogen bonding and, therefore, exhibits\n                    stronger overall IMFs, which means that fewer molecules escape from the liquid\n                    at any given temperature, and so ethanol has a lower vapor pressure than diethyl\n                    ether. </li>\n                <li>Water is much smaller than either of the previous substances and exhibits weaker\n                    dispersion forces, but its extensive hydrogen bonding provides stronger\n                    intermolecular attractions, fewer molecules escaping the liquid, and a lower\n                    vapor pressure than for either diethyl ether or ethanol.</li>\n                <li>Ethylene glycol has two \xe2\x88\x92OH groups, so, like water, it exhibits extensive\n                    hydrogen bonding. It is much larger than water and thus experiences larger\n                    London forces. Its overall IMFs are the largest of these four substances, which\n                    means its vaporization rate will be the slowest and, consequently, its vapor\n                    pressure the lowest.</li>\n            </ul>\n            <image src="../webcontent/vapor_pressure_example.png" alt="Four Lewis structures are shown. The first structure, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cethylene glycol, shows two carbon atoms, single bonded to one another, single bonded each to two hydrogen atoms, and each single bonded to a hydroxyl group. The second image, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cwater,\xe2\x80\x9d shows an oxygen atom that is single bonded on both sides to hydrogen atoms. The third structure, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cethanol,\xe2\x80\x9d shows a carbon bonded to three hydrogen atoms that is single bonded to a second carbon that is bonded to two hydrogen atoms and a hydroxyl group. The fourth image, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cdiethyl ether,\xe2\x80\x9d shows an oxygen atom single bonded on both sides to a carbon that is bonded to two hydrogens, and a second carbon, that is itself bonded to three hydrogen atoms. The first image is labeled as the structure with strongest attractive forces and lowest vapor pressure, and the fourth image is labeled as the structure with weakest attractive forces and highest vapor pressure." width="600"/>\n        </example>\n        <wb:inline idref="vap_pres_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n\n        <section>\n            <title>Temperature and Vapor Pressure</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>As temperature increases, the vapor pressure of a liquid also increases due to\n                    the increased average KE of its molecules. Recall that at any given temperature,\n                    the molecules of a substance experience a range of kinetic energies, with a\n                    certain fraction of molecules having a sufficient energy to overcome IMF and\n                    escape the liquid (vaporize). At a higher temperature, a greater fraction of\n                    molecules have enough energy to escape from the liquid. The escape of more\n                    molecules per unit of time and the greater average speed of the molecules that\n                    escape both contribute to the higher vapor pressure.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_10_03_VapPress3.jpg" alt="A graph is shown where the y-axis is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cNumber of molecules\xe2\x80\x9d and the x-axis is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cKinetic Energy.\xe2\x80\x9d Two lines are graphed and a vertical dotted line, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cMinimum K E needed to escape,\xe2\x80\x9d is drawn halfway across the x-axis. The first line move sharply upward and has a high peak near the left side of the x-axis. It drops just as steeply and ends about 60 percent of the way across the x-axis. This line is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cLow T.\xe2\x80\x9d A second line, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cHigh T,\xe2\x80\x9d begins at the same point as the first, but does not go to such a high point, is wider, and ends slightly further to the right on the x-axis.">\n                    <caption>Temperature affects the distribution of kinetic energies for the\n                        molecules in a liquid. At the higher temperature, more molecules have the\n                        necessary kinetic energy, KE, to escape from the liquid into the gas\n                        phase.</caption>\n                </image>\n\n               \n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <section>\n            <title>Boiling Points</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>When the vapor pressure increases enough to equal the external atmospheric\n                    pressure, the liquid reaches its boiling point. The boiling point of a liquid is\n                    the temperature at which its equilibrium vapor pressure is equal to the pressure\n                    exerted on the liquid by its gaseous surroundings. For liquids in open\n                    containers, this pressure is that due to the earth\xe2\x80\x99s atmosphere. The normal\n                    boiling point of a liquid is defined as its boiling point when surrounding\n                    pressure is equal to 1 atm (101.3 kPa). Figure shows the variation in vapor\n                    pressure with temperature for several different substances. Considering the\n                    definition of boiling point, these curves may be seen as depicting the\n                    dependence of a liquid\xe2\x80\x99s boiling point on surrounding pressure.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_10_03_VapPress2.jpg" alt="A graph is shown where the x-axis is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cTemperature ( degree sign, C )\xe2\x80\x9d and has values of 200 to 1000 in increments of 200 and the y-axis is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cPressure ( k P a )\xe2\x80\x9d and has values of 20 to 120 in increments of 20. A horizontal dotted line extends across the graph at point 780 on the y-axis while three vertical dotted lines extend from points 35, 78, and 100 to meet the horizontal dotted line. Four lines are graphed. The first line, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cethyl ether,\xe2\x80\x9d begins at the point \xe2\x80\x9c0 , 200\xe2\x80\x9d and extends in a slight curve to point \xe2\x80\x9c45, 1000\xe2\x80\x9d while the second line, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cethanol\xe2\x80\x9d, extends from point \xe2\x80\x9c0, 20\xe2\x80\x9d to point \xe2\x80\x9c88, 1000\xe2\x80\x9d in a more extreme curve. The third line, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cwater,\xe2\x80\x9d begins at the point \xe2\x80\x9c0, 0\xe2\x80\x9d and extends in a curve to point \xe2\x80\x9c108, 1000\xe2\x80\x9d while the fourth line, labeled \xe2\x80\x9cethylene glycol,\xe2\x80\x9d extends from point \xe2\x80\x9c80, 0\xe2\x80\x9d to point \xe2\x80\x9c140, 100\xe2\x80\x9d in a very shallow curve." width="600">\n                    <caption>The boiling points of liquids are the temperatures at which their\n                        equilibrium vapor pressures equal the pressure of the surrounding\n                        atmosphere. Normal boiling points are those corresponding to a pressure of 1\n                        atm (101.3 kPa.)</caption>\n                </image>\n                <wb:inline idref="boiling_pt_lbd1" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        \n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry </link>under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n        \n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'