b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n\n<workbook_page id="p3_vp_lower" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n    \n    \n    <head>\n        <title>Vapor Pressure Lowering</title>\n        <!-- <objref idref="describe_colligative"/>-->\n        <objref idref="calculate_colligative"/>\n        \n    </head>\n    \n    <body>\n        \n        <p>As described in the unit on liquids and solids, the equilibrium vapor pressure of a\n            liquid is the pressure exerted by its gaseous phase when vaporization and condensation\n            are occurring at equal rates:</p>\n        <formula>$$\\mathrm{liquid}\\;\\rightleftharpoons\\;\\mathrm{gas}$$</formula>\n        <p>Dissolving a nonvolatile substance in a volatile liquid results in a lowering of the\n            liquid\xe2\x80\x99s vapor pressure. This phenomenon can be rationalized by considering the effect\n            of added solute molecules on the liquid\'s vaporization and condensation processes. To\n            vaporize, solvent molecules must be present at the surface of the solution. The presence\n            of solute decreases the surface area available to solvent molecules and thereby reduces\n            the rate of solvent vaporization. Since the rate of condensation is unaffected by the\n            presence of solute, the net result is that the vaporization-condensation equilibrium is\n            achieved with fewer solvent molecules in the vapor phase (i.e., at a lower vapor\n            pressure). </p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_11_04_RaoultLaw.jpg" alt="This figure contains two images. Figure a is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cpure water.\xe2\x80\x9d It shows a beaker half-filled with liquid. In the liquid, eleven molecules are evenly dispersed in the liquid each consisting of one central red sphere and two slightly smaller white spheres are shown. Four molecules near the surface of the liquid have curved arrows drawn from them pointing to the space above the liquid in the beaker. Above the liquid, twelve molecules are shown, with arrows pointing from three of them into the liquid below. Figure b is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cAqueous solution.\xe2\x80\x9d It is similar to figure a except that eleven blue spheres, slightly larger in size than the molecules, are dispersed evenly in the liquid. Only four curved arrows appear in this diagram with two from the molecules in the liquid pointing to the space above and two from molecules in the space above the liquid pointing into the liquid below." width="500">\n            <caption>The presence of nonvolatile solutes lowers the vapor pressure of a solution by\n                impeding the evaporation of solvent molecules.</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>The relationship between the vapor pressures of solution components and the\n            concentrations of those components is described by Raoult\xe2\x80\x99s law.</p>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        <dl>\n            <dt> Raoult\'s Law</dt>\n            <dd>\n                <p>The partial pressure exerted by any component of an ideal solution is equal to\n                    the vapor pressure of the pure component multiplied by its mole fraction in the\n                    solution. </p>\n                <formula>$$P_\\mathrm A=X_AP_\\mathrm A^\\circ$$</formula>\n                <p>where <em style="italic">P</em><sub>A</sub> is the partial pressure exerted by\n                    component A in the solution, <em style="italic">P</em><sup>o</sup><sub>A</sub>\n                    is the vapor pressure of pure A, and <em style="italic">X</em><sub>A</sub> is\n                    the mole fraction of A in the solution. </p>\n                <p>In solutions containing nonvolatile solutes (which will always be the case for\n                    our purposes)</p>\n                <formula>$$P_\\mathrm{solution}=X_\\mathrm{solvent}P_\\mathrm{solvent}^\\circ$$</formula>\n            </dd>\n        </dl>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        \n        <example>\n            <p>Compute the vapor pressure of an ideal solution containing 92.1 g of glycerin,\n                C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>5</sub>(OH)<sub>3</sub>, and 184.4 g of ethanol,\n                C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH, at 40 \xc2\xb0C. The vapor pressure of pure ethanol is\n                0.178 atm at 40 \xc2\xb0C. Glycerin is essentially nonvolatile at this temperature.</p>\n            <p>Since the solvent is the only volatile component of this solution, its vapor pressure\n                may be computed per Raoult\xe2\x80\x99s law as:</p>\n            <formula>$$P_\\mathrm{solution}=X_\\mathrm{solvent}P_\\mathrm{solvent}^\\circ$$</formula>\n            <p>First, calculate the molar amounts of each solution component using the provided mass\n                data.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\require{cancel}\\begin{array}{l}92.1\\;\\cancel{\\mathrm g\\;{\\mathrm\n                C}_3{\\mathrm H}_5(\\mathrm{OH})_3}\\;\\times\\frac{1\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;{\\mathrm\n                C}_3{\\mathrm H}_5(\\mathrm{OH})_3}{92.094\\;\\cancel{\\mathrm g\\;{\\mathrm C}_3{\\mathrm\n                H}_5(\\mathrm{OH})_3}}\\;=\\;1.00\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;{\\mathrm C}_3{\\mathrm\n                H}_5(\\mathrm{OH})_3\\;\\\\184.4\\;\\cancel{\\mathrm g\\;{\\mathrm C}_2{\\mathrm\n                H}_5\\mathrm{OH}}\\;\\times\\;\\frac{1\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;{\\mathrm C}_2{\\mathrm\n                H}_5\\mathrm{OH}}{46.069\\;\\cancel{\\mathrm g\\;{\\mathrm C}_2{\\mathrm\n                H}_5\\mathrm{OH}}}\\;=\\;4.000\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;{\\mathrm C}_2{\\mathrm\n                H}_5\\mathrm{OH}\\end{array}$$</formula>\n            <p>Next, calculate the mole fraction of the solvent (ethanol) and use Raoult\xe2\x80\x99s law to\n                compute the solution\xe2\x80\x99s vapor pressure.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\begin{array}{l}X_{{\\mathrm C}_2{\\mathrm\n                H}_5\\mathrm{OH}}\\;=\\;\\frac{4.000\\;\\mathrm{mol}}{(1.00\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;+\\;4.000\\;\\mathrm{mol})}\\;=\\;0.800\\\\P_\\mathrm{solution}\\;=\\;X_\\mathrm{solvent}P_\\mathrm{solvent}^\\circ\\;=\\;0.800\\;\\times0.178\\;\\mathrm{atm}\\;=\\;0.142\\;\\mathrm{atm}\\end{array}$$</formula>\n            \n        </example>\n        <wb:inline idref="vp_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>\n        <wb:inline idref="vp_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n        \n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under  <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n        \n        \n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'