b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n\n<workbook_page id="p4_bp_elevation" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Boiling Point Elevation and Freezing Point Depression</title>\n      <!--  <objref idref="describe_colligative"/>-->\n        <objref idref="calculate_colligative"/>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>As described previously, the boiling point of a liquid is the temperature at which its\n            vapor pressure is equal to ambient atmospheric pressure. Since the vapor pressure of a\n            solution is lowered due to the presence of nonvolatile solutes, it stands to reason that\n            the solution\xe2\x80\x99s boiling point will subsequently be increased. Compared to pure solvent, a\n            solution, therefore, will require a higher temperature to achieve any given vapor\n            pressure, including one equivalent to that of the surrounding atmosphere. The increase\n            in boiling point observed when nonvolatile solute is dissolved in a solvent, \xce\x94<em\n                style="italic">T</em><sub>b</sub>, is called boiling point elevation. </p>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        <dl>\n\n            <dt> Boiling Point Elevation</dt>\n            <dd>\n                <p>Boiling point elevation is directly proportional to the molal concentration of\n                    solute species:</p>\n                <formula>$$\\mathrm\\Delta T_\\mathrm b\\mathit\\;=\\;K_\\mathrm bm$$</formula>\n                <p>where <em style="italic">K</em><sub>b</sub> is the boiling point elevation\n                    constant and <em style="italic">m</em> is the molal concentration (molality) of all solute species.</p>\n            </dd>\n        </dl>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        \n        <p>Boiling point elevation constants are characteristic properties that depend on the\n            identity of the solvent. Values of <em style="italic">K</em><sub>b</sub> for several\n            solvents are listed in the table below.</p>\n\n        <p>Solutions freeze at lower temperatures than pure liquids. This phenomenon is exploited in\n            \xe2\x80\x9cde-icing\xe2\x80\x9d schemes that use salt, calcium chloride, or urea to melt ice on roads and\n            sidewalks, and in the use of ethylene glycol as an \xe2\x80\x9cantifreeze\xe2\x80\x9d in automobile radiators.\n            Seawater freezes at a lower temperature than fresh water, and so the Arctic and\n            Antarctic oceans remain unfrozen even at temperatures below 0 \xc2\xb0C (as do the body fluids\n            of fish and other cold-blooded sea animals that live in these oceans).</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_11_04_deice.jpg" alt="This figure contains two photos. The first photo is a rear view of a large highway maintenance truck carrying a bright orange de-icer sign. A white material appears to be deposited at the rear of the truck onto the roadway. The second image is of an airplane being sprayed with a solution to remove ice prior to take off." width="600">\n            <caption>Freezing point depression is exploited to remove ice from (a) roadways and (b)\n                the control surfaces of aircraft.</caption>\n        </image>\n\n        <p>The decrease in freezing point of a dilute solution compared to that of the pure solvent,\n                \xce\x94<em style="italic">T</em><sub>f</sub>, is called the freezing point depression.</p>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        <dl>\n\n            <dt> Freezing Point Depression</dt>\n            <dd>\n                <p>Freezing point depression is directly proportional to the molal concentration of\n                    solute species:</p>\n                <formula>$$\\mathrm\\Delta T_\\mathrm f\\mathit\\;=\\;K_\\mathrm fm$$</formula>\n                <p>where <em style="italic">K</em><sub>f</sub> is the freezing point depression\n                    constant and <em style="italic">m</em> is the molal concentration (molality) of all solute\n                    species.</p>\n            </dd>\n        </dl>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        \n        <p>Just as for boiling point elevation constants, these are characteristic properties whose\n            values depend on the chemical identity of the solvent. Values of <em style="italic"\n                >K</em><sub>f</sub> for several solvents are listed below.</p>\n        <table>\n            <title>Boiling Point Elevation and Freezing Point Depression Constants for Several\n                Solvents</title>\n            <tr>\n                <th>Solvent</th>\n                <th> Boiling Point (\xc2\xb0C at 1 atm)</th>\n                <th><em style="italic">K</em><sub>b</sub> (\xc2\xbaCm<sup>\xe2\x88\x921</sup>)</th>\n                <th>Freezing Point (\xc2\xb0C at 1 atm)</th>\n                <th><em style="italic">K</em><sub>f</sub> (\xc2\xbaCm<sup>\xe2\x88\x921</sup>)</th>\n            </tr>\n            <tr>\n                <td>water</td>\n                <td>100.0</td>\n                <td>0.512</td>\n                <td>0.0</td>\n                <td>1.86</td>\n            </tr>\n            <tr>\n                <td>acetic acid</td>\n                <td>118.1</td>\n                <td>3.07</td>\n                <td>16.6</td>\n                <td>3.9</td>\n            </tr>\n            <tr>\n                <td>benzene</td>\n                <td>80.1</td>\n                <td>2.53</td>\n                <td>5.5</td>\n                <td>5.12</td>\n            </tr>\n            <tr>\n                <td>chloroform</td>\n                <td>61.26</td>\n                <td>3.63</td>\n                <td>\xe2\x88\x9263.5</td>\n                <td>4.68</td>\n            </tr>\n            <tr>\n                <td>nitrobenzene</td>\n                <td>210.9</td>\n                <td>5.24</td>\n                <td>5.67</td>\n                <td>8.1</td>\n            </tr>\n\n\n        </table>\n\n        <p>The extent to which boiling point is increased and freezing point decrease for a solvent\n            depends on the total number of solute particles present in a given amount of solvent,\n            not on the mass or size or chemical identities of the particles. A 1 m aqueous solution\n            of sucrose (342 g/mol) and a 1 m aqueous solution of ethylene glycol (62 g/mol) will\n            exhibit the same boiling point because each solution has one mole of solute particles\n            (molecules) per kilogram of solvent.</p>\n        <example>\n            <p>What is the boiling point of a 0.33 <em style="italic">m</em> solution of a\n                nonvolatile solute in benzene?</p>\n            <p>First, calculate the change in boiling point.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\triangle T_{\\mathrm b}\\;=\\;K_{\\mathrm b}m\\;=\\;2.53^\\circ\\mathrm C\\cdot m^{-1}\\;\\times\\;0.33\\;m\\;=\\;0.83\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C$$</formula>\n           \n            \n            <p>Since we know that boiling point increases with the addition of a solute, add the\n                boiling point elevation to the pure solvent\xe2\x80\x99s boiling point.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\mathrm{Boiling}\\;\\mathrm{temperature}\\;=\\;80.1\\;^\\circ\\mathrm\n                C\\;+\\;0.83\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C\\;=\\;80.9\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C$$</formula>\n        </example>\n        <example>\n            <p>Find the boiling point and freezing point of a solution of 92.1 g of iodine,\n                    I<sub>2</sub>, in 800.0 g of chloroform, CHCl<sub>3</sub>, assuming that the\n                iodine is nonvolatile and that the solution is ideal. The boiling point of pure\n                chloroform is 61.2 <sup>o</sup>C.</p>\n            <p>First we will need to convert mass of I<sub>2</sub> to moles in order to determine\n                the molality of the solution.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\require{cancel}92.1\\cancel{\\;\\mathrm g\\;{\\mathrm\n                I}_2}\\;\\times\\;\\frac{1\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;{\\mathrm I}_2}{253.8\\;\\cancel{\\mathrm\n                g\\;{\\mathrm I}_2}}\\;=\\;0.3629\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;{\\mathrm I}_2$$</formula>\n            <p>Calculate the molality of the solution.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\mathrm{molality}\\;=\\;\\frac{0.3629\\;\\mathrm{mol}}{0.800\\;\\mathrm{kg}}\\;=\\;0.4536\\;m$$</formula>\n            <p>Use the direct proportionality between the change in boiling point and molal\n                concentration to determine how much the boiling point changes.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\triangle T_\\mathrm b\\;=\\;K_\\mathrm bm\\;=\\;3.63\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C\\cdot\n                m^{-1}\\;\\times\\;0.4536\\;m\\;=\\;1.646\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C$$</formula>\n            <p>Determine the new boiling point from the boiling point of the pure solvent and the\n                change.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\mathrm{Boiling}\\;\\mathrm{temperature}\\;=\\;61.26\\;^\\circ\\mathrm\n                C\\;+\\;1.646\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C\\;=\\;62.91\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C$$</formula>\n            <p>Use the direct proportionality between the change in freezing point and molal\n                concentration to determine how much the freezing point changes.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\triangle T_\\mathrm f\\;=\\;K_\\mathrm fm\\;=\\;4.68\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C\\cdot\n                m^{-1}\\;\\times\\;0.4536\\;m\\;=\\;2.123\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C$$</formula>\n            <p>Determine the new freezing point from the freezing point of the pure solvent and the\n                change.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\mathrm{Freezing}\\;\\mathrm{temperature}\\;=\\;-63.6\\;^\\circ\\mathrm\n                C\\;-\\;2.123\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C\\;=\\;-65.5\\;^\\circ\\mathrm C$$</formula>\n        </example>\n        <wb:inline idref="bp_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n        <wb:inline idref="bp_elevation_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n        <wb:inline idref="bp_fp_lbd2" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>\n        <wb:inline idref="bp_elevation_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n        <section>\n            <title>Phase Diagram for an Aqueous Solution of a Nonelectrolyte</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>The colligative effects on vapor pressure, boiling point, and freezing point\n                    described in the previous section are conveniently summarized by comparing the\n                    phase diagrams for a pure liquid and a solution derived from that liquid. Phase\n                    diagrams for water and an aqueous solution are shown in the diagram below.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_11_04_phasediag.jpg" alt="This phase diagram indicates the pressure in atmospheres of water and a solution at various temperatures. The graph shows the freezing point of water and the freezing point of the solution, with the difference between these two values identified as delta T subscript f. The graph shows the boiling point of water and the boiling point of the solution, with the difference between these two values identified as delta T subscript b. Similarly, the difference in the pressure of water and the solution at the boiling point of water is shown and identified as delta P. This difference in pressure is labeled vapor pressure lowering. The lower level of the vapor pressure curve for the solution as opposed to that of pure water shows vapor pressure lowering in the solution. Background colors on the diagram indicate the presence of water and the solution in the solid state to the left, liquid state in the central upper region, and gas to the right." width="600">\n                    <caption>These phase diagrams show water (solid curves) and an aqueous solution\n                        of nonelectrolyte (dashed curves).</caption>\n                </image>\n                <p>The liquid-vapor curve for the solution is located beneath the corresponding\n                    curve for the solvent, depicting the vapor pressure lowering, \xce\x94P, that results\n                    from the dissolution of nonvolatile solute. Consequently, at any given pressure,\n                    the solution\xe2\x80\x99s boiling point is observed at a higher temperature than that for\n                    the pure solvent, reflecting the boiling point elevation, \xce\x94<em style="italic">T</em><sub>b</sub>, associated with\n                    the presence of nonvolatile solute. The solid-liquid curve for the solution is\n                    displaced left of that for the pure solvent, representing the freezing point\n                    depression, \xce\x94<em style="italic">T</em><sub>f</sub>, that accompanies solution formation. Finally, notice that the\n                    solid-gas curves for the solvent and its solution are identical. This is the\n                    case for many solutions comprising liquid solvents and nonvolatile solutes. Just\n                    as for vaporization, when a solution of this sort is frozen, it is actually just\n                    the solvent molecules that undergo the liquid-to-solid transition, forming pure\n                    solid solvent that excludes solute species. The solid and gaseous phases,\n                    therefore, are composed of solvent only, and so transitions between these phases\n                    are not subject to colligative effects.</p>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under  <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n        \n        \n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'