b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p4_evolution_nuclear" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>The Nuclear Atom</title>\n        <objref idref="evolution_atomic"/>\n    </head>\n    <body>\n        <p>The next major development in understanding the atom came from Ernest Rutherford, a\n            physicist from New Zealand who largely spent his scientific career in Canada and\n            England. He performed a series of experiments using a beam of high-speed, positively\n            charged <extra><anchor>alpha particles</anchor><meaning><material><p>positively charged particle consisting of two protons and two neutrons</p></material></meaning></extra> (\xce\xb1 particles) that were produced by the radioactive decay of\n            radium; \xce\xb1 particles consist of two protons and two neutrons. Rutherford and his\n            colleagues Hans Geiger (later famous for the Geiger counter) and Ernest Marsden aimed a\n            beam of \xce\xb1 particles, the source of which was embedded in a lead block to absorb most of\n            the radiation, at a very thin piece of gold foil and examined the resultant scattering\n            of the \xce\xb1 particles using a luminescent screen that glowed briefly where hit by an \xce\xb1\n            particle.</p>\n        <p>What did they discover? Most particles passed right through the foil without being\n            deflected at all. However, some were diverted slightly, and a very small number were\n            deflected almost straight back toward the source. </p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/gold_foil.png" width="600"\n            alt="This figure shows a box on the left that contains a radium source of alpha particles which generates a beam of alpha particles. The beam travels through an opening within a ring-shaped luminescent screen which is used to detect scattered alpha particles. A piece of thin gold foil is at the center of the ring formed by the screen. When the beam encounters the gold foil, most of the alpha particles pass straight through it and hit the luminescent screen directly behind the foil. Some of the alpha particles are slightly deflected by the foil and hit the luminescent screen off to the side of the foil. Some alpha particles are significantly deflected and bounce back to hit the front of the screen.">\n            <caption>Geiger and Rutherford fired \xce\xb1 particles at a piece of gold foil and detected\n                where those particles went, as shown in this schematic diagram of their experiment.\n                Most of the particles passed straight through the foil, but a few were deflected\n                slightly and a very small number were significantly deflected. </caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>Here is what Rutherford deduced: Because most of the fast-moving \xce\xb1 particles passed\n            through the gold atoms undeflected, they must have traveled through essentially empty\n            space inside the atom. Alpha particles are positively charged, so deflections arose when\n            they encountered another positive charge (like charges repel each other). Since like\n            charges repel one another, the few positively charged \xce\xb1 particles that changed paths\n            abruptly must have hit, or closely approached, another body that also had a highly\n            concentrated, positive charge. Since the deflections occurred a small fraction of the\n            time, this charge only occupied a small amount of the space in the gold foil. Analyzing\n            a series of such experiments in detail, Rutherford drew two conclusions:</p>\n        <ul>\n            <li>The volume occupied by an atom must consist of a large amount of empty space.</li>\n            <li>A small, relatively heavy, positively charged body, the nucleus, must be at the\n                center of each atom.</li>\n        </ul>\n        <p>This analysis led Rutherford to propose a model in which an atom consists of a very\n            small, positively charged nucleus, in which most of the mass of the atom is\n            concentrated, surrounded by the negatively charged electrons, so that the atom is\n            electrically neutral. He named this fundamental particle the <extra><anchor>proton</anchor><meaning><material><p>Positively charged subatomic particle located in the nucleus of the atom.</p></material></meaning></extra>, the positively\n            charged, subatomic particle found in the nucleus. With one addition, which you will\n            learn next, this nuclear model of the atom, proposed over a century ago, is still used\n            today.</p>\n        <composite_activity purpose="didigetthis">\n            <p>The image in the activity below represents a close-up diagram of Rutherford\'s gold\n                foil experiment. Drag the description of the observation that Rutherford made to the\n                place on the diagram that represents that observation.</p>\n            <wb:inline idref="gold_foil_dnd_question"/>\n        </composite_activity>\n        <wb:inline idref="gold_foil_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n        <p>One puzzle remained: The nucleus was known to contain almost all of the mass of an atom,\n            with the number of protons only providing half, or less, of that mass. Different\n            proposals were made to explain what constituted the remaining mass, including the\n            existence of neutral particles in the nucleus. As you might expect, detecting uncharged\n            particles is very challenging, and it was not until 1932 that James Chadwick found\n            evidence of <extra><anchor>neutrons</anchor><meaning><material><p>uncharged, subatomic particle located in the nucleus</p></material></meaning></extra>, uncharged, subatomic particles with a mass approximately the same\n            as that of protons. </p>\n\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n                href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'