b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p4_linespectra" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Line Spectra</title>\n        <objref idref="particle_light"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n        <p>Another paradox within the classical electromagnetic theory that scientists in the late\n            nineteenth century struggled with concerned the light emitted from atoms and molecules.\n            When solids, liquids, or condensed gases are heated sufficiently, they radiate some of\n            the excess energy as light. Photons produced in this manner have a range of energies,\n            and thereby produce a continuous spectrum in which an unbroken series of wavelengths is\n            present. Most of the light generated from stars (including our sun) is produced in this\n            fashion. You can see all the visible wavelengths of light present in sunlight by using a\n            prism to separate them. As can be seen in figure below, sunlight also contains UV light\n            (shorter wavelengths) and IR light (longer wavelengths) that can be detected using\n            instruments but that are invisible to the human eye. Incandescent (glowing) solids such\n            as tungsten filaments in incandescent lights also give off light that contains all\n            wavelengths of visible light. </p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/prism.png" width="600"\n            alt="White light passed through a prism produces the continuous spectrum of visible light.">\n            <caption>White light passed through a prism produces the continuous spectrum of visible\n                light.</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>In contrast to continuous spectra, light can also occur as discrete or line spectra\n            having very narrow line widths interspersed throughout the spectral regions such as\n            those shown in the figure below. Exciting a gas at low partial pressure using an\n            electrical current, or heating it, will produce line spectra. Fluorescent light bulbs\n            and neon signs operate in this way. Each element displays its own characteristic set of\n            lines, as do molecules, although their spectra are generally much more complicated.</p>\n        <p>Each emission line consists of a single wavelength of light, which implies that the light\n            emitted by a gas consists of a set of discrete energies. For example, when an electric\n            discharge passes through a tube containing hydrogen gas at low pressure, the\n                H<sub>2</sub> molecules are broken apart into separate H atoms and we see a\n            blue-pink color. Passing the light through a prism produces a line spectrum, indicating\n            that this light is composed of photons of four visible wavelengths, as shown in the\n            figure below.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/prism2.png" width="600"\n            alt="When light generated from a gas tube containing hydrogen supplied with an electric current is passed through a prism, the hydrogen line spectrum is produced.">\n            <caption>When light generated from a gas tube containing hydrogen supplied with an\n                electric current is passed through a prism, the hydrogen line spectrum is\n                produced.</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>Every element has a unique line spectrum, which can be used to identify the element. The\n            image below shows the line spectra of several elements. Compounds also produce unique\n            line spectra, but are more complex than the spectra produced by individual elements.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/emissionspec.jpeg" width="600" alt="An image is shown with 5 rows. Across the top and bottom of the image is a scale that begins at 4000 angstroms at the left and extends to 740 angstroms at the far right. The top row is a continuous band of the visible spectrum, showing the colors from violet at the far left through indigo, blue, green, yellow, orange, and red at the far right. The second row, labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cN a,\xe2\x80\x9d shows the emission spectrum for the element sodium, which includes two narrow vertical bands in the blue range, two narrow bands in the yellow-green range, two narrow bands in the yellow range, and one narrow band in the orange range. The third row, labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cH,\xe2\x80\x9d shows the emission spectrum for hydrogen. This spectrum shows single bands in the violet, indigo, blue, and orange regions. The fourth row, labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cC a,\xe2\x80\x9d shows the emission spectrum for calcium. This spectrum shows bands in the following colors and frequencies; one violet, five indigo, one blue, two green, two yellow-green, one yellow, two yellow-orange, one orange, and one red. The fifth row, labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cH g,\xe2\x80\x9d shows the emission spectrum for mercury. This spectrum shows bands in the following colors and frequencies; two violet, one indigo, two blue, one green, two yellow, two orange, and one orange-red. It is important to note that each of the color bands for the emission spectra of the elements matches to a specific wavelength of light. Extending a vertical line from the bands to the scale above or below the diagram will match the band to a specific measurement on the scale.">\n            <caption>Compare the two types of emission spectra: continuous spectrum of white light\n                (top) and the line spectra of the light from excited sodium, hydrogen, calcium, and\n                mercury atoms. </caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>This <link href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2ZlhRChr_Bw">video</link> shows the line\n            spectra of several different substances. Note that the diffraction grating used works\n            like a prism to bend and separate the light so that each individual frequencies can be\n            seen.</p>\n        <p>The origin of discrete spectra in atoms and molecules was extremely puzzling to\n            scientists in the late nineteenth century, since according to classical electromagnetic\n            theory, only continuous spectra should be observed. Even more puzzling, in 1885, Johann\n            Balmer was able to derive an empirical equation that related the four visible\n            wavelengths of light emitted by hydrogen atoms to whole integers. That equation is the\n            following one, in which <em style="italic">k</em> is a constant:</p>\n        <formula>$$\\frac1{\\mathrm\\lambda}\\;=\\;k\\;\\left(\\frac14\\;-\\;\\frac1{n^2}\\right),\\;n\\;=\\;3,\\;4,\\;5,\\;6$$</formula>\n        <p>Other discrete lines for the hydrogen atom were found in the UV and IR regions. Johannes\n            Rydberg generalized Balmer\'s work and developed an empirical formula that predicted all\n            of hydrogen\'s emission lines, not just those restricted to the visible range, where\n            <em style="italic">n<sub>1</sub></em> and <em style="italic">n<sub>2</sub></em> are integers, <em style="italic">n<sub>1</sub></em> &lt; <em style="italic">n<sub>2</sub></em> and\n            <em style="italic">R<sub>H</sub></em> is the Rydberg constant (1.097\xc3\x9710<sup>7</sup> m<sup>-1</sup>).</p>\n        <formula>$$\\frac1\\lambda\\;=\\;R_H\\left(\\frac1{n_1^2}\\;-\\;\\frac1{n_2^2}\\right)$$</formula>\n        <p>Even in the late nineteenth century, spectroscopy was a very precise science, and so the\n            wavelengths of hydrogen were measured to very high accuracy, which implied that the\n            Rydberg constant could be determined very precisely as well. That such a simple formula\n            as the Rydberg formula could account for such precise measurements seemed astounding at\n            the time, but it was the eventual explanation for emission spectra by Neils Bohr in 1913\n            that ultimately convinced scientists to abandon classical physics and spurred the\n            development of modern quantum mechanics.</p>\n        <wb:inline idref="line_spectra_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="http://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface">Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0\n                License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n                href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'