b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p4_spin" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>The Spin Quantum Number</title>\n        <objref idref="quantum_numbers"/>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>The other three quantum numbers, <em style="italic">n</em>, <em style="italic">l</em>,\n            and <em style="italic">m<sub>l</sub></em>, are properties of specific atomic orbitals\n            that also define in what part of the space an electron is most likely to be located.\n            Orbitals are a result of solving the Schr\xc3\xb6dinger equation for electrons in atoms. The\n            electron spin is a different kind of property. It is a completely quantum phenomenon\n            with no analogues in the classical realm. In addition, it cannot be derived from solving\n            the Schr\xc3\xb6dinger equation and is not related to the normal spatial coordinates (such as\n            the Cartesian <em style="italic">x</em>, <em style="italic">y</em>, and <em\n                style="italic">z</em>). Electron spin describes an intrinsic electron \xe2\x80\x9crotation\xe2\x80\x9d or\n            \xe2\x80\x9cspinning.\xe2\x80\x9d Each electron acts as a tiny magnet or a tiny rotating object with an\n            angular momentum, even though this rotation cannot be observed in terms of the spatial\n            coordinates.</p>\n        <p>The magnitude of the overall electron spin can only have one value, and an electron can\n            only \xe2\x80\x9cspin\xe2\x80\x9d in one of two quantized states. One is termed the \xce\xb1 state, with the z\n            component of the spin being in the positive direction of the z axis. This corresponds to\n            the spin quantum number <em style="italic">m<sub>s</sub></em> = \\(\\frac12\\). The other is called\n            the \xce\xb2 state, with the z component of the spin being negative and <em style="italic"\n                >m<sub>s</sub></em> = \xe2\x88\x92\\(\\frac12\\). Any electron, regardless of the atomic orbital it is\n            located in, can only have one of those two values of the spin quantum number. The\n            energies of electrons having <em style="italic">m<sub>s</sub></em> = \xe2\x88\x92\\(\\frac12\\) and <em\n                style="italic">m<sub>s</sub></em> = \\(\\frac12\\) are different if an external magnetic field\n            is applied.</p>\n        <p>The image below illustrates this phenomenon. An electron acts like a tiny magnet. Its\n            moment is directed up (in the positive direction of the <em style="italic">z</em> axis)\n            for the \\(\\frac12\\) spin quantum number and down (in the negative <em style="italic">z</em>\n            direction) for the spin quantum number of \xe2\x88\x92\\(\\frac12\\). A magnet has a lower energy if its\n            magnetic moment is aligned with the external magnetic field (the left electron on the\n            image below) and a higher energy for the magnetic moment being opposite to the applied\n            field. This is why an electron with <em style="italic">m<sub>s</sub></em> = \\(\\frac12\\) has a\n            slightly lower energy in an external field in the positive z direction, and an electron\n            with <em style="italic">m<sub>s</sub></em> = \xe2\x88\x92\\(\\frac12\\) has a slightly higher energy in the\n            same field. This is true even for an electron occupying the same orbital in an atom. A\n            spectral line corresponding to a transition for electrons from the same orbital but with\n            <em style="italic">z</em> different spin quantum numbers has two possible values of energy; thus, the line in\n            the spectrum will show a fine structure splitting.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/spin1.jpeg" width="600"\n            alt="This diagram has an upward pointing arrow at the left which is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cB subscript 0.\xe2\x80\x9d To the right, two spheres are shown. The first has a gray square at the top labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cN,\xe2\x80\x9d and a second gray square at the bottom labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cS.\xe2\x80\x9d A curved arrow is pointing right across the surface of the sphere and a gray arrow points upward through the center of the sphere. This sphere is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cSpin plus one-half, spin-up.\xe2\x80\x9d The sphere just to the right has a gray square above it labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cS,\xe2\x80\x9d and a gray square below it labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cN.\xe2\x80\x9d This sphere has a curved arrow on its surface that is directed to the left and a gray arrow through the center of the sphere that points downward. This sphere is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cSpin negative one-half spin-down.\xe2\x80\x9d">\n            <caption>Electrons with spin values \xc2\xb1\\(\\frac12\\) in an external magnetic field. </caption>\n        </image>\n        <section>\n            <title>The Pauli Exclusion Principle</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>An electron in an atom is completely described by four quantum numbers: <em style="italic">n</em>, <em style="italic">l</em>,\n                       <em style="italic"> m<sub>l</sub></em>, and <em style="italic">m<sub>s</sub></em>. The first three quantum numbers define the\n                    orbital and the fourth quantum number describes the intrinsic electron property\n                    called spin. An Austrian physicist Wolfgang Pauli formulated a general principle\n                    that gives the last piece of information that we need to understand the general\n                    behavior of electrons in atoms. The Pauli exclusion principle can be formulated\n                    as follows: No two electrons in the same atom can have exactly the same set of\n                    all the four quantum numbers. What this means is that electrons can share the\n                    same orbital (the same set of the quantum numbers <em style="italic">n</em>, <em style="italic">l</em>, and <em style="italic">m<sub>l</sub></em>), but\n                    only if their spin quantum numbers <em style="italic">m<sub>s</sub></em> have different values. Since\n                    the spin quantum number can only have two values (\xc2\xb1\\(\\frac12\\)), no more than two\n                    electrons can occupy the same orbital (and if two electrons are located in the\n                    same orbital, they must have opposite spins). Therefore, any atomic orbital can\n                    be populated by only zero, one, or two electrons.</p>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        <wb:inline idref="table_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n               <wb:inline idref="spin_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n        <wb:inline idref="spin_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0\n                License</link>. </p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n                href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312</link>.</p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'