b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p5_concentration" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title> Units of Solution Concentration: Mass and Volume Percentage</title>\n        <objref idref="ppm_ppb"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>In the previous section, we introduced molarity, a very useful measurement unit for\n            evaluating the concentration of solutions. However, molarity is only one measure of\n            concentration. In this section, we will introduce some other units of concentration that\n            are commonly used in various applications, either for convenience or by convention.</p>\n\n        <section>\n            <title>Mass Percentage</title>\n\n            <body>\n                <p>Earlier, we introduced percent composition as a measure of the relative amount of\n                    a given element in a compound. Percentages are also commonly used to express the\n                    composition of mixtures, including solutions. The <extra><anchor>mass percentage</anchor><meaning><material><p>ratio of solute-to-solution mass expressed as a percentage\n                      </p></material></meaning></extra> of a solution\n                    component is defined as the ratio of the component\xe2\x80\x99s mass to the solution\xe2\x80\x99s\n                    mass, expressed as a percentage.</p>\n\n\n            </body>\n        </section>\n\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n           <dl>\n               <dt><em> Mass Percent</em></dt>\n               <dd> <formula>$$\\mathrm{mass}\\;\\mathrm{percentage}\\;=\\;\\frac{\\mathrm{mass}\\;\\mathrm{of}\\;\\mathrm{component}}{\\mathrm{mass}\\;\\mathrm{of}\\;\\mathrm{solution}}\\;\\times\\;100\\%$$</formula>\n               </dd>\n           </dl>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n                <p>We are generally most interested in the mass percentages of solutes, but it is\n                    also possible to compute the mass percentage of solvent.</p>\n\n                <p>Mass percentage is also referred to by similar names such as percent mass,\n                    percent weight, weight/weight percent, and other variations on this theme. The\n                    most common symbol for mass percentage is simply the percent sign, %, although\n                    more detailed symbols are often used including %mass, %weight, and (w/w)%. Use\n                    of these more detailed symbols can prevent confusion of mass percentages with\n                    other types of percentages, such as volume percentages (to be discussed later in\n                    this section).</p>\n\n                <p>Mass percentages are popular concentration units for consumer products. The label\n                    of a typical liquid bleach bottle cites the concentration of its active\n                    ingredient, sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl), as being 7.4%. A 100.0\xe2\x88\x92g sample of\n                    bleach would therefore contain 7.4 g of NaOCl.</p>\n\n        <image src="../webcontent/bleach.png" alt="The sides of two cylindrical containers are shown. Each container\xe2\x80\x99s label is partially visible. The left container\xe2\x80\x99s label reads \xe2\x80\x9cBleach.\xe2\x80\x9d The right label contains more information about the product including the phrase, \xe2\x80\x9cContains: Sodium hypochlorite 7.4 %.\xe2\x80\x9d">\n                    <caption>Liquid bleach is an aqueous solution of sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl).\n                        This brand has a concentration of 7.4% NaOCl by mass.</caption>\n                </image>\n\n                <example>\n                    <p> A 5.0\xe2\x88\x92g sample of spinal fluid contains 3.75 mg (0.00375 g) of glucose. What\n                        is the percent by mass of glucose in spinal fluid?</p>\n\n                    <p> Substituting the given masses into the equation defining mass percentage\n                        yields:</p>\n\n                    <formula>$$\\%\\;\\mathrm{glucose}\\;=\\;\\frac{3.75\\;\\mathrm{mg}\\;\\mathrm{glucose}\\;\\times\\;{\\displaystyle\\frac{1\\;\\mathrm g}{1000\\;\\mathrm{mg}}}}{5.0\\;\\mathrm g\\;\\mathrm{spinal}\\;\\mathrm{fluid}}\\;=\\;0.075\\%$$</formula>\n\n                    <p>Note that while any mass unit may be used to compute a mass percentage (mg,\n                        g, kg, oz, and so on), the same unit must be used for both the solute and\n                        the solution so that the mass units cancel, yielding a dimensionless ratio.\n                        In this case, we converted the units of solute in the numerator from mg to g\n                        to match the units in the denominator. We could just as easily have\n                        converted the denominator from g to mg instead. As long as identical mass\n                        units are used for both solute and solution, the computed mass percentage\n                        will be correct.</p>\n                </example>\n\n                <example>\n                    <p>\xe2\x80\x9cConcentrated\xe2\x80\x9d hydrochloric acid is an aqueous solution of 37.2% HCl that is\n                        commonly used as a laboratory reagent. The density of this solution is 1.19\n                        g/mL. What mass of HCl is contained in 0.500 L of this solution?</p>\n\n                    <p>In order to derive the mass of solute in a solution from its mass percentage,\n                        we need to know the corresponding mass of the solution. Using the solution\n                        density given, we can convert the solution\xe2\x80\x99s volume to mass, and then use\n                        the given mass percentage to calculate the solute mass. This mathematical\n                        approach is outlined in this flowchart:</p>\n\n                    <image src="../webcontent/flowchart.png"\n                        alt="A diagram of three boxes connected by a right-facing arrow in between each is shown. The box on the left contains the phrase, \xe2\x80\x9cVolume of solution ( m L ),\xe2\x80\x9d the middle box reads, \xe2\x80\x9cMass of solution ( g ),\xe2\x80\x9d while the one on the right contains the phrase, \xe2\x80\x9cMass of H C l ( g ).\xe2\x80\x9d There is a phrase under the left arrow that says, \xe2\x80\x9cMultiply by density ( g / m L )\xe2\x80\x9d and under the right arrow it states, \xe2\x80\x9cMultiply by mass percent as ratio ( g H C l / g solution ).\xe2\x80\x9d"/>\n\n                    <p>For proper unit cancellation, the 0.500 L volume is converted into 500 mL,\n                        and the mass percentage is expressed as a ratio, 37.2g HCl/g solution:</p>\n\n                    <formula>$$500\\;\\mathrm{mL}\\;\\mathrm{solution}\\;\\left(\\frac{1.19\\;\\mathrm g\\;\\mathrm{solution}}{\\mathrm{mL}\\;\\mathrm{solution}}\\right)\\left(\\frac{37.2\\;\\mathrm g\\;\\mathrm{HCl}}{100\\;\\mathrm g\\;\\mathrm{solution}}\\right)\\;=\\;221\\;\\mathrm g\\;\\mathrm{HCl}$$</formula>\n                </example>\n\n                <wb:inline idref="concentration_lbd_1" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n\n                <section>\n                    <title>Volume Percentage</title>\n                    <body>\n                        <p>Liquid volumes over a wide range of magnitudes are conveniently measured\n                            using common and relatively inexpensive laboratory equipment. The\n                            concentration of a solution formed by dissolving a liquid solute in a\n                            liquid solvent is therefore often expressed as a <extra><anchor>volume percentage</anchor><meaning><material><p>ratio of solute-to-solution volume expressed as a percentage</p></material></meaning></extra>, %vol\n                            or (v/v)%.</p>\n                        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n                        <dl><dt><em>Volume Percentage</em></dt>\n\n                        <dd><formula>$$\\mathrm{volume}\\;\\mathrm{percentage}\\;=\\;\\frac{\\mathrm{volume}\\;\\mathrm{solute}}{\\mathrm{volume}\\;\\mathrm{solution}}\\;\\times\\;100\\;\\%$$</formula>\n                        </dd>\n                        </dl>\n                        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>  \n                        <example>\n                            <p>Rubbing alcohol (isopropanol) is usually sold as a 70% vol aqueous\n                                solution. If the density of isopropyl alcohol is 0.785 g/mL, how\n                                many grams of isopropyl alcohol are present in a 355 mL bottle of\n                                rubbing alcohol?</p>\n\n                            <p>Per the definition of volume percentage, the isopropanol volume is\n                                70% of the total solution volume. Multiplying the isopropanol volume\n                                by its density yields the requested mass:</p>\n\n                            <formula>$$355\\;\\mathrm{mL}\\;\\mathrm{solution}\\;\\left(\\frac{70\\;\\mathrm{mL}\\;\\mathrm{isopropyl}\\;\\mathrm{alcohol}}{100\\;\\mathrm{mL}\\;\\mathrm{solution}}\\right)\\left(\\frac{0.785\\;\\mathrm g\\;\\mathrm{isopropyl}\\;\\mathrm{alcohol}}{1\\;\\mathrm{mL}\\;\\mathrm{isopropyl}\\;\\mathrm{alcohol}}\\right)\\;=\\;195\\;\\mathrm g\\;\\mathrm{isopropyl}\\;\\mathrm{alcohol}$$</formula>\n                        </example>\n                        \n                        <wb:inline idref="concentration_lbd_2" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n                        \n                        <wb:inline idref="concentration_lbd_3" purpose="learnbydoing"/>\n                        \n                        <wb:inline idref="concentration_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n                        \n                        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                                4.0 License. </link></p>\n                        <p>Download for free at <link\n                            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n                        \n                        \n                    </body>\n                </section>\n\n            \n        \n\n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'