b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p5_dipole_dipole" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Dipole-Dipole Attractions</title>\n        <objref idref="describe_imf"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>Recall from the unit on chemical bonding and molecular geometry that polar molecules have\n            a partial positive charge on one side and a partial negative charge on the other side of\n            the molecule\xe2\x80\x94a separation of charge called a dipole. Consider a polar molecule such as\n            hydrogen chloride, HCl. In the HCl molecule, the more electronegative Cl atom bears the\n            partial negative charge, whereas the less electronegative H atom bears the partial\n            positive charge. An attractive force between HCl molecules results from the attraction\n            between the positive end of one HCl molecule and the negative end of another. This\n            attractive force is called a dipole-dipole attraction\xe2\x80\x94the electrostatic force between\n            the partially positive end of one polar molecule and the partially negative end of\n            another, as illustrated below.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/dipole_dipole.jpg" alt="Two pairs of molecules are shown where each molecule has one larger blue side labeled \xe2\x80\x9cdelta sign, negative sign\xe2\x80\x9d and a smaller red side labeled \xe2\x80\x9cdelta sign, positive sign. In the first pair, the red sides of the two molecules both face to the left and the blue side to the right. A horizontal dotted line lies in between the two. In the second pair, the molecules face up and down, with the red and blue ends aligning. A horizontal dotted line lies between the red and blue ends facing upward and another lies between the red and blue ends facing downward." width="700">\n            <caption>This image shows two arrangements of polar molecules, such as HCl, that allow\n                an attraction between the partial negative end of one molecule and the partial\n                positive end of another.</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>The effect of a dipole-dipole attraction is apparent when we compare the properties of\n            HCl molecules to nonpolar F<sub>2</sub> molecules. Both HCl and F<sub>2</sub> consist of\n            the same number of atoms and have approximately the same molecular mass. At a\n            temperature of 150 K, molecules of both substances would have the same average KE.\n            However, the dipole-dipole attractions between HCl molecules are sufficient to cause\n            them to \xe2\x80\x9cstick together\xe2\x80\x9d to form a liquid, whereas the relatively weaker dispersion\n            forces between nonpolar F<sub>2</sub> molecules are not, and so this substance is\n            gaseous at this temperature. The higher normal boiling point of HCl (188 K) compared to\n                F<sub>2</sub> (85 K) is a reflection of the greater strength of dipole-dipole\n            attractions between HCl molecules, compared to the attractions between nonpolar\n                F<sub>2</sub> molecules. We will often use values such as boiling or freezing\n            points, or enthalpies of vaporization or fusion, as indicators of the relative strengths\n            of IMFs of attraction present within different substances.</p>\n        <example>\n            <p>Predict which will have the higher boiling point: N<sub>2</sub> or CO. Explain your\n                reasoning.</p>\n            <p/>\n            <p>CO and N<sub>2</sub> are both diatomic molecules with masses of about 28 amu, so they experience\n                similar London dispersion forces. Because CO is a polar molecule, it experiences\n                dipole-dipole attractions. Because N<sub>2</sub> is nonpolar, its molecules cannot exhibit\n                dipole-dipole attractions. The dipole-dipole attractions between CO molecules are\n                comparably stronger than the dispersion forces between nonpolar N<sub>2</sub> molecules, so CO\n                is expected to have the higher boiling point.</p>\n        </example>\n        <wb:inline idref="dipole_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry </link>under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'