b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\r\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\r\n<workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/"\r\n\txmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\r\n\txmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\r\n\txmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\r\n\txmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="p5_electron_affinity">\r\n\t<head>\r\n\t\t<title>Variation in Electron Affinities</title>\r\n\t\t<objref idref="ion_energy"/>\r\n\t</head>\r\n\t<body>\r\n\t\t<p id="fd88f781675845158d25666b65c5d032">The electron affinity [EA] is the energy change for\r\n\t\t\tthe process of adding an electron to a gaseous atom to form an anion (negative ion).</p>\r\n\t\t<p id="c2d6201f401a4229b9b0def5f6e41a72">\r\n\t\t\t<formula>$$X(g) + e^- \\rightarrow X^-(g) \\ \\ \\ \\ \\mathrm{EA}_1$$</formula>\r\n\t\t</p>\r\n\t\t<p id="ec70c0cc156d42e994bde70259a6d2fb">This process can be either endothermic or\r\n\t\t\texothermic, depending on the element. The EA of some of the elements is given in\r\n\t\t\tperiodic table below. You can see that many of these elements have negative values of\r\n\t\t\tEA, which means that energy is released when the gaseous atom accepts an electron.\r\n\t\t\tHowever, for some elements, energy is required for the atom to become negatively charged\r\n\t\t\tand the value of their EA is positive. (It is important to note that the more negative a\r\n\t\t\tvalue for EA the greater its EA. The values indicate the magnitude of energy change, the\r\n\t\t\tsign indicates the direction.) Just as with ionization energy, subsequent EA values are\r\n\t\t\tassociated with forming ions with more charge. The second EA is the energy associated\r\n\t\t\twith adding an electron to an anion to form a \xe2\x80\x932 ion, and so on.</p>\r\n\t\t<p id="d6d2cfc25e4741e9be45ac8b64a30217">As we might predict, it becomes easier to add an\r\n\t\t\telectron across a series of atoms as the effective nuclear charge of the atoms\r\n\t\t\tincreases. We find, as we go from left to right across a period, EAs tend to become more\r\n\t\t\tnegative. The exceptions found among the elements of group 2 (2A), group 15 (5A), and\r\n\t\t\tgroup 18 (8A) can be understood based on the electronic structure of these groups. The\r\n\t\t\tnoble gases, group 18 (8A), have a completely filled shell and the incoming electron\r\n\t\t\tmust be added to a higher n level, which is more difficult to do. Group 2 (2A) has a\r\n\t\t\tfilled <em style="italic">ns</em> subshell, and so the next electron added goes into the higher energy np, so,\r\n\t\t\tagain, the observed EA value is not as the trend would predict. Finally, group 15 (5A)\r\n\t\t\thas a half-filled <em style="italic">np</em> subshell and the next electron must be paired with an existing np\r\n\t\t\telectron. In all of these cases, the initial relative stability of the electron\r\n\t\t\tconfiguration disrupts the trend in EA.</p>\r\n\t\t<image id="dade0b00097f492f89485ad56bd7e85c" src="../webcontent/affinity1.jpeg"\r\n\t\t\talt="The figure includes a periodic table with the title, \xe2\x80\x9cElectron Affinity Values for Selected Elements (k J per mol).\xe2\x80\x9d The table identifies the row or period number at the left in purple, and group or column numbers in blue above each column. Electron affinity values for representative elements are indicated with values marked with asterisks identifying calculated values. The electron affinity values for group 1 (column 1) elements are provided with the element symbols in the table as follows: H negative 72, L i negative 60, N a negative 53, K negative 48, R b negative 46, and C s negative 45. In group 2, the values are: B e positive 240 asterisk, M g positive 230 asterisk, C a positive 150 asterisk, S r positive 160 asterisk, and B a positive 50 asterisk. In group 13, the values are: B negative 23, A l negative 44, G a negative 40 asterisk, I n negative 40 asterisk, and T l negative 50. In group 14, the values are: C negative 123, S i negative 120, G e negative 115, S n negative 121, and P b negative 101. In group 15 the values are: N 0, P negative 74, A s negative 7, S b negative 101, and B i negative 101. In group 16, the values are: O negative 141, S negative 20, S e negative 195, T e negative 190, and P o negative 170. In group 17, the values are: F negative 322, C l negative 348, B r negative 324, I negative 295, and A t negative 270 asterisk. In group 18, the values are: H e positive 20 asterisk, N e negative 30, A r positive 35 asterisk, K r positive 40 asterisk, X e positive 40 asterisk, and R n positive 40 asterisk."\r\n\t\t\tstyle="inline" vertical-align="middle" width="600">\r\n\t\t\t<caption>This version of the periodic table displays the electron affinity values (in\r\n\t\t\t\tkJ/mol) for selected elements.</caption>\r\n\t\t\t\r\n\t\t</image>\r\n\t\t<p id="f0ef5f1e4d164db4a0d50ce080ce5769"> We also might expect the atom at the top of each\r\n\t\t\tgroup to have the largest EA; their first ionization potentials suggest that these atoms\r\n\t\t\thave the largest effective nuclear charges. However, as we move down a group, we see\r\n\t\t\tthat the second element in the group most often has the greatest EA. The reduction of\r\n\t\t\tthe EA of the first member can be attributed to the small size of the <em style="italic">n</em> = 2 shell and\r\n\t\t\tthe resulting large electron\xe2\x80\x93electron repulsions. For example, chlorine, with an EA\r\n\t\t\tvalue of \xe2\x80\x93348 kJ/mol, has the highest value of any element in the periodic table. The EA\r\n\t\t\tof fluorine is \xe2\x80\x93322 kJ/mol. When we add an electron to a fluorine atom to form a\r\n\t\t\tfluoride anion (F <sup>\xe2\x80\x93</sup> ), we add an electron to the n = 2 shell. The electron is\r\n\t\t\tattracted to the nucleus, but there is also significant repulsion from the other\r\n\t\t\telectrons already present in this small valence shell. The chlorine atom has the same\r\n\t\t\telectron configuration in the valence shell, but because the entering electron is going\r\n\t\t\tinto the <em style="italic">n</em> = 3 shell, it occupies a considerably larger region of space and the\r\n\t\t\telectron\xe2\x80\x93electron repulsions are reduced. The entering electron does not experience as\r\n\t\t\tmuch repulsion and the chlorine atom accepts an additional electron more readily. </p>\r\n\t\t<p id="aef3f85ff4874a18812518dfaefd3aee"/>\r\n\t\t<wb:inline idref="variation_ea_1a72870b9734648619c10bbebcfd2902b" purpose="didigetthis"/>\r\n\t\t<p id="af6f71a4295e434b9534b870ed68989a"/>\r\n\t\t<wb:inline idref="variation_ea_digt2b956a134b2414e2aaa6855d07bb56a60" purpose="didigetthis"/>\r\n\t\t<p id="aeb8d1fdab3064121a995eb2279cb6b41"/>\r\n\t\t<p id="eea53521d92141688a6999db283234de"/>\r\n\t\t<p id="f20f18a4e0ae4a96b64d67db40688da4">The properties discussed in this module (size of\r\n\t\t\tatoms and ions, effective nuclear charge, ionization energies, and electron affinities)\r\n\t\t\tare central to understanding chemical reactivity. For example, because fluorine has an\r\n\t\t\tenergetically favorable EA and a large energy barrier to ionization (IE), it is much\r\n\t\t\teasier to form fluorine anions than cations. Metallic properties including conductivity\r\n\t\t\tand malleability (the ability to be formed into sheets) depend on having electrons that\r\n\t\t\tcan be removed easily. Thus, metallic character increases as we move down a group and\r\n\t\t\tdecreases across a period in the same trend observed for atomic size because it is\r\n\t\t\teasier to remove an electron that is farther away from the nucleus.</p>\r\n\t\t<p id="b330fbf607af401faa337432859f8950"> Adapted from <link\r\n\t\t\thref="http://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface" target="self"\r\n\t\t\tinternal="false">Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\r\n\t\t\t\thref="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" target="self" internal="false"\r\n\t\t\t\t>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License.</link>\r\n\t\t</p>\r\n\t\t<p id="d8a6a2b974824894bdb5b4f30896dba2"> Download for free at <link\r\n\t\t\thref="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\r\n\t\t\ttarget="self" internal="false"\r\n\t\t\t>http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link>\r\n\t\t</p>\r\n\t</body>\r\n</workbook_page>\r\n'