b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n\n<workbook_page id="p5_gas_n_liquid" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Solutions of Gases in Liquids</title>\n        <objref idref="solubility"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>The chemical structures of the solute and solvent dictate the types of forces possible\n            and, consequently, are important factors in determining solubility. For example, under\n            similar conditions, the water solubility of oxygen is approximately three times greater\n            than that of helium, but 100 times less than the solubility of chloromethane,\n                CHCl<sub>3</sub>. Considering the role of the solvent\xe2\x80\x99s chemical structure, note\n            that the solubility of oxygen in the liquid hydrocarbon hexane,\n                C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>14</sub>, is approximately 20 times greater than it is in\n            water.</p>\n        <p>Other factors also affect the solubility of a given substance in a given solvent.\n            Temperature is one such factor, with gas solubility typically decreasing as temperature\n            increases, as seen in the graph below. This is one of the major impacts resulting from\n            the thermal pollution of natural bodies of water.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_11_03_gasdissolv.jpg" alt="This graph shows solubilities of methane, oxygen, carbon monoxide, nitrogen, and helium in 10 superscript negative 3 mol L superscript negative 1 at temperatures ranging from 0 to 30 degrees Celsius. Solubilities as indicated on the graph in decreasing order are methane, oxygen, carbon monoxide, nitrogen, and helium. At ten degrees, solubilities in 10 superscript negative 3mol L superscript negative 1 are approximately as follows; methane 1.9, oxygen 1.8, carbon monoxide 1.2, nitrogen 0.7, and helium 0.4. At twenty degrees, solubilities in 10 superscript negative 3 mol L superscript negative 1 are approximately as follows; methane 1.2, oxygen 1.1, carbon monoxide 0.9, nitrogen 0.5, and helium 0.35.">\n            <caption>The solubilities of these gases in water decrease as the temperature increases.\n                All solubilities were measured with a constant pressure of 101.3 kPa (1 atm) of gas\n                above the solutions.</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>When the temperature of a river, lake, or stream is raised abnormally high, usually due\n            to the discharge of hot water from some industrial process, the solubility of oxygen in\n            the water is decreased. Decreased levels of dissolved oxygen may have serious\n            consequences for the health of the water\xe2\x80\x99s ecosystems and, in severe cases, can result\n            in large-scale fish kills.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_11_03_O2dissolv.jpg" alt="Two photos are shown. The first shows the top portion of a transparent colorless glass of a clear colorless liquid with small bubbles near the interface of the liquid with the container. The second photo shows a portion of a partially frozen body of water with dead fish appearing on in the water and on an icy surface." width="500">\n            <caption>(a) The small bubbles of air in this glass of chilled water formed when the\n                water warmed to room temperature and the solubility of its dissolved air decreased.\n                (b) The decreased solubility of oxygen in natural waters subjected to thermal\n                pollution can result in large-scale fish kills. (credit a: modification of work by\n                Liz West; credit b: modification of work by U.S. Fish and Wildlife\n                Service)</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>The solubility of a gaseous solute is also affected by the partial pressure of solute in\n            the gas to which the solution is exposed. Gas solubility increases as the pressure of\n            the gas increases. Carbonated beverages provide a nice illustration of this\n            relationship. The carbonation process involves exposing the beverage to a relatively\n            high pressure of carbon dioxide gas and then sealing the beverage container, thus\n            saturating the beverage with CO<sub>2</sub> at this pressure. When the beverage\n            container is opened, a familiar hiss is heard as the carbon dioxide gas pressure is\n            released, and some of the dissolved carbon dioxide is typically seen leaving solution in\n            the form of small bubbles. At this point, the beverage is supersaturated with carbon\n            dioxide and, with time, the dissolved carbon dioxide concentration will decrease to its\n            equilibrium value and the beverage will become \xe2\x80\x9cflat.\xe2\x80\x9d</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/CNX_Chem_11_03_beverage.jpg" alt="A dark brown liquid is shown in a clear, colorless container. A thick layer of beige bubbles appear at the surface of the liquid. In the liquid, thirteen small clusters of single black spheres with two red spheres attached to the left and right are shown. Red spheres represent oxygen atoms and black represent carbon atoms. Seven white arrows point upward in the container from these clusters to the bubble layer at the top of the liquid." width="450">\n            <caption>Opening the bottle of carbonated beverage reduces the pressure of the gaseous\n                carbon dioxide above the beverage. The solubility of CO<sub>2</sub> is thus lowered,\n                and some dissolved carbon dioxide may be seen leaving the solution as small gas\n                bubbles. (credit: modification of work by Derrick Coetzee)</caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>For many gaseous solutes, the relation between solubility and partial pressure is a\n            proportional one and can be determined using Henry\'s law.</p>\n        <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        \n        <dl>\n            <dt>Henry\'s Law</dt>\n            <dd>\n                <p>The quantity of an ideal gas that dissolves in a definite volume of liquid is\n                    directly proportional to the pressure of the gas.</p>\n                <formula>$$C_\\mathit g\\mathit\\;\\mathit=\\mathit\\;kP_\\mathit g$$</formula>\n                <p>where <em style="italic">C<sub>g</sub></em> is solubility, <em style="italic"\n                            >P<sub>g</sub></em> is partial pressure, and <em style="italic">k</em>\n                    is a proportionality constant that depends on the identities of the gaseous\n                    solute and solvent, and on the solution temperature. </p>\n            </dd>\n        </dl>\n       <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n        \n        <example>\n            <p>At 20 \xc2\xb0C, the concentration of dissolved oxygen in water exposed to gaseous oxygen at\n                a partial pressure of 101.3 kPa is 1.38 \xc3\x97 10<sup>\xe2\x88\x923</sup> mol L<sup>\xe2\x88\x921</sup>. Use\n                Henry\xe2\x80\x99s law to determine the solubility of oxygen when its partial pressure is 20.7\n                kPa, the approximate pressure of oxygen in earth\xe2\x80\x99s atmosphere.</p>\n            <p>According to Henry\xe2\x80\x99s law, for an ideal solution the solubility, <em style="italic"\n                        >C<sub>g</sub></em>, of a gas (1.38 \xc3\x97 10<sup>\xe2\x88\x923</sup> mol L<sup>\xe2\x88\x921</sup>, in\n                this case) is directly proportional to the pressure, <em style="italic"\n                        >P<sub>g</sub></em>, of the undissolved gas above the solution (101.3 kPa in\n                this case). Because we know both <em style="italic">C<sub>g</sub></em> and <em\n                    style="italic">P<sub>g</sub></em>, we can rearrange this expression to solve for\n                    <em style="italic">k</em>.</p>\n            <formula>$$\\begin{array}{l}C_g\\;=\\;kP_g\\\\k\\;\\;=\\;\\frac{C_g}{P_g}\\\\k\\;=\\;\\frac{1.38\\times10^{-3}\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;\\mathrm\n                L^{-1}}{101.3\\;\\mathrm{kPa}}\\\\k\\;=\\;1.36\\times10^{-5}\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;\\mathrm\n                L^{-1}\\;\\mathrm{kPa}^{-1}\\end{array}$$</formula>\n            <p>Now we can use k to find the solubility at the lower pressure.</p>\n            <formula>$$C_g\\;=\\;kP_g$$</formula>\n            <formula>$$C_g\\;=\\;1.36\\times10^{-5}\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;\\mathrm\n                L^{-1}\\;\\mathrm{kPa}^{-1}\\;\\times\\;20.7\\;\\mathrm{kPa}\\;=\\;2.82\\times10^{-4}\\;\\mathrm{mol}\\;\\mathrm\n                L^{-1}$$</formula>\n            <p>Notice that as the pressure decreased from 101.3 kPa to 20.7 kPa the concentration also decreased, \n                illustrating the direct proportionality of pressure and concentration of a gas in a liquid.\n          \n            </p>\n        </example>\n        <wb:inline idref="henry_lbd" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>\n        <wb:inline idref="henry_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n        <wb:inline idref="like_like_digt" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under  <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'