b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p5_orbital_energy" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Energy of Orbitals</title>\n        <objref idref="quantum_numbers"/>\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n\n        <p>Having introduced the basics of atomic structure and quantum mechanics, we can use our\n            understanding of quantum numbers to determine how atomic orbitals relate to one another.\n            This allows us to determine which orbitals are occupied by electrons in each atom. The\n            specific arrangement of electrons in orbitals of an atom determines many of the chemical\n            properties of that atom.</p>\n        <p>The energy of atomic orbitals increases as the principal quantum number, n, increases. In\n            any atom with two or more electrons, the repulsion between the electrons makes energies\n            of subshells with different values of l differ so that the energy of the orbitals\n            increases within a shell in the order s &lt; p &lt; d &lt; f. The diagram below, which\n            we saw previously, depicts how these two trends in increasing energy relate. The 1s\n            orbital at the bottom of the diagram is the orbital with electrons of lowest energy. The\n            energy increases as we move up to the 2s and then 2p, 3s, and 3p orbitals, showing that\n            the increasing n value has more influence on energy than the increasing l value for\n            small atoms. However, this pattern does not hold for larger atoms. The 3d orbital is\n            higher in energy than the 4s orbital. Such overlaps continue to occur frequently as we\n            move up the chart.</p>\n        <image src="../webcontent/orbenergy1.jpeg" width="600"\n            alt="A table entitled, \xe2\x80\x9cSubshell electron capacity,\xe2\x80\x9d is shown. Along the left side of the table, an upward pointing arrow labeled, \xe2\x80\x9cE,\xe2\x80\x9d is drawn. The table includes three columns. The first column is narrow and is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c2.\xe2\x80\x9d The second is slightly wider and is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c6.\xe2\x80\x9d The third is slightly wider yet and is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c10.\xe2\x80\x9d The fourth is the widest and is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c14.\xe2\x80\x9d The first column begins at the very bottom with a horizontal line segment labeled \xe2\x80\x9c1 s.\xe2\x80\x9d Evenly spaced line segments continue up to 7 s near the top of the column. In the second column, a horizontal dashed line segment labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c2 p,\xe2\x80\x9d appears at a level between the 2 s and 3 s levels. Similarly 3 p appears at a level between 3 s and 4 s, 4 p appears just below 5 s, 5 p appears just below 6 s, and 6 p appears just below 7 s. In the third column, a dashed line labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c3 d,\xe2\x80\x9d appears just below the level of 4 p. Similarly, 4 d appears just below 5 p and 5 d appears just below 6 p. Six d however appears above the levels of both 6 p and 7 s. The far right column entries begin with a dashed line labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c4 f,\xe2\x80\x9d positioned at a level just below 5 d. Similarly, a second dashed line segment appears just below the level of 6 d, which is labeled, \xe2\x80\x9c5 f.\xe2\x80\x9d">\n            <caption>Generalized energy-level diagram for atomic orbitals in an atom with two or\n                more electrons (not to scale). </caption>\n        </image>\n        <p>In their ground state, electrons in successive atoms on the periodic table tend to fill\n            low-energy orbitals first. Thus, many students find it confusing that, for example, the\n            5p orbitals fill immediately after the 4d, and immediately before the 6s. The filling\n            order is based on observed experimental results, and has been confirmed by theoretical\n            calculations. As the principal quantum number, n, increases, the size of the orbital\n            increases and the electrons spend more time farther from the nucleus. Thus, the\n            attraction to the nucleus is weaker and the energy associated with the orbital is higher\n            (less stabilized). This order of orbitals from lowest energy to highest energy is\n            important, but you do not need to memorize it. We will see shortly that this order is\n            represented in the structure of the periodic table.</p>\n        <wb:inline idref="orbital_energy_digt" purpose="didigetthis"/>\n        <p>Adapted from <link href="http://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n                >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0\n                License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n                href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n                >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'