b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p5_volume_pressure" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Gas Laws: Volume and Pressure</title>\n        <objref idref="gas_laws"/>\n        \n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n        <section>\n            <title>Volume and Pressure: Boyle\'s Law</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>If we partially fill an airtight syringe with air, the syringe contains a\n                    specific amount of air at constant temperature, say 25 \xc2\xb0C. If we slowly push in\n                    the plunger while keeping temperature constant, the gas in the syringe is\n                    compressed into a smaller volume and its pressure increases; if we pull out the\n                    plunger, the volume increases and the pressure decreases. This example of the\n                    effect of volume on the pressure of a given amount of a confined gas is true in\n                    general. Decreasing the volume of a contained gas will increase its pressure,\n                    and increasing its volume will decrease its pressure. In fact, if the volume\n                    increases by a certain factor, the pressure decreases by the same factor, and\n                    vice versa.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/vol_pressure_anim.gif" width="500"\n                    alt="Animation showing enclosed volume of gas progressively decreasing in volume at constant temperature. The pressure increases as a result.">\n                    <caption>As seen in the animation above, as volume decrease at constant\n                        temperature, pressure increases.</caption>\n                </image>\n                <p>Animation developed from PhET Interactive Simulations, University of Colorado\n                    Boulder, <link href="https://phet.colorado.edu">https://phet.colorado.edu</link>\n                    .</p>\n\n                <p>Volume-pressure data for an air sample at room temperature are graphed below. </p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/vol_press_graph.jpg" width="650"\n                    alt="This figure contains a diagram and two graphs. The diagram shows a syringe labeled with a scale in m l or c c with multiples of 5 labeled beginning at 5 and ending at 30. The markings halfway between these measurements are also provided. Attached at the top of the syringe is a pressure gauge with a scale marked by fives from 40 on the left to 5 on the right. The gauge needle rests between 10 and 15, slightly closer to 15. The syringe plunger position indicates a volume measurement about halfway between 10 and 15 m l or c c. The first graph is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cV ( m L )\xe2\x80\x9d on the horizontal axis and \xe2\x80\x9cP ( p s i )\xe2\x80\x9d on the vertical axis. Points are labeled at 5, 10, 15, 20, and 25 m L with corresponding values of 39.0, 19.5, 13.0, 9.8, and 6.5 p s i. The points are connected with a smooth curve that is declining at a decreasing rate of change. The second graph is labeled \xe2\x80\x9cV ( m L )\xe2\x80\x9d on the horizontal axis and \xe2\x80\x9c1 divided by P ( p s i )\xe2\x80\x9d on the vertical axis. The horizontal axis is labeled at multiples of 5, beginning at zero and extending up to 35 m L. The vertical axis is labeled by multiples of 0.02, beginning at 0 and extending up to 0.18. Six points indicated by black dots on this graph are connected with a black line segment showing a positive linear trend.">\n                    <caption>When a gas occupies a smaller volume, it exerts a higher pressure; when\n                        it occupies a larger volume, it exerts a lower pressure (assuming the amount\n                        of gas and the temperature do not change). Since <em style="italic">P</em> and <em style="italic">V</em> are inversely\n                        proportional, a graph of 1/<em style="italic">P</em> vs. <em style="italic">V</em> is linear.</caption>\n                </image>\n                <p>Unlike the <em style="italic">P</em>\xe2\x88\x92<em style="italic">T</em> and <em style="italic">V</em>\xe2\x88\x92<em style="italic">T</em> relationships, pressure and volume are not directly\n                    proportional to each other. Instead, <em style="italic">P</em> and <em style="italic">V</em> exhibit inverse proportionality.</p>\n                <p>The relationship between the volume and pressure of a given amount of gas at\n                    constant temperature was first published by the English natural philosopher\n                    Robert Boyle over 300 years ago. It is summarized in the statement now known as\n                    <extra><anchor>Boyle\xe2\x80\x99s law</anchor><meaning><material><p>volume of a given number of moles of gas held at constant temperature is inversely proportional to the pressure under which it is measured</p></material></meaning></extra>: The volume of a given amount of gas held at constant temperature is\n                    inversely proportional to the pressure under which it is measured.</p>\n\n                <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n                <dl>\n                    <dt><em>Boyle\'s Law</em></dt>\n                    <dd>\n                        <p>Boyle\'s law states that the volume of a given amount of gas held at\n                            constant temperature is inversely proportional to the pressure under\n                            which it is measured. Mathematically this can be represented as:</p>\n                        <formula>$$\\begin{array}{l}P\\;\\propto\\;\\frac1V\\\\P\xe2\x8b\x85V\\;=\\;k\\\\P_1V_1\\;=\\;P_2V_2\\end{array}$$</formula>\n                    </dd>\n                </dl>\n                <image src="../../../webcontent/green_line.png"></image>\n                <p>Graphically, this relationship is shown by the straight line that results when\n                    plotting the inverse of the pressure (1/<em style="italic">P</em>) versus the volume (<em style="italic">V</em>), or the inverse\n                    of volume (1/<em style="italic">V</em>) versus the pressure (<em style="italic">P</em>). Graphs with curved lines are\n                    difficult to read accurately at low or high values of the variables, and they\n                    are more difficult to use in fitting theoretical equations and parameters to\n                    experimental data. For those reasons, scientists often try to find a way to\n                    \xe2\x80\x9clinearize\xe2\x80\x9d their data. If we plot <em style="italic">P</em> versus <em style="italic">V</em>, we obtain a hyperbola as seen\n                    below.</p>\n                <image src="../webcontent/vol_press_graph2.jpg" width="500"\n                    alt="This diagram shows two graphs. In a, a graph is shown with volume on the horizontal axis and pressure on the vertical axis. A curved line is shown on the graph showing a decreasing trend with a decreasing rate of change. In b, a graph is shown with volume on the horizontal axis and one divided by pressure on the vertical axis. A line segment, beginning at the origin of the graph, shows a positive, linear trend.">\n                    <caption>The relationship between pressure and volume is inversely proportional.\n                        (a) The graph of <em style="italic">P</em> vs. <em style="italic">V</em> is a hyperbola, whereas (b) the graph of (1/<em style="italic">P</em>) vs.\n                        <em style="italic">V</em> is linear.</caption>\n                </image>\n                <example>\n                    <p>The sample of gas has a volume of 15.0 mL at a pressure of 0.884 atm.\n                        Determine the pressure of the gas at a volume of 7.5 mL.</p>\n                    <p>Because we are looking for the pressure change caused by a volume change at\n                        constant temperature, we will use Boyle\'s law equation.</p>\n                    <formula>$$P_1V_1\\;\\;=\\;\\;P_2V_2$$</formula>\n                    <p>Identify the variables in the problem.</p>\n                    <p>$$\\begin{array}{l}P_1\\;=\\;0.884\\;atm\\;\\;\\\\V_1\\;=\\;15.0\\;mL\\;\\;\\\\P_2\\;=\\;?\\;\\;\\\\V_2\\;=\\;7.5\\;mL\\end{array}$$</p>\n                    <p>Now we will plug the values into the equation:</p>\n                    <formula>$$0.884\\;\\mathrm{atm}\\;\\times\\;15.0\\;\\mathrm{mL}\\;=\\;P_2\\;\\times\\;7.5\\;\\mathrm{mL}$$</formula>\n                    <p>Rearranging variables to solve for <em style="italic">P</em><sub>2</sub> gives:</p>\n                    <formula>$$P_2\\;=\\;\\frac{0.884\\;\\mathrm{atm}\\;\\times\\;15.0\\;\\mathrm{mL}}{7.5\\;\\mathrm{mL}}\\;$$</formula>\n                    <formula>$$P_2\\;=\\;1.77\\;\\mathrm{atm}$$</formula>\n                </example>\n                <wb:inline idref="gaslaws_volpress_lbddfd7d59702594af58d6390037349ab8e" purpose="learnbydoing"></wb:inline>\n                <wb:inline idref="gaslaws_volpress_digtf091d7d5006c4fecb89e44b8a4a6f79e" purpose="didigetthis"></wb:inline>\n               \n            </body>\n        </section>\n        \n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n\n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'