b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n\n\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p6_phase_summary" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n\n\n    <head>\n        <title>Module Summary and Quiz</title>\n\n    </head>\n\n    <body>\n<section>\n    <title>Phase Changes: Summary</title>\n    <body>\n        <p>Phase transitions are processes that convert matter from one physical state into another.\n            There are six phase transitions between the three phases of matter. Melting,\n            vaporization, and sublimation are all endothermic processes, requiring an input of heat\n            to overcome intermolecular attractions. The reciprocal transitions of freezing,\n            condensation, and deposition are all exothermic processes, involving heat as\n            intermolecular attractive forces are established or strengthened. The temperatures at\n            which phase transitions occur are determined by the relative strengths of intermolecular\n            attractions and are, therefore, dependent on the chemical identity of the substance.</p>\n        <p>The temperature and pressure conditions at which a substance exists in solid, liquid, and\n            gaseous states are summarized in a phase diagram for that substance. Phase diagrams are\n            combined plots of three pressure-temperature equilibrium curves: solid-liquid,\n            liquid-gas, and solid-gas. These curves represent the relationships between\n            phase-transition temperatures and pressures. The point of intersection of all three\n            curves represents the substance\xe2\x80\x99s triple point\xe2\x80\x94the temperature and pressure at which all\n            three phases are in equilibrium. At pressures below the triple point, a substance cannot\n            exist in the liquid state, regardless of its temperature. The terminus of the liquid-gas\n            curve represents the substance\xe2\x80\x99s critical point, the pressure and temperature above\n            which a liquid phase cannot exist.</p>\n    </body>\n</section>\n        <section>\n            <title>End of Lesson Questions</title>\n            <body>\n                <p>Before you take the quiz, please evaluate your understanding of the\n                    learning objectives for the <em style="italic">Phase Changes</em> module and use the\n                    <em style="emphasis">My Response</em> link below to ask any questions you might have about\n                    the material that you would like the instructor to address. Your questions can\n                    be for clarification of the material or further insight. Your self-evaluation\n                    and questions may also shape the discussions in class.</p>\n                <p>Your responses will not be graded, but will be available for your instructor.</p>\n                <activity idref="phase_change_feedback" purpose="myresponse"/>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n        \n        <activity idref="phase_change_pooled_quiz" purpose="quiz"></activity>\n        \n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry </link>under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n        \n\n\n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n'