b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC " -//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd">\n<workbook_page id="p6O_km_summary" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/"\n    xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/"\n    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/"\n    xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/">\n    \n    \n    <head>\n        <title>The Kinetic-Molecular Theory: Summary </title>\n        \n    </head>\n    \n    <body>\n        <section>\n            <title></title>\n            <body>\n                <p>The kinetic molecular theory is a simple but very effective model that\n                    effectively explains ideal gas behavior. The theory assumes that gases consist\n                    of widely separated molecules of negligible volume that are in constant motion,\n                    colliding elastically with one another and the walls of their container with\n                    average velocities determined by their absolute temperatures. The individual\n                    molecules of a gas exhibit a range of velocities, the distribution of these\n                    velocities being dependent on the temperature of the gas and the mass of its\n                    molecules. </p>\n                <p>Gaseous atoms and molecules move freely and randomly through space. Diffusion is\n                    the process whereby gaseous atoms and molecules are transferred from regions of\n                    relatively high concentration to regions of relatively low concentration.\n                    Effusion is a similar process in which gaseous species pass from a container to\n                    a vacuum through very small orifices. The rates of effusion of gases are\n                    inversely proportional to the square roots of their densities or to the square\n                    roots of their atoms/molecules\xe2\x80\x99 masses (Graham\xe2\x80\x99s law). </p>\n                <p>Gas molecules possess a finite volume and experience forces of attraction for one\n                    another. Consequently, gas behavior is not necessarily described well by the\n                    ideal gas law. Under conditions of low pressure and high temperature, these\n                    factors are negligible, the ideal gas equation is an accurate description of gas\n                    behavior, and the gas is said to exhibit ideal behavior. However, at lower\n                    temperatures and higher pressures, corrections for molecular volume and\n                    molecular attractions are required to account for finite molecular size and\n                    attractive forces. The van der Waals equation is a modified version of the ideal\n                    gas law that can be used to account for the non-ideal behavior of gases under\n                    these conditions. </p>\n            </body>\n        </section>\n      \n        \n        <p>Adapted from <link href="https://cnx.org/contents/havxkyvS@9.422:b39avmGq@29/Preface"\n            >Openstax Chemistry</link> under <link\n                href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> Creative Commons Attribution\n                4.0 License. </link></p>\n        <p>Download for free at <link\n            href="http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312"\n            >http://cnx.org/contents/85abf193-2bd2-4908-8563-90b8a7ac8df6@9.312.</link></p>\n        \n        \n    </body>\n</workbook_page>\n\n'