b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ae0799c90cfc454bb41bf2541c88cc87"><head><title>The Law of Small Numbers</title></head><body><image id="bf76bf98af29464a8f10e8c90b82041c" src="../webcontent/1_rss.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="532" width="650"><caption><p id="e5c344dd878c49b28ac2c7fb8b953add">Figure 1. Kidney Cancer Rate in Each U.S. County (2007-2011). (Source: https://dataremixed.com)</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b9d63cfe1dff45fb90a7a6bd7583f467">Although we know that we should not make inferences from not enough data, we often forget that. We tend to overgeneralize from small samples. Sometimes, this is called the <em>law of small numbers</em>. Now, there is no statistical law of small numbers\xe2\x80\x93it is used here as a satire, playing on <em style="italic">the law of large numbers</em>. The law of large numbers states that, under general conditions, <em style="italic">as the sample size gets large, the mean of the sample will be near the mean of the overall population with a very high probability.</em></p><p id="de39b89690d94603b9566a11e08143b0">In his book <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow" target="new" internal="false">Thinking, Fast and Slow</link>, Daniel Kahneman describes examples of cognitive biases of fast thinking. Drawing naive conclusions and making inferences about the population from such a small sample size is one of them. The book provides a great illustration of the dangers of acting as if the law of small numbers is actually a law.</p><p id="f75c1a05e861453aa480833786b1cd39">A study of the incidence of kidney cancer in the 3,141 counties of the United States reveals a remarkable pattern. You may find out that the counties in the United States with the lowest incidence of kidney cancer are mostly rural rather than urban. Now, you can probably imagine why that&apos;s true if you&apos;re healthy or living out of the countryside with better air, or maybe you&apos;re eating from the food that you&apos;re growing, and you&apos;re getting better nutrition. You can come up with some interesting reasons why this rural lifestyle would lead to a lower rate of kidney cancer.</p><p id="dce0a4aa21f64d4f9bd9447a977542a0">Now consider also the counties in which the incidence of kidney cancer is highest. You may find these ailing counties tend to be also mostly rural, sparsely populated, and located in the Midwest, the South, and the West. So now you&apos;re going to maybe come up with some reasonable explanation: &quot;Oh, well, It is easy to infer that their high cancer rates might be directly due to the poverty of the rural lifestyle\xe2\x80\x93no access to good medical care, a high-fat diet, and too much alcohol, too much tobacco.\xe2\x80\x9d</p><p id="a5e60cc372284d3ba3a9d8c9a2271ef7">None of these explanations is correct. What&apos;s really going on is that the rural counties have fewer people. So we have a smaller sample size and, therefore, more variation in our observed kidney cancer rate even though there isn&apos;t any difference in the actual cancer rate because we have more variation for the small counties. Both the lowest and the highest rates come from the counties with a small population, the rural counties.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'