b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="b5ccf28bb8484442a03caa4cece47534"><head><title>Overview</title></head><body><p id="f4d847f5c53a4c43a425cd2d8651c7e9">Having introduced the data science lifecycle in the previous unit, we will now discuss the more concrete steps that you should take in your own data science project. Similar to traditional software development projects, Data Science projects should also be guided by documentation to support the different steps taken while embarking on the project. The documentations provide a framework for <em>envisioning the project</em>, <em>gathering requirements</em>, <em>designing the solution</em>, and <em>planning concrete milestones</em>. In this unit, we explore each of the four flavors of the framework, their importance, benefits, and best practices.  </p><p id="ef9ac1fb6b8340c29f4d634275d8f2b2">As you have learned in a previous unit, gaining an understanding of the business need and formulating project objectives (business and analytic) are best practices for successfully meeting client expectations. Once the project objectives have been defined, the project team will identify the needs and constraints of stakeholders and the current system or environment related to the business need; this is referred to as the <em style="italic">Requirements Gathering Process</em>.</p><p id="d4ed9f8236ae4081a1e14321966fe8cf"><em style="italic">Requirements gathering</em> establishes communication between the solutions development team (referred to as the project team in this unit) and the business stakeholders. The objective of the requirements gathering process is to define the system inputs, processes, outputs, and interfaces. When properly done, requirements gathering will positively influence the outcome of a project. Requirements gathering can also help the project team to visualize the intended solution.</p><p id="a118a59efdb243689e4e72d1fa2fe936">The requirements gathering process involves input from the <em style="italic">system users</em> and <em style="italic">system owners</em>. A system user interacts with the solution, and a system owner (who can also be a user) is an official who is responsible for decisions made about systems within their organization. In this unit, we will refer to these roles as <em style="italic">stakeholders</em>.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'