b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="bce9e0d10f3742ac9807040cfe2e749f"><head><title>What is Data Science Ethics?</title><objref idref="f8c2d1d75430476e95a19a3c4c74c3fc" /><objref idref="bf89331844044b759699aaef71d0fd04" /></head><body><p id="cbdb51d3ab4b4c06ab0dd5238a7efbe9">As we practice data science, it is important that we do so with an ethical framework in mind. There are many ways we can cause unintended negative consequences through our work as data scientists if we blindly focus on the techniques we learn without considering their consequences. In this module, we will talk about how we could potentially make mistakes and how we can avoid making these mistakes.</p><section id="ba590ce56c7e43f59909e90ce0545be3"><title>Ethics</title><body><p id="ee1edeb4f5134f78a42650c9343354c8">Let\xe2\x80\x99s start with a simple definition of ethics. Ethics are rules that we, as fellow citizens, voluntarily follow because we believe they make the world a better place. Ethics guide us to distinguish right from wrong and are at the bedrock of human civilization.</p><p id="f3280c302b7c4e11af0089220405f324">Consider this simple example: Ethics stop you from shoplifting. There may be other things that could stop you from shoplifting, such as the possibility of being caught by the store owner,  but ethics would stop you even if there is no one in the store to catch you. What stops you is the fundamental principle of what you think is right. Ethics are the shared values of the society that compel us to think about how we want to be treated, which then translates into how we treat others.</p><p id="b5fd04acf1014854bd6a5b99bfd47fd2">Ethics are distinct from the law. Consider an example where you tell a friend a secret, and the friend promises not to tell anyone else. The friend then breaks that promise and spreads your story. The friend may not have broken any law and is unlikely to face any legal consequences. Nonetheless, we can agree that the friend\xe2\x80\x99s behavior is unethical because it is a common principle of human relationships and interactions to keep one\xe2\x80\x99s promises, especially to one\xe2\x80\x99s own friends.</p><p id="ab44df6dbd7e4cd4b623c0e249f590f4">Ethics are not laws, but laws often follow the shared social values of ethics. Laws are created and enforced to ensure these common social values. However, despite having generally agreed upon shared values, not everyone will act in accordance with those values, either because they don\xe2\x80\x99t share them or because they\xe2\x80\x99ve justified to themselves in some way that they\xe2\x80\x99re not truly violating them. For example, just because we have a shared principle saying it is wrong to shoplift doesn\xe2\x80\x99t mean there are no shoplifters in society. It merely means that we all have agreed that stealing is wrong as a society and can therefore pass legislation that punishes thieves. These laws are then enforced by our criminal justice system, which also determines the punishments for those who violate them.</p></body></section><section id="a48c3d2ee2ed420192299eeb5e55ab8b"><title>The Tragedy of the Commons</title><body><p id="c0fd584c1d3349bea275e200bc3e6721">One practical way to think about the benefit of ethics is through the lens of economics. In general, society as a whole does best when individuals maximize their own private returns. This is the fundamental principle of a modern free-market economy. However, there are situations where we see that the results of collective actions from individuals under the name of maximizing private benefits are a detriment to society.</p><p id="dec1c9ec7f6241b7a2db6d96adeda4fd">When individuals act in their own interest while collectively accessing a public resource (called a commons), it is likely they will ultimately deplete or otherwise corrupt that resource. This situation is known as <em>the tragedy of the commons</em>, a term used for the first time by Garret Hardin in 1968 and published in <link href="https://cmu.idm.oclc.org/login?url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/1724745" target="new" internal="false">Science Magazine</link> (requires CMU credentials to access). <em>The tragedy of the commons</em> stresses that \xe2\x80\x9cthe population problem has no technical solution; it requires a fundamental extension in morality,\xe2\x80\x9d in which \xe2\x80\x9cpopulation\xe2\x80\x9d refers to members of society and \xe2\x80\x9cextension in morality\xe2\x80\x9d refers to ethical principles. It explains individuals\xe2\x80\x99 tendency to make decisions based on selfish needs that sometimes lead them to ignore the best interests of the group as a whole\xe2\x80\x93 of which they are a part themselves.</p><p id="ca3ab6712b6c415ea84bd90bc0b3f3c7">In 2009, Elinor Ostrom became the first woman to be awarded the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences for revisiting the tragedy of the commons and her work on <link href="https://doi-org.cmu.idm.oclc.org/10.1017/CBO9781316423936" target="new" internal="false">governing the commons</link> (requires CMU credentials to access). She showed cases where such \xe2\x80\x9ctragedy\xe2\x80\x9d was not inevitable and that if humans cooperated with one another and monitored and enforced rules to manage the commons, then the \xe2\x80\x9ctragedy\xe2\x80\x9d could be avoided.</p><p id="a08477c573ae466eba279b4174d0a3c3">Now that we\xe2\x80\x99ve learned about what ethics are and how together we can avoid unintended negative consequences from selfish and unethical practices, in the subsequent modules, we will link this with data science and demonstrate the core values of ethical data science practices to motivate the discussion of how data scientists can apply ethical principles.</p></body></section></body></workbook_page>\n'