b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="bdc55f33fb3346febdd1425a47325913"><head><title>Computer Vision Applications</title></head><body><section id="cbedf9235c444dabac49cb1742e4a445"><title>Computer Vision Applications and the three \xe2\x80\x9cRs\xe2\x80\x9d of Computer Vision</title><body><p id="f1b06981aff044269b35992cfa9dd59c"><link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jitendra_Malik" target="new" internal="false">Jitendra Malik</link>, a computer vision pioneer, proposed the &apos;Three R&apos;s&apos; as the classic problems of computational vision: reconstruction, recognition, and (re)organization. You might have come across many computer vision applications in your daily life, which are most likely attempts to solve one of the three Rs. In this section, we brief a few common applications of computer vision.</p><ol id="f9a8cb6f292446aa8b553732b1c4d75f"><li><p id="fd153880d23b4c46bea4e775eca73ac5">Optical character recognition (OCR)</p><image id="fb241f2c97eb48548bb265a9e096a212" src="../webcontent/image-fa4af4b47a6b4c43af857ae981212dc6-4.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="262" width="500"><caption><p id="c5fa1b2d29d8435384de54443156b07c">Figure 4. LeNet 5.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ea9baa2860b84fbaafa5e07439755e00"><em>Optical character recognition</em> or <em>optical character reader</em> (<em>OCR</em>) is a technology to convert images of text into actual text. The text images can be typed, handwritten, or printed into machine-encoded text such as a scanned document, a photo of a document, or an image that contains the text. Figure 4 shows the results of probably the first OCR task, LeNet. OCR is a commonly used method to digitalize printed text to reduce storage size and enable editability and searchability.</p></li><li><p id="f2def9693c3d435885795ff999256a65">Object Recognition</p><p id="fbaba4d25efb411a8ac62180dd84cfc9"><em>Object recognition </em>is a computer vision technique for identifying objects in images or videos. It might be relatively easy for a human to look at a photograph or watch a video and spot people, objects, scenes, and visual details. However, it is not as straightforward for a computer not only to recognize the items but also to understand what the items mean to the level of understanding of a human. Object recognition is a key technology behind driverless cars (Figure 5), enabling them to recognize a stop sign or to distinguish a pedestrian from a lamp post. It is also valuable for disease identification in biological imaging, industrial inspection, and robotic vision applications, just to name a few.</p><image id="cd0b62703fef40cf93343aa8dca05c41" src="../webcontent/image-fa4af4b47a6b4c43af857ae981212dc6-5.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="400" width="548"><caption><p id="e15c9e8eb450496ea60e5b9db910b3f4">Figure 5. Object recognition technology from Tesla\xe2\x80\x99s Autopilot and full self-driving capabilities.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></li><li><p id="a45aacac11424eb295d08f2a2adda943">Face Recognition</p><image id="a9f3e259e76c4eaea991ae60a1db7f4d" src="../webcontent/image-fa4af4b47a6b4c43af857ae981212dc6-6.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="341" width="650"><caption><p id="c7c60b8cf20a4a5e82813c1ff00a9ab3">Figure 6. Apple\xe2\x80\x99s Face ID.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ee9c8254c2484352ad793f678fbdf856"><em>Facial recognition</em> is a specific case of object detection where the primary object is a human face. While similar to object detection as a task, where features are detected and localized, facial recognition performs not only detection but also recognition of the detected face. Facial recognition systems search for standard features and landmarks like eyes, lips, or a nose and classify a face using these features and the positioning of these items. The facial recognition system is used as an ID verification process to authenticate users for security purposes, such as Apple&apos;s Face ID (Figure 6), <link href="https://www.travelandleisure.com/airlines-airports/clear-airport-security" target="new" internal="false">Clear</link> airport security service, and the United States driver&apos;s license photo database.</p><p id="e8300394a88341979e4095bc7b062eac">Image augmentation applications on various social media services, such as Snapchat, use an algorithm to detect faces and perform augmentation to swap faces in an image for entertainment (Figure 7).</p><image id="fa73666bb6d44c1587df7688898c7b88" src="../webcontent/image-fa4af4b47a6b4c43af857ae981212dc6-7.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="450" width="617"><caption><p id="add38e53e1a248ee945ffe9e53529105">Figure 7. Snapchat\xe2\x80\x99s Face Swap.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></li><li><p id="b07c464c853b4b2fa5c45e4af466cd2c">Vision-based Biometrics</p><image id="c1bb96bd5bde4a5e9d33ea6a5c8d906a" src="../webcontent/image-fa4af4b47a6b4c43af857ae981212dc6-8.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="450" width="617"><caption><p id="b9584b25860d4df5afd2d232f9da91b3">Figure 8. Sharbat Gula, photographed in 1984 and 2002.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="b19b12391f8b44aa9f78b467692828a3">Sharbat Gula, one of the students in an informal school at the Nasir Bagh refugee camp in Afghanistan, was identified 18 years later from a photograph taken in 1984 when she was 12, using an analysis of her iris pattern image (Figure 8). <link href="https://www.robots.ox.ac.uk/~az/lectures/est/iris.pdf" target="new" internal="false">Daugman (2004)</link> computed IrisCodes from both of her eyes from the photograph in 1984 and 2002, respectively, and matched them using a Hamming Distance to confirm that the images are of the same person. You can read more about the story <link href="https://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~jgd1000/afghan.html" target="new" internal="false">here</link>.</p></li></ol></body></section></body></workbook_page>\n'