b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="bee01d50fdef4392a022cb08e3055bfc"><head><title>Writing a Requirements Document</title></head><body><p id="bf0fb6d25cfb4fe8944a2933096841d7">The requirements document should not only state all the hardware and software requirements of the project but also other requirements such as functional and non-functional requirements and the intended group of users that the project aims to target. The most significant sub-headings that must be covered in a requirements document have been detailed below.</p><p id="edb23b48c69943d19c9c8478a94784ea">The first section is the introduction which would either include an introduction to the project or to the upcoming sections in the document. If the project is more research-oriented, the introduction should summarize the experiments that will be conducted during the entire duration of the project. For industrial or software-oriented projects, it should describe the various interfaces that will be developed for the system. The document will also mention how testing will be done and how various modules will be run together. This would make developers think about the various sub-sections involved in the overall project. The intended users section will detail the various groups of users involved in the project and their corresponding use cases so that the requirements of each group of users can be determined beforehand. This would help develop a solution that fits all the requirements of all the various stakeholders.</p><p id="bd1bfaf25a0a45c79ab982e83e54bd7a">The next section in the requirements document will be the system functionality section. This section describes the goals of the project using multiple simplified diagrams, such as context diagrams and component diagrams, which can be used to illustrate these goals. </p><p id="d6b8ceecb9c5451287cbd349e5438737">While developing this document, the non-functional requirements, including various quality attributes of the system like speed, reliability, and performance, will be considered. This will help developers handpick the most important non-functional requirements for the system, which would be achievable within the time frame of the project. The use cases of the project must be kept in mind when selecting the non-functional requirements. Other constraints like hardware and software resources, monetary resources, and human effort must also be taken into account before committing to the functional and non-functional requirements of the project. The requirements document would be the preliminary attempt at defining the overall resource requirement of the project for meeting the goals of the entire project. Developers should begin thinking about a design methodology while preparing this document.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'