b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="c3afdfacb9204ec0a2bf90c5361ee997"><head><title>Design Considerations</title></head><body><p id="fd2d54f792654fc3abbfa2b4d1b529b9">Before we talk deeper about diagrams, it is important to outline what factors will affect your design, i.e., what you have to keep in mind when designing your solution.</p><p id="d20a319eaf1044d8a2e2cf7089094c38">For this section, it will be useful to go back to your requirements document. Most constraints will be apparent from the Non-Functional Requirements (NFRs) and Scope sections, but other sections like Intended Users may also bring up some interesting constraints.</p><p id="dc43961bb4784c15bbd62e7975d3fd44">Some examples are:</p><ol id="af0e8472db7e48c3a3ccc66fc6007e43"><li><p id="c64635500c21477193aba183ee3a86e6">If your system is a prototype or a proof of concept, you may want to include that assumption in this section. Accordingly, in your design, the deployment model may not be really important as it is a research project. You can have a \xe2\x80\x9cbest-case\xe2\x80\x9d deployment model, i.e., a model that indicates the best way to deploy a full-scale version of the idea.</p></li><li><p id="e098c26a73e74b4eb1392d0385b3deb7">Information about the intended users of the system (e.g., working professionals or consumers) may affect the type of information your system has to expose. In your design, this will translate into specific outlets of information from your model.</p></li><li><p id="f3a423314f2a4aa4b749ea4ce2ac0a9d">Related to the above point, if your system deals with sensitive consumer information, your design will have to be careful of which outlets are exposed to the external world and what information is part of that outlet.</p></li><li><p id="d3281172a62f4f569dfa0ca149fee0d7">If performance is an important NFR, then a good assumption to have is the response time for your system (e.g., the requirement may indicate that an API call has to respond back within no more than 2 ms).</p></li><li><p id="f8f53bb17b9d493fa437692654ce176e">If the client has specifically asked for the system to be deployed on AWS/Azure/GCP or wants a specific platform to be used for the solution, one should make sure to include this requirement here. This will affect your design, as these platforms have their own constraints, which you may want to consider in your design.</p></li></ol></body></workbook_page>\n'