b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="c3f0a1483ed946b6ad84ef1dde3ebbbb"><head><title>Module 11 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="a04a892289874ac4bcbea0e9b4fd58eb"><li><p id="c77bea6a8dd349318de15913a442ac06">Statistics provides methods for planning how to gather data for research studies, summarizing the data, and Making predictions based on the data. Data is typically categorized as numeric or categorical. Quantitative data is represented as continuous or discrete values, while categorical data can be nominal or ordinal values.</p></li><li><p id="ae7855d687d9443a857a95598221bc61">Structured Data has organized facts that are presented in fixed formats and are easy to extract. Unstructured Data does not neatly fit in the row, and column structure or cannot be maintained in formats that are uniform.</p></li><li><p id="fe30277f76124a5188ddf3e2d6f2e2e3">Unlike structured data, unstructured data can be stored without a predefined schema. New-generation database frameworks, also known as NoSQL databases, have been developed specifically to handle this type of data.</p></li><li><p id="d9bb96bd72ad4415974867152109a65b">Internal data is data collected and/or controlled by an organization, and external data is data that is collected from sources outside of an organization.</p></li><li><p id="e4e59abef11c43059f5c6f463adb19aa">Data Wrangling is the process of cleaning, formatting, and enriching raw data to make it usable for analysis. Data wrangling is sometimes referred to as feature engineering. Feature engineering involves selecting the right features from the data to further improve the performance of your models.</p></li><li><p id="a3aa1f40aff54520923c32260adc7c78">Dummy variables are a technique that allows for categorical data to be transformed into 0s and 1s. A dataset containing customer spending data can have a categorical variable, gender, with two categories, male and female. The gender variable can be converted to binary/dummy variables.</p></li><li><p id="b95a92fb0c0b4c4084cf3a8282e42e18">The purpose of descriptive statistics is to make it easier to assimilate information. The exploratory data analysis (EDA) process comprises visualizing data to allow a data scientist or a data analyst to explore datasets. EDA uses non-graphical techniques and graphical techniques to explore the data.</p></li><li><p id="e67351ef444e4e17b3be1c5009dfb3b5">Correlation or correlation coefficient describes how strong the association between two variables, x, and y, is in terms of how closely the data follow a straight-line trend. It is a different measure than covariance because it describes both the direction and strength of the linear relationship between the variables.</p></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'