b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="c98c595df5fe4c708d82f2a4bb2726a5"><head><title>Problem Identification</title><objref idref="b06d4e6407ac4dd2b30b6244bb1f3509" /></head><body><p id="b979eafb29394823bac3fe4b77edd961">Just like other business processes, a data science project is complex with moving parts that include understanding the business needs and objectives of the company that influences the stakeholders, existing system environment, and support structure. The data whose analysis supports the proposed solution may have to be gathered both from inside and outside the organization. Overall, this process of initiating and executing a data science project can be challenging, and it requires technical expertise as well as domain guidance. A <link href="https://www.gartner.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2018-02-13-gartner-says-nearly-half-of-cios-are-planning-to-deploy-artificial-intelligence" target="new" internal="false">Gartner study</link> showed that 85% of data science projects fall short of expectations. Project expectations are defined by your client, and the data science team creates a solution vision that will meet their expectations. The path to defining those project expectations must be tread carefully to avoid project failure. </p><p id="a763490cdb9542fd943e6cf08beca1d4">According to the <link href="https://www.information-age.com/projects-continue-fail-alarming-rate-123470803/" target="new" internal="false">Chaos Report</link>, a group that tracks IT project failure, reports that data science projects might fail due to multiple reasons, including those that occur in general IT projects. However, there are some unique issues that data science teams must consider to ensure the success of their projects. Some of the reasons for data science project failure include:</p><ul id="a828cbef1fe542aabe6b28e1de3990a1"><li><p id="e0612d41eab74c98b7c9c23c9f39e158">Insufficient or inappropriate data,</p></li><li><p id="ec824ba4d01d45a98c66c4ab20191d69">Lack of technical data science skills,</p></li><li><p id="c47690fde0d0497aa8c435e18a2dad07">Issues with project management,</p></li><li><p id="efbe31e438e84a54b4b8f50e91b95fc1">Inaccurate interpretation of results, and</p></li><li><p id="c5afb6bbef004cf9a4c1d4fb158fe5d7">Mismanaged client expectations.</p></li></ul><p id="caccb274cfd24490b944f25c87625514">The above-mentioned issues are related to a misunderstanding regarding the client\xe2\x80\x99s business needs and to inadequate communication between the data science project team and the business stakeholders. It is important to identify and understand your client\xe2\x80\x99s business needs, environment, and current solution. This will increase the chances of meeting the business objectives and providing the right analytical solution.</p><p id="bcafbeabf4f14fad8f4717c9e4a9e94a">In this unit, we will discuss how you derive analytic objectives from a client\xe2\x80\x99s or organization\xe2\x80\x99s business needs. In doing so, you need to broaden your understanding of the data science process beyond the gathering of data and the application of machine learning methods to a more or less clean dataset. While these aspects are certainly important parts of many data science projects, being a successful data scientist involves being mindful of the big picture to envision, design, implement and ultimately deploy creative solutions for real-world problems. You will find that this course introduces a data science approach that is grounded in scientific research, software engineering principles, and experimentation.</p><p id="a7490af149954da882d870272b926e0b">The remainder of this unit focuses on the ability to identify problems and envision a solution, which is among the most important skills a data scientist must possess.</p><wb:inline idref="newfca0e9a8e5cf4898b05d2cd1922084a7" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'