b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="c9c4a0e70194444fb7f47474704b64e7"><head><title>Framing Analytic Requirements</title><objref idref="fddc9352f8594dcf9e301b1159522f8d" /><objref idref="e9e19ee410aa4e5c847c62559c95be7b" /></head><body><p id="d2667c56fc7543ada45bfc98cc87b38a">Once it is determined that an organization is Data Science ready, the project team will gather requirements that will enable the development of an analytics solution to meet the defined business need(s).</p><p id="c72054172a6c474493c037bcff31e9c1">Let us explore a scenario with a two-year college that is seeking to improve the recruitment of new students and increase the retention of existing students by 10% over the next five (5) years. The college would like to use predictive modeling to achieve this objective. The predictive model should provide insights that can inform business processes related to recruitment and retention.</p><p id="e5dffc8f06c5481c930ae77b45a6bc30">Upon meeting with project sponsors, assessing the client for data science readiness, and defining business and analytic objectives, the project team embarks on gathering requirements for this project. The business analyst (BA) identifies all necessary stakeholders and systems related to recruitment and retention in the college. The BA takes the lead in eliciting information about user needs and system constraints.</p><p id="e757b9d0676c423980a8ec04ea4fb17e">In this scenario, requirements elicitation involves interviewing stakeholders and document analysis. Once user and system requirements are defined, the project team can now define the requirements for the analytic solution.</p><p id="f08a263de82e49d1b48dbd9705381ee8"><em>Data Requirements </em></p><p id="f1975649025043d9a97a4201655e36fd">While distilling analytic objectives for this project, the project team determined that an exploratory analysis of the college\xe2\x80\x99s prospective student data is needed to perform segmentation for targeted advertising and recruitment efforts. Prior to performing a segmentation task or cluster analysis, the team defines the requirements for the data that will be explored.</p><p id="f0fc75226db44e2abd9cfca6f3a37718">Defining data requirements involves understanding the data needed to reach the business and analytic objectives. Defining the data requirements will also involve considerations for data sources, data management, and data extraction. The following questions must be answered to determine the data requirements:</p><ul id="aca9adffaec34c7f9280676bf4261ac2"><li><p id="c7c0f2271c9a4e46b12b99e93670d894">How can data be used to meet the business and analytic objectives? </p></li><li><p id="a749f276e69946e995f910601d91efba">What data is needed for developing the analytic solution? Can the data be collected from credible sources?</p></li><li><p id="ad03b74079ce4b8199eac0cb1ec0f409">How can the data be prepared to visualize and answer relevant questions?</p></li></ul><p id="e2ef3fa2feca48f79420c41f53e9d3fe"><em>Model Requirements </em></p><p id="a08f06d206f64b279437a1c971757641">Although the talent for developing models resides within the project team, the model requirements are defined collaboratively. Model explainability is important to ensure that a client understands the insights that can be gleaned from the results/outputs from the model(s). </p><p id="f52bec096d9f4757b974a7a91d23f673">Let\xe2\x80\x99s consider the scenario above. The client will benefit from models that predict the probability of a prospective applicant enrolling in the college. Without understanding the output of a predictive model, the client will not be able to decipher the observations that could have a positive yield from their engagement efforts. This can result in the college wasting funds in targeting prospective students, therefore leading to a failed solution.</p><p id="f5562adc0d964f638387de65db260bc2">Model requirements describe the behavior and attributes of a model. The figure below highlights questions that should be answered, defining requirements for a model/models:</p><image id="e2f858a6fa4342649f883acf9b5f1b12" src="../webcontent/Analytic_Models.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="329" width="800"><caption><p id="aa5a9ec1417e4fd696a107646a10939e">Figure 1. Defining Model Requirements</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="cc131721b55e486799f7f065fe4d64c0"><em style="italic"><em>Reports and Dashboards: </em></em><em style="italic">&quot;Reports are often considered as a solution for business intelligence projects. If the college needs to generate reports, the project team will work with the college to define the requirements for reports by inquiring about (1) the current reports used in the college and the changes that need to be made to the reports, (2) data sources for the reports, (3) considerations for users generating reports i.e. how can an authorized user customize a report to display the data they need?&quot;. </em></p><p id="b128c2dcbcc44deaa2534e24b1c32b25">Similar to traditional IT projects, requirements should also be gathered for analytic solutions that are packaged. i.e., not developed in-house or outsourced.</p><p id="a5b88b26121d496ab6f4d9e53947c65a">Reading: <link href="https://industrial-ai.skf.com/machine-learning-due-diligence/" target="new" internal="false">Requirements for an IIoT (Industrial Internet of Things) Predictive Maintenance Solution.</link></p><wb:inline idref="newfd0786b763c74d57b5ba9c67e8a8585f" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'