b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="df997e30254b4079800e09653fc6ef8e"><head><title>Module 5 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="dd3c0e2ee39e46bcb91a0906f9b630f2"><li><p id="a9a5381ec55546449b8ff849fa9a0774">The difference between a traditional IT project and a Data Science project is the focus on the analytical data, model, and operations requirements.</p></li><li><p id="bf2362c6b2fb4913a5d09d3af43aeb97">Requirements are capabilities needed to achieve an objective. Requirements are gathered from stakeholders of a project, including the client, end-users, and the data science team. Good requirements are correct, complete, unambiguous, verifiable, measurable, and traceable.</p></li><li><p id="abda84d2354e4b019cf1e8c5a21648eb">Requirements analysis involves activities that identify business needs, evaluate the feasibility of solutions, and establish constraints.</p></li><li><p id="f7a07d8279bf4db4b37041c23e2b31f2">Requirements management is an iterative set of activities to help ensure that elicitation, documentation, refinement, and changes of requirements are done during the data science project life cycle.</p></li><li><p id="d497309309514a4aaf57c050ea831672">Requirements gathering involves fact-finding that describes the current state of the business and the business objectives that inform the proposed solution. Requirements gathering is done to ensure that business needs and solutions are well defined.</p></li><li><p id="c4159c043be84cd8a293cb7416dc3032">There are three types of requirements highlighted in this unit. The business, the system, and user, and the solution requirements.</p></li><li><p id="b938f4750a8e401fa7e88f9ce75cc7d7">Poorly documented requirements lead to assumptions and miscommunications between the project team and client stakeholders. Communication issues can lead to defects in solutions and unmet expectations. These are issues that a project team should avoid. This can be achieved by defining requirements in the early stages of solution development. Requirements are well-documented statements that define the needs of the users and systems that should be implemented to address a business need. The requirements gathering process can become complex if it is not managed properly. This process is managed by the business analyst.</p></li><li><p id="d0498af2f21b4708b1127df7d97db1be">There are different types of requirements including business and solution requirements. Business requirements describe the \xe2\x80\x9cwhy\xe2\x80\x9d behind the implementation of a solution, while the user requirements describe the tasks that users will be able to perform with the system, and the solution requirements specify the behavior of the system and its characteristics.</p></li><li><p id="ff4987d829c34916ab7338ee48d5c306">Similar to a traditional IT project, it is a best practice to collect requirements for analytic projects. The requirements for an analytic project include determining how data, models, and results or outputs of the models will support meeting the analytic and business objectives.</p></li><li><p id="bde981dd58dc4aa586ced5874be4bc40">There are techniques that are used to gather requirements including conducting interviews, brainstorming sessions, and facilitated workshops, other techniques used in addition to the above listed include document analysis and observations. Once requirements are elicited, they are analyzed and translated into written requirements for understanding. Finally, requirements are validated by the project and client team to signal the commencement of solution development.</p></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'