b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e0e0e4def10146f0821e46fc2f1a1bd5"><head><title>Introduction to Data Science Ethics</title><objref idref="b25ceb80386b4047a1c2c4f72d8b2a54" /><objref idref="dbcb01e3d5354ab1afecdb7ece077ff3" /><objref idref="b012fecccba94dd09a7dba22fede95f5" /></head><body><section id="ec4f2cd6447743dc9a907f0304154a97"><title>Introduction to Data Science Ethics</title><body><p id="bd4e847ff98c472aa97beddd761e7591">For much of human civilization, people did the best they could to thrive under challenging circumstances. These were times when there weren\xe2\x80\x99t many rules to follow, so people did and took what they could and weren\xe2\x80\x99t exactly ethical, but arguably this ethic was necessary to survive difficult times. That is also where we see the situation of <em>the tragedy of the commons</em>, mentioned in the previous module. We also saw that the tragedy could be overcome \xe2\x80\x93 that is, we can begin to produce a better civilization for all. In this improved civilization, we no longer do things just because we can or feel we have to. We now have to follow rules of ethics that give us more benefits collectively than they cost us.</p><p id="e42b7bf2c93c47c8a9e2fc9519bf3585">We have virtually unlimited access to data as data scientists today, and we have unprecedented analytical techniques with which to analyze that data. So the question we should be thinking about is whether we should do something just because it is technically possible. Are there things that are possible to do but which we can agree would not be right to do? This may sound strange, but it is a question that modern science has already begun considering and continues to do so.</p><p id="ab9b35176fef4f8baac1ed732db9a927">Think about how data science creates impacts and the tremendous excitement about how data science applications provide better ways of doing things in society. Think about the power you have as a data scientist and how that power influences people\xe2\x80\x99s lives, potentially for the better. <em>With that great power comes great responsibility</em>. It is crucial as data scientists that we be responsible when exercising that great power.</p><p id="b84ca4f5972a4df6b7eec7e0b2a1da9b">The difficult thing about being an ethical data scientist is not about understanding ethics. It is the connection to how one applies ethical principles to data science practice; it is about doing \xe2\x80\x9cgood\xe2\x80\x9d or ethical data science.</p></body></section><section id="e6c9acc9841a4fdd90bb6cc086be90aa"><title>Doing Good Data Science</title><body><image id="eb92267b6935468982df666dfaa87294" src="../webcontent/image-e0e0e4def10146f0821e46fc2f1a1bd5-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="434" width="650"><caption><p id="e436d5dc47c745cd8f1f17608376fa83">By Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed, CC BY-SA 4.0, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=23391637</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="a7746c80733845a591ae34062a4aca72">This is the Amsterdam Civil Registry Office in the Netherlands. Buildings like these were record offices that contained cabinets full of records about the Dutch population. During World War II, following the Nazi invasion and occupation of the Netherlands in 1940, the Nazis took over the registry office and used these records to identify members of the Dutch resistance. The records about their birth were used as a potent weapon to identify members of the Dutch population who were Jewish and to therefore decide whom to send to extermination camps.</p><p id="cd45e7f73b9049d0b08a9acd5ba5a438">The Dutch resistance saw that the mere existence of the Civil Registry Office was dangerous in the hands of the Nazi war machine. So they planned a bombing of the Office in 1943 in an effort to destroy records that would help the Nazis identify Jews. Figure 2 is of a plaque in Amsterdam that lists the names of the people in the Dutch Resistance who bombed this record office. They were the ones that identified links between these records and what was happening in the war, took actions to prevent it, and paid the price. They were captured and executed.</p><image id="a2f61c8b5f244eef9646848181e73455" src="../webcontent/image-e0e0e4def10146f0821e46fc2f1a1bd5-2.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="650" width="524"><caption><p id="afbc37281c68427cac0c794de7a65560">By Design: Willem Sandberg. Photographer: Frans Willemsen - Own work, CC BY-SA 3.0 nl, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=32468279</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ada8b69f8172455687df4bb822ac02e9">We hope this is a good place to start the conversation about doing good data science and the motivation to do so. In the rest of the module, we hope to convince you, if you\xe2\x80\x99re not already convinced, that the story of the 1943 bombing of the Amsterdam civil registry office is highly relevant to the work you do as a data scientist. While the data science work you do may be mundane by comparison and not involve a life-or-death decision, ethical data science practices matter to everyday things that affect all of us. The goal of this module is to help you participate in the ethical debates that you will face as a data scientist, infuse your data science work with ethical principles, and inform you to be thoughtful, deliberate, and ethical \xe2\x80\x93 the kind of data scientists that we all hope that you\xe2\x80\x99re going to be.</p></body></section><section id="f70f8b69607d495796cd91cf6a207f0e"><title>The Five Cs</title><body><p id="c142a96295ec4dd7b1fbcd0142d676f3">[Required Reading]</p><p id="d4fe47a1b20946d5b55617515eb1e780">Please read chapter 3 from <link href="https://cmu.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01CMU_INST/6lpsnm/alma991019696464404436" target="new" internal="false">Loukides, Mason, H., &amp; Patil, D. (2018). </link><em style="italic"><em>Ethics and Data Science (1st edition)</em></em><link href="https://cmu.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01CMU_INST/6lpsnm/alma991019696464404436" target="new" internal="false">. O\xe2\x80\x99Reilly Media, Inc.</link></p><p id="a76004d2b5bc456ba454bdfe1e836683">Note: When prompted to select institution, select &quot;Not listed? Click here&quot; and enter your CMU email address to access content.</p></body></section></body></workbook_page>\n'