b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e148406a387545d7ac7e91f1ab4ae2e3"><head><title>Statistics &amp; Data Types</title><objref idref="b51674a34f404ad3ad59b1b2d59f386e" /></head><body><p id="a0c95407a8764a619cbf6c1e27bf7f75"><em style="italic">Statistics</em> is the science of using data to learn about the world around us. In this course, we use the term &quot;statistics&quot; in the broad sense to refer to <em>methods for obtaining and analyzing data</em>. Specifically, statistics provides methods for:</p><ol id="c29831cb31944441ab9f9cf760e93009"><li><p id="d96798f3c24542f3901a84fcafa95192"><em>Design</em>: Planning how to gather data for research studies,</p></li><li><p id="d4baef616b8b48088bb9579158847455"><em>Description</em>: Summarizing the data, and</p></li><li><p id="b32398dae05b4325a9f86c2b24a82ad0"><em>Inference</em>: Making predictions based on the data.</p></li></ol><p id="ffcf7577e0fe4559a5c53e89762a5f75"><em>Design</em> refers to planning how to obtain the data. For a survey, for example, the design aspects would specify how to select the people to interview and would construct the questionnaire to administer.</p><p id="cf59abdc05254f7ba562aef9f61131bc"><em>Description</em> refers to summarizing data to help understand the information they provide. For example, an analysis of the number of siblings based on a survey might start with a list of the number reported for each of the people who responded to that question that year. The raw data are a complete listing of observations, person-by-person. These are not easy to comprehend, however. We get bogged down in numbers. For the presentation of results, instead of listing all observations, we could summarize the data with a graph or table showing the percentages of respondents reporting one sibling, two siblings, three siblings, and so on. Alternatively, we could just report the average number of siblings, let\xe2\x80\x99s say 3, or the most common response, let\xe2\x80\x99s say 2. Graphs, tables, and numerical summaries are called <em>descriptive statistics</em>.</p><p id="c9ddd14bc33245a89878e4a01f52a2c4"><em>Inference</em> refers to making predictions based on data. For instance, for the survey data on the number of siblings, suppose 15.6% reported having no siblings. Can we use this information to predict the percentage of all adults in the U.S. at that time who is an only child? Predictions made using data are called <em style="italic">statistical inferences</em>. We will explore statistical inference in more detail in the upcoming section.</p><p id="f251f6ea2ca4431f969c6dabcf4cd8a0"><em>Description</em> and <em>inference</em> are the two types of statistical analysis - ways of analyzing the data. Data scientists use descriptive and inferential statistics to answer questions about data. For instance, &quot;Is changing the website layout associated with an increase in visitors?&quot; or &quot;Does student performance in schools depends on the amount of money spent per student, the size of the classes, or the teachers&apos; salaries?&quot;</p><p id="ae1c9f674bd54937a18963f4e0771425">Statistical methods help us determine the factors that explain the <em>variability</em> among subjects. Any characteristic we can measure for each subject is called a <em style="italic">variable</em>. The name reflects the values of the characteristics that vary among subjects. In data science, we usually see the term <em style="italic">feature</em> used interchangeably with <em style="italic">variable</em>.</p><p id="d6258b7064914f759a2baea0fef21c2e">Different subjects may have different values of variables: the values the variable takes to form the measurement scale. These measurement scales result in data exhibiting different types. In this section, we discuss the measurement scales of data analogous to data types. <em>The valid values for a feature depending on its data type. Thus data types affect the methods we will choose to develop an analytic solution.</em></p><p id="c911d6bbf8404dc09db4634efc5156f4">When discussing data types in data science, data is typically categorized as numeric or categorical and classified as one of the four measurement scale types. Quantitative data is represented as continuous or discrete values, while categorical data can be nominal or ordinal values.</p><table id="ceebb6897e1c4a11b761f0aac38acd3f" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i296724dc48d54076b4ab1ef61fb616c5" /><caption><p id="ef38dbe9b20a4ec583c57e4157a3c59d" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f3119bbb9872451d8b0bae6b0d7c8875"><em>Quantitative Data</em></p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="dd215c69fdfc40deafb67316cc284bca"><em>Categorical Data</em></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="df43e720ccb147b5ab798d77872f71d4">Discrete: I have <em>one</em> sibling. </p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e4c15dc9131b4750a607dd9d088b3d34">Ordinal: I can rate my customer service experience at the grocery store as <em>Good.</em></p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="c91c5d773db24dffa7b9934545c2eb65">Continuous: It takes <em>1 hour and 20 minutes</em> to get to school. </p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f7b9b0af57394b029b12b56933457626">Nominal: What is your hair color? <em>Brown.</em></p></td></tr></table><p id="fd6cbf1e99a94c85b2c645a5831935a7"><em>Quantitative and Categorical Data</em></p><p id="da0f290ea24f48abb2c43d4dd8763d6c">Data is quantitative when the measurement scale has numerical values. The values represent different magnitudes of the variable. Examples of quantitative variables are income, the number of siblings, age, the number of years of education completed, etc.</p><p id="c5a1bb2d29cf4185b347f370415096e3">Meanwhile, data is categorical when the measurement scale is a set of categories. For example, marital status, with categories (single, married, divorced, widowed), is categorical. For Americans, states are categorical, with the categories Pennsylvania, Montana, Utah, and so on; for Canadians, the province of residence is categorical, with the categories Alberta, British Columbia, and so on. Other categorical data are whether employed (yes, no), favorite type of music (classical, country, folk, jazz, rock), and political party preference.</p><p id="d8f168cac29349dd92079380f537c897">For categorical data, distinct categories differ in quality, not in numerical magnitude. Categorical data are often called <em style="italic">qualitative</em>. We distinguish between categorical and quantitative data because different analytical methods apply to each type. For example, the average is a statistical summary of a quantitative variable because it captures numerical values. It&apos;s possible to find the average for quantitative data such as income but not for categorical data such as religious affiliation or favorite type of music.</p><p id="ec88fa7b04c44ac9aff231ca7bfb39d0"><em>Structured and Unstructured Data</em></p><p id="abd9dec5c9e649bb9f2411daeffde0fd">Structured Data is organized facts that are presented in fixed formats and are easy to extract. This data can be stored in spreadsheets, relational databases, and other repositories in, for example, a row and column format. Unstructured data is most difficult to extract. It is not easily stored in typical relational databases and spreadsheets because it does not neatly fit in the row and column structure or cannot be maintained in formats that are uniform. Text, multimedia files, and log files from servers are examples of unstructured data. New generation database frameworks, also known as NoSQL databases, have been developed specifically to handle unstructured data. Unlike structured data, unstructured data can be stored without a predefined schema.</p><p id="e028c6094ed64667bfc0a3221c8e9bb4"><em>Internal and External Data</em></p><p id="cb71b080f9404488a332c9f288f97141">Data can also be classified as <em style="italic">internal </em>data, which is data collected and/or controlled by an organization. An example would be personnel data collected and stored by the human resources department. We also have <em style="italic">external </em>data, data that is collected from sources outside of an organization. Census data and data gathered from credit reporting agencies are examples of external data.</p><p id="ca1d70e03ff6490ba2abe92bf4b66ebe"><em>Data Sources</em></p><p id="c2493366642a497da250dfd257797611">The different types of data explored earlier are collected through different sources. <em style="italic">Primary </em>data sources include data that is collected and processed by an organization and housed internally. <em style="italic">Secondary </em>data sources include data that is gathered from sources external to an organization. Keep in mind that internal data can come from a primary or secondary data source and that an organization&apos;s data governance framework affects data that is collected from primary and secondary sources as long as they are used by the organization.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'