b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e29c43b25dbf4a898cc00544d06001ab"><head><title>Regression Evaluation Metrics</title><objref idref="f884b110ee3f48bfaf5a73e27e20b647" /></head><body><p id="eed624878a44470ca76f85ae09c84019">Regression tasks will predict the state of a target variable based on other input variables. As a quick reminder, the target variables in these tasks are continuous values. Let us discuss the metrics that are used to evaluate the outcome of regression tasks:</p><section id="d784a9354b904ac692a14b8805cc49f2"><title>Coefficient of Determination (R-squared)</title><body><p id="c5a3b93d1f7c4f93bbe58d4468b31fe2" /></body></section><p id="c97239e7b428456eae9d97cb3583bd03">R-squared, also known as the Coefficient of Determination, is the proportion of the <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Explained_variation" target="new" internal="false">variance</link> in the outcome variable that can be predicted using the predictor variables. It tells you how well-observed outcomes are replicated by a model based on the proportion of total variation of outcomes explained by the model. When interpreting R-squared in a simple linear regression model, it is considered to be the square of the sample correlation coefficient between the outcomes and predictors (r<sup>2</sup>). If R<sup>2</sup> is 0.5, this would mean that 50% of the variation in the dependent variable is explained by the predictor variables. A good model has a high R<sup>2</sup>. </p><p id="ca4c2b9d57f749bfa22da2daa23984dd">When there are multiple regressors, then R<sup>2</sup> is the square of the coefficient of multiple correlations (&quot;correlation between the variable&apos;s values and the best predictions that can be computed linearly from the predictive variables&quot;). This metric will provide an indication of how well new data will be predicted by the model.</p><section id="ef1226cce9304ac0bc5554f7701e05b4"><title>Adjusted R-squared</title><body><p id="babd1f52df2f45adbc763727f8122f83"> </p></body></section><p id="b690ed9522494774aa4c6979c41374c7">Adjusted R<sup>2</sup> is calculated by dividing the residual mean square error by the total mean square error (which is the sample variance of the target field). The result is then subtracted from 1. It identifies the percentage of variance in the target field that is explained by the input or inputs. Adjusted R<sup>2</sup> is always less than or equal to R<sup>2</sup>. A value of 1 indicates a model that perfectly predicts values in the target field. A value that is less than or equal to 0 indicates a model that has no predictive value. In the real world, adjusted R<sup>2</sup> lies between these values. </p><p id="fec3bcc2967942b09585f100d8e5de22">A weakness of R<sup>2</sup> is that it cannot determine whether the coefficient estimates and predictions might be biased. The R<sup>2</sup> will typically increase when a predictor is added to a model, and as you add more predictors, your model will likely overfit and result in a high R<sup>2</sup>. Adjusted R<sup>2</sup> attempts to correct this overestimation. Adjusted R<sup>2</sup> will only increase if newly added predictors improve the model more than expected and decrease when a predictor or predictors improve the model less than expected. It tells you the percentage of variation explained by predictors that will have an effect on the outcome. Basically, adjusted R<sup>2</sup> will calculate R<sup>2</sup> from the predictors that have a significant impact on the model. Adjusted R<sup>2</sup> is best used to compare models with different numbers of predictors.</p><section id="d404de64498c40f1b5130433a5738ae8"><title>Mean Squared Error (MSE)</title><body><p id="b7a95929105040de8672b427dd77ebd6" /></body></section><p id="ea470d22cfa74595a1fdec45b2bc2e57"><em style="italic">Mean Squared Error (MSE) </em>is a measure of the quality of an estimator or a predictor (depending on context). A value closer to zero is always best. Mean squared error refers to the unbiased estimate of error variance: <em style="italic">the residual sum of squares divided by the number of degrees of freedom</em>.</p><section id="e7ad1a42353e433f966c2af75726c91a"><title>Mean Absolute Error (MAE)</title><body><p id="ab2052b8a20544bfae40ebf7bbe76aac" /></body></section><p id="dcb16b3d7cba48d883c9e9a2b7d3f469">Mean Absolute Error (MAE) is the measure of errors between paired observations and is computed as the average of all absolute errors (the absolute error is the absolute value of the difference between a predicted value and the actual value). This metric is used to measure accuracy. You use the <em style="italic">Mean Absolute Percentage Error</em> (MAPE) to compare predictions and interpret whether the size of an error is small or large. The MAPE is a model evaluation technique that clearly interprets the relative error.</p><section id="aacef61e817a481ab2d79d08ead7a536"><title>Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE)</title><body><p id="b9638afdaf734964aa24d1fb195ad52c" /></body></section><p id="c19baf372ff043588da7656cdcb8c646">Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE) gives weight to large errors since it squares the errors before computing the mean. The RMSE is computed by first determining the residuals (difference between the actual and predicted y values). Residuals are squared and the squares are averaged. Finally, the square root of the averaged squares will result in the RMSE. An easier way to think about the formula is: &quot;square root of (1-r2) multiplied by the standard deviation of <em style="italic">y</em>.</p><p id="e9ba8c8ac8904fe590b0b4844bda2051">Resource: <link href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/model_evaluation.html#regression-metrics" target="new" internal="false">Regression Metrics-scikit-learn</link></p><wb:inline idref="mooclet_activity" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'