b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e3586cba434145ecbd1803995318fb6b"><head><title>Introduction to Natural Language Processing</title></head><body><section id="cfa3146c5ab24bd2b65a237a76c3e949"><title>Introduction to Natural Language Processing</title><body><p id="c1e578e7acc842c0a0f46012336ae877">Natural Language Processing (NLP hereafter) is a subfield of computer science aiming to  build  systems that:</p><ul id="fd2820f1c779403e95bac632a21733f6"><li><p id="dc68d44843a0457ea0064b10126a4bb6">Enable human-computer communication</p></li><li><p id="b0be077465044c1c93d741464dcf1d68">Enable/enrich human-human communication</p></li><li><p id="fb36ebb5433445d4811e93c4f6eb2b02">Perform tasks requiring the use of human language faculty, more efficiently and more correctly.</p></li></ul><p id="d63b53fe40b8440885160eaf16172a53">Here are some applications of NLP in these three areas:</p><ul id="ceae11721fde46afa6336636edaf20c5"><li><p id="a65adcd0f5834daf94acda779e4d3510">Human-computer communication</p><ul id="a925e7d1581d493f8e19d6bb0b30d7b7"><li><p id="a0b6629e030a4b4ab1c9a1a16e981fe1">Dictating email messages</p></li><li><p id="e13fe4be3a834ee8bd1cdbcd8fd38d14">Listening to email messages</p><ul id="cdde982d97744ad7800770ea5cc7a14b"><li><p id="cc2d7f8a26f44c1a94ddcd163edb2e10">With proper pronunciation, tone, and stress!</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="fb63fa38b35e4e2693614fd4df41e6c9">Using human language to give commands to the operating system</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="bb99720456dc4387978b0ebe8acd77c6">Human-human communication</p><ul id="afbb44fe68d3481ab15e0b2fbe4088a0"><li><p id="b304f600f6d04de498a3a75d214a3d78">Real-time text and speech translation</p></li><li><p id="e2fc093fe5c74ca5ae0dbd48c8bc7e76">Summarizing meeting conversations</p></li><li><p id="a0980217ea4d498ebc6c608c1f2295d1">Enabling communication with people with hearing/vision impairments</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="c166ad7b95d3452b82392d3e022bb181">Improving the efficiency of tasks requiring human language faculty</p><ul id="b3b9ff5553fc421d82c8ded8d174fb05"><li><p id="e72eb70adff249c8b2dbd10d04b15419">Correcting typing/grammatical errors</p></li><li><p id="cfb28a5db2ff4a2fa8530acb65814c12">Question answering</p></li><li><p id="bc799254074b4008847f378177d85395">Answering e-mails automatically</p></li><li><p id="ff277b823e1240e391cc6e38016da67d">Searching large document databases</p></li></ul></li></ul><p id="ad9983c6a67f4d28bb0cccf034a8798e">Here are some (and definitely not a comprehensive set of) applications of  NLP in a diverse set of areas:</p><ul id="e7a39a7451e646b6a88eb66ebe255345"><li><p id="ae18d39c0652459aad601f5f19d60c92">Information extraction (IE), especially \xe2\x80\x9copen\xe2\x80\x9d IE:  Given a text (or a collection of texts), find out <em style="italic">who</em> did <em style="italic">what</em> to <em style="italic">whom</em>, <em style="italic">where</em>, <em style="italic">when</em>, <em style="italic">how</em>, <em style="italic">why</em>, <em style="italic">with what</em>, <em style="italic">in exchange for what</em>, etc.</p></li><li><p id="c76b1e1a68d84f43a95f2cdeeb19b6f1">Document classification: Classifying a document into topic areas (e.g., news, sports, business, entertainment, sports, etc.), classifying an email as spam or not, or as important or not.</p></li><li><p id="c0156e5a9baa4f89ac02f595613ecbc3">Question answering beyond finding the documents relevant to the question and instead delivering the actual answer.</p></li><li><p id="d9e3879d87104b9496ec7165f2f45efa">Conversational Agents (e.g., Siri, Alexa, Google Assistant): Holding a typically multi-stage turn-taking goal-driven conversation with a user, going beyond question answering and helping with other tasks such as making appointments, helping with shopping or entertainment options, etc.</p></li><li><p id="fee05df39a1a4906ac086a64927c6f21">Image (and eventually video) understanding:  Expressing the pictorial or video content in human language (e.g., image captioning or verbalizing a football match action in a TV program setting). </p></li><li><p id="e65543d695f0494388a39235ed5fe7ee">Text (including text on images) and speech translation with additional applications in video call transcription and translation, real-time lecture translation, generating speech output in the right accent and the right lip rendering for much more natural-looking video generation.</p></li><li><p id="f664e2f23756456a93d2b107b2967c4a">Sign-language translation and scene-to-speech for the visually impaired (which would be akin to video understanding above).</p></li><li><p id="e7d0117107ed4a70bbf475041600e577">Summarization:  Generating a short summary of the salient points of a document or a set of documents.</p></li><li><p id="cfab9d37df4a4b9a8947fe88a4bab610">Opinion and sentiment analysis:  Extracting political or personal sentiments from news pieces, tweets, product or movie reviews.</p></li><li><p id="dbb33789db0b4d8b916dc7fa68bcaea7">Essay evaluation: Evaluate an essay (say in an SAT exam setting) for proper structure, sentence, and vocabulary use.</p></li><li><p id="c81b603a4b2e4c739fac8861e9b36848">Fake news or fake review detection:  Automatic fact-checking of news, especially in real-time viral settings on social media; verifying that product, restaurant, or movie reviews in online shopping or recommendation settings are genuine and not generated by bots, etc.</p></li></ul></body></section><section id="f0299be536744baf9c42a026e1beb7e6"><title>Bird\xe2\x80\x99s Eye View of NLP</title><body><p id="d3c0395b9c0e43488c155ba71b825f43">The following figure gives a bird\xe2\x80\x99s eye view of NLP and various functions or tasks that partake in building and evaluating NLP applications.</p><image id="e257c3c78ad148a390c0434dee7a68eb" src="../webcontent/image-d01319063f22438e9dcc5d684f637143-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="324" width="459"><caption><p id="b60e106846444b21ba4413e9eed4956c">From Eduard Hovy\xe2\x80\x99s \xe2\x80\x9cThe Past and 3\xc2\xbd Futures of NLP\xe2\x80\x9d presentation.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></section><section id="d12d25d47f1f4cbc80278d10b28436a5"><title>Fundamental functions in NLP</title><body><p id="dd82540189f4413e9c4716c278369993">There are three high-level functions that NLP tries to automate:</p><ol id="cc9e6ec88ca44c528c5486a3a1b3b901"><li><p id="bf07f9dc026a4eef898c8c61287732e8"><em>Analysis</em> (or \xe2\x80\x9cunderstanding\xe2\x80\x9d or \xe2\x80\x9cprocessing\xe2\x80\x9d \xe2\x80\xa6) where the input is language (text or speech), and the output is some <em style="italic">representation</em> that supports useful action (e.g., translation or robot movements) in response.</p></li><li><p id="fd4116e9cff543acb6891c0b4499effa"><em>Generation</em>: input is a representation of an utterance and possibly a representation of the context, and the output is text or speech that captures the semantics and the intent encoded in the input representation (e.g., generating the target language sentence in machine translation).</p></li><li><p id="cbb37f6e4f3041c08c9883c2ffb3c78c"><em>Acquisition</em>: obtaining the representation and necessary algorithms from data (e.g., learning to translate from aligned translated sentences).</p></li></ol><p id="e77efbecf58e418d825378ba2aa3880b">The representation that these employs depends on the actual task being solved:  they can be explicit such as morphological analyses of words, syntax trees, or part-of-speech symbol sequences of sentences that capture the linguistic structure of words or sentences. They can also be very opaque, like sentence embeddings that a neural machine translation system computes as it analyzes an input sentence.</p></body></section><section id="d0d8f47bbb8e403dab3cc1deccb2c075"><title>Relation to Other Fields</title><body><p id="a7d6cc0b559b4d11ba87adf2e02d9788">NLP is closely related to the following areas of computer science and other fields Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Statistical modeling, Information Theory, Human-computer interaction, Software Engineering, Linguistics,  Ethics, Cognitive Science, Logic, Social sciences, political science, and psychology.</p><p id="ca94a7b006d540c4afe143211ee82c5c">Currently, almost all functions implemented in NLP applications make heavy use of machine learning, especially deep learning, involving transformers, large-scale neural language models, and the like.  These all necessitate large-scale data sources such as annotated and unannotated text, speech corpora, and large-scale computing resources to train.</p></body></section></body></workbook_page>\n'