b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e453a3c17d1f4be8909e27937597da4b"><head><title>Step 4a: Drafting the Methods Statement</title><objref idref="c652b19601414ebebcfaed9f52cd17e0" /></head><body><p id="c2a8d63975364845946b0b72aedb7ed8"><em>Proposing Learning Methods </em></p><p id="eba4c7d095514959a0e6c6daf2a30196">If you have not already, you should notice a pattern at this stage. The conceptual progression <em style="italic">Business Need \xe2\x87\x92 Business Objective \xe2\x87\x92 Analytic Objective including Problem Statement \xe2\x87\x92 Task Definition \xe2\x87\x92 Method &amp; Data Statement</em> serves the purpose of gradually refining our understanding of what the client needs until we arrive at a technical project specification that the technicians can design against. The statement of methods to be applied will vary in specificity depending on your project, but three elements are important: </p><ol id="bf2fb9220a654d9abdb50654efa0135a"><li><p id="f346cfbbf91045b2886b51e4bea0d2d7">The statement  must be precise enough so that the data science team understands it as a concise summary of the technical approach.</p></li><li><p id="b1562940de8e4c68bb0288a55e63a93e">At the same time, it should allow for testing different techniques around the main conceptual idea.</p></li><li><p id="d788da3970764503b37e4d58e3d0c0ae">The methods should in principle be suitable to produce the target functionality/insight for the task given the available data.</p></li></ol><p id="b07c0d883f7c423da575ee8251b1f263">As you become more proficient in the discipline of data science (e.g., after having completed the more advanced units of this course), you will develop refined intuitions about which method to propose in which context. The most general categories of methods one can identify in this statement typically include:</p><ul id="aa7449faec814a1694baa2821f9df02e"><li><p id="d55e9a063245412aa96b1c3a413c271f"><em>Supervised learning methods</em> which involve learning to predict a target variable (typically through regression or classification) by training on \xe2\x80\x9ctrue\xe2\x80\x9d example data points whose target variable has manually been labeled or is available by other means.</p></li><li><p id="ec5893a78e6d4f5382f9d58828eada3b"><em>Unsupervised learning methods</em> which deal with finding patterns in unlabeled data without an explicit prediction target.</p></li><li><p id="d1ec18e20c3f4d5bbfa2e87c464e96a8"><em>Semi-Supervised learning methods</em> which encompass hybrid methods that combine supervised and unsupervised learning in different ways.</p></li></ul><p id="ed8396b44a624ebaaa01f772f2518dee">This course is very focused on the application of machine learning, which has a large overlap with various kinds of <em>statistical methods</em>. It is possible to phrase your method statement around the use of statistics, but it is recommended that one qualifies this rather broad term as something adequate for the project.</p><p id="c6cf4c7df08d4501af4a1fe445f0ccfc"><em style="italic">Note: the precise categorization of some methods as supervised or unsupervised methods is subject to some disagreement in the community. After completing this course, you will be able to make an informed decision regarding the use of these terms. </em></p><p id="ac777cc5d5794f6bb889eced0bcf8fca">In many contexts, the method will need to be stated much more precisely than that, especially if the problem domain is already well-studied in data science or there is some prior work that should be extended. The method can range from specifying a particular family of models (e.g., linear vs. non-linear), using a new feature set, testing the explainability of a particular model\xe2\x80\x99s predictions, optimizing hyperparameters for faster training and inference in neural networks, and more. We can illustrate the specific vs. general statement in the context of an example:</p><example id="b74ad004c82f4e68a270e6b6255af844"><p id="f422acb1763443abac99107c26069e6c">Your client gives you access to a large dataset of electronics product manufacturing and customer support data and asks you to help improve quality control (business objective) as the quality control personnel do not reliably find all potential defects (<em>problem</em>). Your model should be able to predict product failure within one month after the sale (<em>task 1</em>) and identify predictors measured at quality control time (<em>task 2</em>). In a pilot project, you propose to apply \xe2\x80\x9ctraditional supervised learning methods to train a classifier and examine the model for predictive variables.\xe2\x80\x9d You then proceed to conduct the project using basic logistic regression and some nonlinear tree-based models as they allow straightforward model explanation.</p><p id="acd762fbb8c245fdb244a88c32fd6e8b">Variation: Your pilot project was a success, and your models are being used to better inform quality control personnel. However, it turns out that it still produces a high false-positive rate (<em>problem</em>) and causes shipping delays, which the client wants to minimize (<em>business objective</em>). You are asked to improve the model\xe2\x80\x99s performance by reducing its false-positive rate (<em>task</em>). You are further given access to quality control diagnostic equipment readings, which the engineers believe are useful to discern whether a product is defective or just \xe2\x80\x9cneeds to be broken in.\xe2\x80\x9d You hence propose to integrate the reading data using a special signal encoding algorithm in combination with a nonlinear model architecture to improve the model.</p></example><p id="b478f17753fa43bbbab355bd857a9cc0">The method and data are the heart of a data science project. Finding the best tool for the task is, of course, one of the core skills of being a good data scientist. This course will give you an introduction to basic methods and provide you with the opportunity to apply them in course projects. As you gain deeper knowledge and experience, you will become better not only at analyzing problems and tasks in different domains but also at researching data science literature and libraries effectively and coming up with project proposals that are aligned with state-of-the-art solutions. At the same time, thinking through different approaches and deciding on a set of methods and datasets benefit from teamwork, open discussion, and active seeking of advice and feedback from your peers, mentors, and relevant specialists.</p><p id="e87c8bd478d64be8a3bbb095ebc1e0b9">A good beginning strategy is to check your proposed method against the target functionality or insight by conceptually thinking through its application and explicitly formulating expected results. </p><example id="f69a65f1ca724b7596669c2479eed6c6"><title>Title</title><p id="f46fea99b64b439ab13a6bda389abb19">In the above electronics scenario, you imagine training a logistic regression model on the features in the data to predict product failure. Once trained, influential features should receive a high weight in the regression equation, allowing you to identify them easily, similar to correlation analysis. If you train a decision tree, you can identify features by traversing its branches. On the other hand, if you were to propose to train a complex random forest model to predict product failure with maximal accuracy, you may encounter the objection that random forests are not as easily interpretable as simpler models. It would hence be an unsuitable method for task 2 in the pilot stage. A good way would be to go with the simpler models for now and leave more complex models for later phases if needed. In the variation, a colleague may suggest that the signal encoding algorithm you plan to use is outdated and recommends you use a more recently developed encoding. You may research both algorithms and make an informed decision, or even use both algorithms in a comparative experiment.</p><wb:inline idref="newea3ea32d00894ced8ec8fbce6779b79d" purpose="didigetthis" /></example></body></workbook_page>\n'