b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\r\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ebc62268ac6c4c188a6719231f3c3f54"><head><title>Overview</title><objref idref="c9f8497753cb4836aae3e8011b861f25" /><objref idref="fddc9352f8594dcf9e301b1159522f8d" /><objref idref="d9ef6dee1241438291e00fe3788a5e7b" /></head><body><p id="b0f497f7d17d438bb8b510e83458953b">As you have learned in a previous unit, gaining an understanding of the business need and formulating project objectives (business and analytic) are best practices for successfully meeting client expectations. Once the project objectives have been defined, the project team will identify the needs and constraints of stakeholders and the current system or environment related to the business need; this is referred to as the <em style="italic">Requirements Gathering Process</em>. \r</p><p id="e0b142103d444fc6b80ab8d34d9c162b"><em style="italic">Requirements gathering</em> establishes communication between the solutions development team (referred to as the project team in this unit) and the business stakeholders. The objective of the requirements gathering process is to define the system inputs, processes, outputs, and interfaces. When properly done, requirements gathering will positively influence the outcome of a project. Requirements gathering can also help the project team to visualize the intended solution. \r</p><p id="b058315143b04a3488f9b6f47eb0f417">The requirements gathering process involves input from the <em style="italic">system users</em> and <em style="italic">system owners</em>. A system user interacts with the solution and a system owner (who can also be a user) is an official who is responsible for decisions made about systems within their organization. In this unit, we will refer to these roles as <em style="italic">stakeholders</em>.\r</p><p id="b9070b05948f4c26a08d0d12905878d0">Similar to traditional software development projects, data science projects are also guided by requirements gathering principles, figure 3 lists the steps that are followed during the process. Requirements gathering for a data science project will involve eliciting the needs of the stakeholders, and defining the requirements for the analytic solution(s). </p><image id="e8fb5c3a7c314f2f87560360f009ff3d" src="../webcontent/Requirements.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="dd3cc4617c7f40b382470723d209f923">Figure 3: Requirements Gathering Process</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="c6f27bd2fc84403b846ebcb6ee5a02c9">The requirements gathering process involves eliciting user and system needs, and defining data and analytic requirements for the successful implementation of a data related project.</p><ul id="ba6fbd6dbfb9402abd5dc39b241da46d"><li><p id="bb16fd4833d84c46b7a8e0277723274e"><em>Gather Information: </em>The first step in gathering information is to identify the stakeholders within the business; the stakeholders will be individuals who perform tasks that will meet the business need, as well as decision makers within the business. Once stakeholders are identified, the business analyst will elicit information to determine what the solution should do to meet the defined business and analytic objectives.\r Later on in this unit, we will discuss the techniques used to gather information.</p></li><li><p id="ba453de236c742609bc2937e66e0dee6"><em>Define and Prioritize Requirements: </em>Stakeholders will provide information according to their view of the business needs, it is the job of the business analyst to lead the effort in defining and prioritizing requirements. It is important to document &quot;complete&quot; requirements that capture the needs of the stakeholders, as this will guide the project team in developing the right solution(s). Stakeholders might provide information that can be used for future projects related to the proposed solution, that information should not be discarded, it is prioritized as a low priority requirement and considered for future implementation. </p></li><li><p id="bcdac04fc95344eeb0f3b21dd90eb65d"><em>Evaluate Requirements: </em>The project team must verify and validate all documented requirements. This additional step in the requirements gathering process will ensure that the solution meets the business needs and satisfies the expectations of the stakeholders.</p></li><li><p id="cbae648e54804d5f87d1f98c767669da"><em>Receive Sign-Off: </em>This is an indication that the requirements have been approved and agreed upon by the client. Requirements are signed off twice during the development lifecycle; sign-offs take place prior to the start of solution development and after testing the solution.</p></li></ul><p id="e3ffb98f3d9e4e8f812dd9f5ba3d5cd6"><em>Requirements Management Plan</em></p><p id="c921737da16b47c698a69d954caee049">A <em style="italic">requirements management plan</em> can be used to document the requirements gathering process. This document is made available to the client and the project team as it contains information that affects both parties. There is no standard template for this document but it is in good practice to include the following sections:\r</p><p id="c9ed4280b0154283872098c70be99a82"><em style="italic"><em>Project description </em></em>is an overview of your project, this section describes the purpose of your project. </p><p id="c5daab07ef284f6bbda4a53743845167"><em style="italic"><em>Team Responsibilities</em></em> are defined in this plan to designate who will be involved in managing activities during the requirements gathering process. Data science project team members might take on duties outside of their normal roles e.g. a data analyst on the data science team might serve in the role of Scribe during joint application development sessions. \r</p><p id="e880acf60d6043a0aa69fe71aedfcd56"><em style="italic"><em>Tools</em></em> used to manage the requirements include project management tools, and word processing or other dedicated systems used to capture, manage, and track requirements through the requirements gathering process and throughout the project lifecycle.\r</p><p id="eaea66c571a6463fa765413f4ec27027"><em style="italic"><em>Requirements Gathering Process</em></em> should be defined in this plan. This section will describe the techniques used in eliciting user and system needs, defining the requirements, and evaluating the success of the requirements gathering process (these techniques are covered later in this unit).\r</p><table id="d68c0fbd7ca94622896b975733792dd5" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="iff474ad0a26f41d89d73d718f8b4e632" /><caption><p id="f181a724bdf1422f87bae7149873a86a" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="bbb81e90d6c548718c786165944c7ef7"><em style="italic">Change control and requirements gathering: </em>Modern day collaboration tools will support <em style="italic">change control</em>. However, a change control process should be documented to ensure that changes to requirements are formally managed.\r</p></td></tr></table><wb:inline idref="neweb9368bf39be415ead82b9fb43a83883" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\r\n'