b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\r\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ff16c81c152740aa9d2d3e312b8cc4f7"><head><title>Accuracy versus Interpretability</title><objref idref="aaaf4d4a01484fd3aff18868f882e298" /></head><body><p id="c2ed1ffba8f94c37a89ea2635a578444">Throughout this course, you have learned about understanding your client&apos;s needs, develop and implement the right analytic solution to meet those objectives. At this stage, we want to think through the interpretability of models. This will be helpful for fixing issues with the model, and explaining why a model produced its results. <em style="italic">Interpretability </em>is a very important research area in Data Science and Machine Learning. We want to explain why a model produces certain results and what happens when there are changes within a model; also known as <em style="italic">explainability. </em>Interpretability ensures that a data scientist can measure the effects of any trade-offs within a model. </p><p id="a32627b702cb484fae8601fd74239731">Let us turn our attention to the accuracy of a model and how its results can proffer better solutions and decisions. As you know by now, errors can be the difference between a useful solution and a solution that will lead to loss of money and (with how data science solutions are integrated into everyday life) lives. <em style="italic">Accuracy</em> can be defined as the measurement used to determine the best model for a task. If the model can properly generalize new data, it will produce better results (such as predictions). </p><p id="e4609ce2e6c547ffbf8da487d4cc9d90">There are certain sectors that are restricted by laws and standards in their use of certain techniques, an example is the banking and education industry. Some of these restrictions protect the consumers data and ensure that bias is not introduced into the decision making process. As you read on the last page, the more we learn about interpretability, and employ interpretability strategies, these issues might become a thing of the past. Accuracy is very important in these sectors and as we have learned, accuracy will typically lead to less interpretability. The big question is &quot;how can we retain interpretability, while improving accuracy?&quot;</p><p id="d6baab4a3d394b299566a46949f3dc90"><link href="https://www.oreilly.com/content/predictive-modeling-striking-a-balance-between-accuracy-and-interpretability/" target="new" internal="false">Hall (2016)</link> has recommended the following steps: </p><ul id="d3bfc7e19bc04dbf9510dbf47fe5c4d6"><li><p id="a6a5f1379f2d42a1987e66df34108e4b">Train black box models and use them as benchmarks.</p></li><li><p id="c3bed7471dc14adda7f105c6e08dc0db">Use different regression techniques.</p></li><li><p id="b3a8bb847ff44b8785275bfdc821bdb5">Use black box models in the deployment process.</p></li><li><p id="d11af9f5e7494d5291a999b5b9cedcdc">Train small interpretable ensemble models.</p></li><li><p id="f2edee7b7cf2499b9192bcd8dbb75386">Create nonlinear predictors using black box techniques.</p></li><li><p id="caec629e262e40a7bbb0ba65ee4484ae">Explain black box models better using variable importance measures.</p></li></ul><image id="d1157a9cd3c845929780b8b445c269bb" src="../webcontent/Accuracy_vs_Interpretability.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="f4dde8b7997e47e5a41d8910e0c3a30b"><em style="italic">Source: </em><link href="http://datascienceninja.com/" target="new" internal="false"><em style="italic">Rane-2018</em><em style="italic"><sup>1</sup></em></link></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="e74e100355cc4b038f2f6a9bf7460b3d">In the next module, we will discuss the different metrics to evaluate model accuracy.</p><wb:inline idref="newc4042dc106bb443485fac575eac5079c" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\r\n'