<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="newa26a93bfc540457ea04cf76a8abc29b4" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="1"><title>Quiz 3</title><page id="ee9d43f3abf84de79b3bd9acc88e969b"><title>Page 1</title><content available="always"><p id="e5f73076aab14cc8bff945407d478ce6">Welcome to Quiz 3! Please answer the questions and select the options with the BEST fit. You can justify your answers as well (a space is provided at the end of the quiz for all questions). Please <em>read</em> the question clearly. It is not expected that answers can be directly sourced from OLI. Some questions test your understanding and ability to apply a concept discussed on OLI. All the best.</p></content><content available="always"><p id="d446a4b57ebc4de084fb1a296f5c281d">Review the table below and answer questions 1-3. (<em style="italic"> </em><em style="italic"><em>The table contains 14 records. If it is not displaying properly, please note that the Last record is UserID-986, Loanpackage-Conventional, PropType-SingleFamily, Income-$80k</em></em>).</p><image id="e1cac3e7979043078e2fc583592e606f" src="../webcontent/Q3_(2).jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="fd75af88d95a41438a3e3ee16732663b" /></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></content><multiple_choice id="newa26a93bfc540457ea04cf76a8abc29b4_1a" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="e1d88e949ebb44fba276ad4963ab6685">If you transform <em>LoanPackage </em>to a dummy variable and assume that you will use the most frequent category as the reference category. Which statement below is correct:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">You should create a third category as your reference category.</choice><choice value="no">Conventional would be the reference category.</choice><choice value="adb81c9975f947058671c2ca13d23293">You can use either category as the reference category.</choice><choice value="c16a2bb40bda40e68d29e81c21cb43b2">USDA would be the reference category.</choice></input><part id="caa0e8dc3f6644db8122359d42bcac43"><skillref idref="db33e28466704689ab10354a5334deba" /><response match="yes" score="0"><feedback><p id="a9b81e36a58844cba6ceee91eac77966">Incorrect: There is no need for this with this dataset.</p></feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback><p id="c59fa92390aa44449ad83e4b94e7e51d">Incorrect: This category does not have the most frequent category.</p></feedback></response><response match="adb81c9975f947058671c2ca13d23293" score="0"><feedback><p id="c67dae42be704ec292010a8e6e416e03">Incorrect: You want to use the category with the most frequent category as directed.</p></feedback></response><response match="c16a2bb40bda40e68d29e81c21cb43b2" score="10"><feedback><p id="aaeb94ca484642aa81bed80d8b9a35bf">Correct: When creating dummy variables, the reference category is typically the category with most frequent occurences.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="c65fe0ac3db9422fb2911e70a19f469a" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="f9a65f5b28f140b09468708a65b18b36">Transform the <em>PropertyType</em> into category scores, Single Family = 1 and Townhouse = 0. How many would have the category score of 0?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f19a14e6bfd74e4c8b90d5ed81402d1c" labels="false"><choice value="cf12a3c2320841819d01e9d76341ade8">5</choice><choice value="e53f747ba5cc4f1cbd4f4ed6a7ff0315">6</choice><choice value="b573fd4eee84412085d95e93c1120e1f">8</choice><choice value="bf41d72ec5524ebbbfdc8f81fd994da7">14</choice></input><part id="a2dc1af4a4cc401cb3489b5ab11b2f49"><skillref idref="db33e28466704689ab10354a5334deba" /><response match="cf12a3c2320841819d01e9d76341ade8" score="0"><feedback><p id="a6cacd7dae3e4cd8ae75031390fa211c">Incorrect: You are missing one more observation.</p></feedback></response><response match="e53f747ba5cc4f1cbd4f4ed6a7ff0315" score="10"><feedback><p id="c629cd8dbaed484fa6b974c02fe34d9b">Correct: You have identified the correct number of values with a category score = 0.</p></feedback></response><response match="b573fd4eee84412085d95e93c1120e1f" score="0"><feedback><p id="fcc3b0c635964594a0e2fa975c490199">Incorrect: 8 would be the total number of Single Family or category score = 1.</p></feedback></response><response match="bf41d72ec5524ebbbfdc8f81fd994da7" score="0"><feedback><p id="b8c4bceb35ff4882836d71f60a707096">Incorrect: 14 would be the total number of PropertyType values.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="cd07e6c5e34e48cba9dff5b4351e68fa" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="c243201512f14af08c156a992166c82b">Assume you had four categories in the <em>LoanPackage</em> variable, how would you transform those categories to dummy variables:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d9da4f7a82f34ca2b2399fc8f3b35a8d" labels="false"><choice value="d35f564ab2c946769844619baebd10db">You would transform all categories to dummy variables as long as you have less than five (5) categories.</choice><choice value="d2b1ae259ee248749a15f1097c76b2d9">You would use the k-1 rule to transform the categories to dummy variables.</choice><choice value="f96a201c3b3446bcb09450c7b965beed">You would bin the like-categories into two variables.</choice><choice value="fb43a9788b9948ee80e5ec8dc1526c60">You would select the two variables that are useful to your analysis and omit the other categories.</choice></input><part id="bcd4737d996d4486b0f513ef506010b2"><skillref idref="db33e28466704689ab10354a5334deba" /><response match="d35f564ab2c946769844619baebd10db" score="0"><feedback><p id="c3c43350762f468b9205c6cf3ca0b0e7">Incorrect: You should use the k-1 rule to transform categories into dummy variables. </p></feedback></response><response match="d2b1ae259ee248749a15f1097c76b2d9" score="10"><feedback><p id="b89470d6d2bc4c2b9591952e3a6ec9a2">Correct: Depending on the tool you use, you will be assigned a reference category. You can make that reference category the most frequent category.</p></feedback></response><response match="f96a201c3b3446bcb09450c7b965beed" score="0"><feedback><p id="ebc1045660d748bd81dd3e77e6c75585">Incorrect: This would result in loss of data and affect the quality of your results. </p></feedback></response><response match="fb43a9788b9948ee80e5ec8dc1526c60" score="0"><feedback><p id="fc483817181147b9a9de26a5f846b94d">Incorrect: You should avoid omission as much as possible so that you do not lose data that produce useful results for decision making.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="ef673d0001e2424da2eba4a0dda79a27" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="dcb5bab62f344a1f9f8ab2e9a2a72004">You want to have a better understanding of your client and you are running a report to inspect a dataset the client has provided to you. While cleaning up the dataset, you have handled missing values, however the dataset is quite large and would benefit from creating categories by binning. To do this, you would start by:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="b8839b580d374afdbe9fc6d388a7542d" labels="false"><choice value="fbb45d0c949b45b38338251b00d74e3c">Dropping 15% of observations to create a smaller sample that you can explore.</choice><choice value="c0ad7ce1a8c3449eb93bfb8619519f7a">Identifying the values you want to transform into bins.</choice><choice value="db9475668c874ba1982a2ea778a7355e">Omitting all the missing value/values in the dataset, as this will allow for smoother binning.</choice><choice value="a1a56bf2097b480b9e0689a60ec0cad8">Splitting your dataset into two categories to allow for smoother exploration.</choice></input><part id="ef057563d7e243e7944ef3858180f4f9"><skillref idref="ff782392a1bf4d459d4195a7bfccb5aa" /><skillref idref="cdeb75b111df47138d58db1ee21409e5" /><response match="fbb45d0c949b45b38338251b00d74e3c" score="0"><feedback><p id="f22bb766819f405c84b48a9d3fcc6fa2">Incorrect: You should not delete observations without reason.</p></feedback></response><response match="c0ad7ce1a8c3449eb93bfb8619519f7a" score="10"><feedback><p id="e2c0a3b078a243f084db541797d174fa">Correct: This is the first step you should take when you are binning values.</p></feedback></response><response match="db9475668c874ba1982a2ea778a7355e" score="0"><feedback><p id="db61cf8d36b64ad3b33fa60d8353da2e">Incorrect: You have handled all missing values and should not repeat this step now that you are binning.</p></feedback></response><response match="a1a56bf2097b480b9e0689a60ec0cad8" score="0"><feedback><p id="bfb37cbf8ced48ceb796733a39a4407d">Incorrect: You should not subset your variables without reason and certainly not for &quot;smoother exploration&quot;.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><essay id="bcc61ab6bf4545adb3b475f424d7572c" grading="automatic"><body><p id="f872706b1f1d4379956b0866a35df9b4">Justify your answer:</p></body><part id="f6c21b3745ea473c892924237bf99697"><skillref idref="ff782392a1bf4d459d4195a7bfccb5aa" /><response match="*" score="1"><feedback><p id="abc2964db5254e318e8f938e47b9ef6b" /></feedback></response></part></essay><multiple_choice id="ad3f7244400141b5b09cf1df5b3ca7b4" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="e62c4d612918439e8fda251c3187e11d">You are analyzing a retirement benefits data set for GMU Inc&apos;s HR Department. That dataset contains 20,000 observations and 14 variables. You are now assessing the <em>PensionPlan </em>variable. <em>PensionPlan</em> contains the names of the four (4) companies that provide retirement services to all GMU employees. It is mandatory for each record in the dataset to have a retirement account with one of the four companies, thus no observation has a blank value in the <em>PensionPlan </em>variable. You are transforming <em>PensionPlan</em> to dummy variables to allow for better exploration, how many variables should be created?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="b036b01cd4024ca0818a68ae55ad7e36" labels="false"><choice value="d4ba919aafd148618a20f9c029ce3525">3</choice><choice value="e52511fc8cd54d30adb31f4f05ba021e">5</choice><choice value="d32d16333ab2470890b38a360b89c6ad">2</choice><choice value="aee2dec9bd94407d8623c38df58e343a">1</choice></input><part id="ccea781333914fd895dac8083b8e8ed4"><skillref idref="ff782392a1bf4d459d4195a7bfccb5aa" /><skillref idref="db33e28466704689ab10354a5334deba" /><response match="d4ba919aafd148618a20f9c029ce3525" score="10"><feedback><p id="c189d775912249b1a3f1de3e597cfdc9">Correct: Implement the k-1 rule to create your dummy variables.</p></feedback></response><response match="e52511fc8cd54d30adb31f4f05ba021e" score="0"><feedback><p id="a5c2573ad1b44881a393be7b82615f31">Incorrect: Selecting this option means you added one extra variable to the dataset.</p></feedback></response><response match="d32d16333ab2470890b38a360b89c6ad" score="0"><feedback><p id="c971af30f4914c728b903817bfeb69ac">Incorrect: You have only selected two variables meaning you will lose data.</p></feedback></response><response match="aee2dec9bd94407d8623c38df58e343a" score="0"><feedback><p id="e95c4076546e4c2d8578afe9efc37e0f">Incorrect: If you leave the variables as is, you will run into issues when it is time to to build your model.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="a6aead370fa948d5811f3dc64aec56e7" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="c2c16746713541cab912f8c6d8027b60">What is the first step in treating a dataset with missing values:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="a4ff09a17bdb4476a18546d92c690495" labels="false"><choice value="cede5468beb443e593a5cda5b2ddbebe">Count the number of observations with missing values and if it is less than 10% of your dataset, the data is usable. You can do this because 10% of a dataset is not considered to be a sizeable amount of data.</choice><choice value="a882bf6bff1744f98ebbfb3f12ac8d3b">You want to understand why the values are missing. As best as possible, determine if it was due to data entry error or otherwise. A dataset with too many missing values could be incomplete and unusable. </choice><choice value="a5c835778d7e40c8b7f86b5b08accc46">The first step in handling missing values is to always use the omission technique as it saves time. Immediately using the omission technique to exclude some observations from the dataset will result in a clean dataset.</choice><choice value="d8accbee1a404cea997536a231134fc6">The first step in handling missing values is to replace the missing values with the mean value of all the observations or the values in that variable. You do not lose data and you have a more representative dataset.</choice></input><part id="c4c0b2c8be18475dbc9b707208b1c203"><skillref idref="ad4e5db0d42b4b37aac33bd55d481663" /><skillref idref="b46137cc3d904241bbc85b0e6f4cd421" /><response match="cede5468beb443e593a5cda5b2ddbebe" score="0"><feedback><p id="cae82553db2d44f1bed24704e7dd51e6">Incorrect: You must consider that 10% of a dataset with say 100 records would have a greater effect on analysis than 10% of a dataset with 1 million observations. You would still lose information in both cases so refrain from taking this route.</p></feedback></response><response match="a882bf6bff1744f98ebbfb3f12ac8d3b" score="10"><feedback><p id="e46171143cc341208019902424f90e7a">Correct: This will help you determine if the dataset is usable or if data collection is still ongoing. Once you have taken this step and determined that the data is usable, you can apply one of the techniques for handling missing values.</p></feedback></response><response match="a5c835778d7e40c8b7f86b5b08accc46" score="0"><feedback><p id="bd34dd6104d44fe9b74e1d8ce1ff28da">Incorrect: You can decide on one of two missing value strategies after you have determined the reason why the dataset has missing values.</p></feedback></response><response match="d8accbee1a404cea997536a231134fc6" score="0"><feedback><p id="ddc79ef55a794d859b6f9dff400244a1">Incorrect: You can decide on one of two missing value strategies after you have determined the reason why the dataset has missing values.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><essay id="b71411485fe34ecb86db6e89fa0569c7" grading="automatic"><body><p id="bbef6be7223d414d98f38e321a663f73">Justify your answer</p></body><part id="f5aeb1ca242f40a6be5472d268c5e400"><skillref idref="b46137cc3d904241bbc85b0e6f4cd421" /><response match="*" score="1"><feedback><p id="da91ae4593ac4fa1a3ecd873de8b0eac" /></feedback></response></part></essay><multiple_choice id="e4f4613a107b41918fc4c80a568518d2" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="d0cf263446014a45908c47c988bca940">The transformation process in the data wrangling pipeline must be approached systematically. Once you have gathered or extracted data from the appropriate sources, your next step should be to:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="e4544a2886ca4e3c8b4b32eb46f79ee8" labels="false"><choice value="c6ccc704bc894601a9a6beab90ca43b2">Assess the quality of the data.</choice><choice value="ea9f6631b40646e1b9c8783adbfb5c32">Begin replacing missing values.</choice><choice value="ebf927c448464907aa84ce7354cb26ff">Begin by transforming categorical variables as they are most difficult to transform.</choice><choice value="dfbf3622f1064f0e8c91ff3dd6136071">Begin by transforming numeric variables. </choice></input><part id="df56a3e586d649679e1fe0db6994694c"><skillref idref="b46137cc3d904241bbc85b0e6f4cd421" /><response match="c6ccc704bc894601a9a6beab90ca43b2" score="10"><feedback><p id="d34aa306343c4f1491d4304abf4d501c">Correct: Inspecting your data either through visualizing the data, or performing simple assessment tasks like counting will give you better insight into the quality of your dataset. </p></feedback></response><response match="ea9f6631b40646e1b9c8783adbfb5c32" score="0"><feedback><p id="dc0faa8d86fd480687f70b5a5e2bade5">Incorrect:  Missing values are handled different ways and you should not begin replacing them until you have assessed your data and its quality.</p></feedback></response><response match="ebf927c448464907aa84ce7354cb26ff" score="0"><feedback><p id="ec6e097e7d6648bda12c5eb637288643">Incorrect: The only way you would know that categorical values need to be transformed is by assessing the quality of your data.</p></feedback></response><response match="dfbf3622f1064f0e8c91ff3dd6136071" score="0"><feedback><p id="ec6bd66b52154cbeb94593455ff02841">Incorrect: The only way you would know that numeric values need to be transformed is by assessing the quality of your data.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="c9d2a90d84904c18896c059070fcc58f" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="c1c43ff3de0343318f54bb7ca7abc7db">You are conducting research on alumni relations for a University. You will have access to the University&apos;s extensive 300,000 record alumni database for this study. You will need data on the alumni but you will not collect data from all alumni. You have determined that your sample size is 60,000. Which of the following options is an example of performing stratified sampling:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="f8368144ccd94abfa1c0b95a10f76a4e" labels="false"><choice value="d28766559a174df583469f28870b5965">You group alumni according to the three (3) alumni status. From the total number of records in each group, you will select 10,000 records from the 40-59 year alumni status group, 20,000 records from the 20-39 year alumni status group, and 30,000 records from the 0-19 year alumni status group. </choice><choice value="d893913126564fae9c4c53b818eb8849">You will create groups of alumni according to their status, the groups are 40-59 year alumni status, 20-39 year alumni status, and 0-19 year alumni status. You will then select two (2) of the three (3) groups and then randomly select records from the two (2) groups. </choice><choice value="fba1e84cdd824bd4b02c72bda496cc27">You select every 5th record from your entire alumni population until you have reached 60,000 records, and then you gather those records as your sample.</choice><choice value="a2124f24152248c18774a4af243ee4a6">You randomly select 60,000 records across all alumni groups as your sample prior to beginning data collection and analysis. </choice></input><part id="c948dccfd40b42ad9d368ebf4824dfe9"><skillref idref="b163095f2da44799ab4246c5f4758178" /><response match="d28766559a174df583469f28870b5965" score="10"><feedback><p id="c0f852c9fc15427d87d087123c0c1a2e">Correct: When you divide your dataset into separate groups and select records from that group by dividing your sample over the entire population and multiplying that by the size of each strata, you used the stratified sampling technique.</p></feedback></response><response match="d893913126564fae9c4c53b818eb8849" score="0"><feedback><p id="b7d0a7b88ca44f988b86ed3e3d674331">Incorrect: In this example, you are using the cluster sampling method.</p></feedback></response><response match="fba1e84cdd824bd4b02c72bda496cc27" score="0"><feedback><p id="a352f493eb5642888a69bcbb7b3589a6">Incorrect: This is using the systematic sampling method.</p></feedback></response><response match="a2124f24152248c18774a4af243ee4a6" score="0"><feedback><p id="e1e14e2d9a6e4900b263be6282473189">Incorrect: You are using the random sampling method.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><essay id="a3e13015e0ae4a08a4ff29539ef950a1" grading="automatic"><body><p id="f8a57fed3d69457ab3a2d3389451321e">Feel free to justify your answer:</p></body><part id="a354b340684a41a4b2f7e6a63141e725"><skillref idref="b163095f2da44799ab4246c5f4758178" /><response match="*" score="1"><feedback><p id="b867444b91b14e80b435fba11eada441" /></feedback></response></part></essay><multiple_choice id="e4cd5617d5af4f38bf74980f2028b4fa" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="a29aa16eff8a4fc9a1fd68c09228b0c3">Which statement below <em>best </em>defines data transformation:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="b0f5ebafc2db416e947330b9f655f629" labels="false"><choice value="ffb317e705e9422d84aa432491bf46c4">Converting data from one structure to another.</choice><choice value="ba07128203614d2283b09a0345c8a800">Extracting portions of your data for the purpose of analysis.</choice><choice value="d76deba6b5744982992a1983e0ec8189">Replacing missing values with the mean values across all observations in the dataset.</choice><choice value="cc5e6f1fcd884e0cbd453ba927f76d64">Visualizing data to identify outliers.</choice></input><part id="e5363775e6cc4d53ab209d5ec180bbe5"><skillref idref="ff782392a1bf4d459d4195a7bfccb5aa" /><skillref idref="b46137cc3d904241bbc85b0e6f4cd421" /><response match="ffb317e705e9422d84aa432491bf46c4" score="10"><feedback><p id="b4fc2e45112b4a5a984c46bd855b2c89">Correct: Data transformation is the data conversion process of transforming data from one structure to another.</p></feedback></response><response match="ba07128203614d2283b09a0345c8a800" score="0"><feedback><p id="b037d4f51b314196a203a01f68abe285">Correct: Data transformation is the data conversion process of transforming data from one structure to another.</p></feedback></response><response match="d76deba6b5744982992a1983e0ec8189" score="0"><feedback><p id="ded67520033f403b9b374a6f0be6b416">Incorrect: When you replace missing values using a statistical method, you are performing imputation. </p></feedback></response><response match="cc5e6f1fcd884e0cbd453ba927f76d64" score="0"><feedback><p id="a466279cc7f9460f8c89afd09fe03542">Incorrect: Visualizing your data can be done prior to transforming your data.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><multiple_choice id="d729f9a530564fd39958e9fb570ad58a" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="f30ae86505d848d3aa9581fad6d5ce54">The data wrangling process is a key part of data understanding and one of the most time consuming tasks in the data science project lifecycle. Although a data scientist should be skilled at inspecting, preparing and enriching your data, there are other team members that can assist with this process or handle this process in the absence of an in-house data scientist. Assume an organization has all the roles listed in the options below on a data project team. Which of the roles would be best suited for handling the data wrangling process:</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="d1a5664cdc9b4c1cad267750ec89c54b" labels="false"><choice value="bb8b4324aedc450193cdf39998cae10b">Data Analyst.</choice><choice value="e0dc8a7eebea497c996ab05f9ffe7bfc">Project Manager.</choice><choice value="b15e68e8e7df4f5fb9db0f82ee2e2017">Business Analyst.</choice><choice value="b16cac68908e4dcca5061224fc86f471">Solutions Architect.</choice></input><part id="c06984c84c064b91aa80006ee4281c63"><skillref idref="b5c81529dbd64d2fa9c4b8a9dd71bf1d" /><response match="bb8b4324aedc450193cdf39998cae10b" score="10"><feedback><p id="bbbc916879e14c8eb25a5bf4927a02b8">Correct: The data analyst is best suited for this role as they work with exploring the dataset and can provide insights prior to model development. </p></feedback></response><response match="e0dc8a7eebea497c996ab05f9ffe7bfc" score="0"><feedback><p id="b34e5511afbf466e8d44b031c3afc4d1">Incorrect: The project manager handles project task management.</p></feedback></response><response match="b15e68e8e7df4f5fb9db0f82ee2e2017" score="0"><feedback><p id="da3df22624c04eeab47065928b8256a8">Incorrect: The business analyst has client-facing skills and might not be technically inclined to data wrangling tasks.</p></feedback></response><response match="b16cac68908e4dcca5061224fc86f471" score="0"><feedback><p id="d3f4f12abfe64f5bba81d6e587d46015">Incorrect: The solutions architect might have the technical skills but will not be involved in the data wrangling process.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice><essay id="cc347878b494409dad74d2b9f9e60720" grading="automatic"><body><p id="bd83c3711ede49a495bca301fdb8cb94">You can use this space to include more information related to questions you answered during the quiz:</p></body><part id="a9f92056690744fea6b39bb791ff8a76"><skillref idref="b46137cc3d904241bbc85b0e6f4cd421" /><response match="*" score="1"><feedback><p id="d5209c4f34364144b8940c8a40e9a325" /></feedback></response></part></essay></page></assessment>
