b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="a2c9cadf120741b1b0709f4ea57eea38"><head><title>Overview (Draft)</title><objref idref="bb8cd74aab6c47c39d8c9786d3b7eb30" /><objref idref="e8adf19133834c47a6a0fc1b7e84ae08" /><objref idref="f4d0b27f5b9e41ef9f78810b14467651" /></head><body><p id="b2dbbf4381ad4a4184f91ad4e007a870">You have learned that understanding a problem is an important step in providing a solution. We can apply this same thought process to exploring our data before building and deploying solutions. When you investigate and understand your data, you will uncover patterns, test hypotheses, check assumptions, and spot anomalies. This process is called <em>Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA)\r. </em></p><table id="f1ed7aade4b449a591c31fd6fadb66b1" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i6d60b48eca3945629c816c44936746b8" /><caption><p id="c972c19422ce4ce1a70e25007a1d0395" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b2d525a80dd14730ae27f06560bf46b3">\xe2\x80\x9cExploratory data analysis is an approach to analyzing data sets to summarize their main characteristics, often with visual methods. A statistical model can be used as well\xe2\x80\x9d. The main purpose of EDA is to see what the data can tell you beyond formal modeling.</p></td></tr></table><p id="b51077ed43674fb9a0aa5fd92e205993"><em>Importance of Exploratory Data Analysis</em></p><p id="a987b2c014a7466c966ac47ebca3e23d">Data can tell stories, help decision makers glean insights about their organizations and influence our general way of life. Now that we have access to large amounts of data that are sometimes &quot;free&quot; (think data gotten from google dataset toolbox) and in other cases require programming skills for access (data that your scrap from the web using Python programming skills), you must use this data responsibly, even when the data is sourced internally. One responsible use of data is exploration. Exploring your data allows you to:</p><ul id="c0ccc68f7cfc492fb1a0d67fcade1a3e"><li><p id="d991455b23c04cbf8c640c5cca936c0e">Identify trends and patterns in the data.</p></li><li><p id="eeee37ea1dac4fed8080ca3f1d4d7034">Highlight outlier values in the data.</p></li><li><p id="d05b94617d374cfaafbabfbb1b9128f3">Draw conclusions on the data even without modeling.</p></li><li><p id="c097aceca98e49c8a1b758c831f14804">Visualize the data to pinpoint points of action.</p></li></ul><p id="c6d49a624f364e1eae0986fc3594cdd0">We perform exploratory data analysis using the following steps:</p><ol id="a585a9e8a4ab4305b63580ce01df7a69"><li><p id="d3ab9a5672e444afb4a77dbd23e8575f">Visually inspect the data - What are we looking for? Missing values or rows, strange text in otherwise numerical columns, obvious problems.\r</p></li><li><p id="eb8b0329519748ada719094b25f35f57">Perform basic statistical analysis on each column/variable - This allows us to get an overall understanding of the data.\r</p></li><li><p id="a82e7218bab74c66b9d9635e46292a26">Graph columns using simple visualizations - this allows us to identify potential issues in the data that might not be quickly seen with visual inspections or with basic statistics.</p></li></ol><p id="eabd34caa33149c7a39ab457b124b597">Take a look at the data in the figure below:</p><image id="bb5d5e20a78c42c8a99dad880458d4ca" src="../webcontent/Unit4_(4).jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="fd57b4429eb2403686352628967c30db"><em style="italic">Sample Dataset (Four (4) sets, 11 observations with two (2) variables each)</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ef36620ed1e54f40a37beb8a0e8c89ae">Now take a look at the averages for all sets. You notice that the averages and summary statistics are the same. Could this mean that the data is statistically the same?</p><image id="e97ec17b45354ac1a1155a403e026d84" src="../webcontent/Unit4_Table_(3).jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="a3fcfb1817c5461f9fa80b2b885d15a9"><em style="italic">Averages for sample dataset</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><image id="d0dc89b9018f4c7ea2e4dc65a8197673" src="../webcontent/Unit41.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="f163cd3f5e22480c96dcebe57e23f00e"><em style="italic">Summary Measures of Sample Data</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="ca7925c8956d42939b03ec0a114271cd">Now, let us plot the data. This is when you will see the difference between sets a, b, c, and d.</p><figure id="b0efeb217ee748cf81e945244375fb2d"><title>Visual Representation</title><image id="db5b9c8799114a11a2fc0d263ebe96b6" src="../webcontent/Unit4_5.jpg" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle"><caption><p id="cabb6dcc516146eb89c7176650b59341"><em style="italic">Plots of Sets within Sample Dataset.</em></p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></figure><p id="cf34fd4e33b04c758878425201242642">As you see from the above, example; visualizing our data is helpful in seeing patterns that are otherwise difficult to spot using summary statistics. As a data scientist, it would be careless to explore data with just summary statistics and proceed to feature engineering and model development. You can see in Set C, there is an outlier and the spread of the data is set D needs more exploration. Let us break down each of these steps on the next page. On the next page, we will describe how to approach each summary statistic and use visualizations to support your exploration process. This module will also expose us to engineering features of our dataset as a way to explore, understand, and finalize the preparation process before attempting data science tasks.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'