b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ac0b705f87d44dbdab3a7b27dfd6f04b"><head><title>Module 12 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="da7c14c3999541afbdbcdadefb341293"><li><p id="c12f1953a6e24af083bde63dd68b1d02">Statistical Inference is the process of drawing inferences from your data using probability theory. Statistical inference is used to draw scientific conclusions and test hypotheses.</p></li><li><p id="bc5a42ac71824abca1e599c9b7e1d590">If n samples are drawn from the same distribution and are independently distributed, they are said to be independently and identically distributed.</p></li><li><p id="cc29ef4cfaf7410f9a177da33a6778fe">As the sample size n increases, the standard error approaches the true standard deviation for large n. This is because the standard error is an estimate of the true value of the standard deviation.</p></li><li><p id="f4d553b740884bb591099c356b38380b">A hypothesis test is a statistical procedure by which you can test some assumption about some fact about the true distribution of your dataset.</p></li><li><p id="be2e437e509e4ed68421db9fec19cf1d">A hypothesis test is used to demonstrate that certain hypotheses are unlikely given the assumptions and evidence; they are NOT iron-clad rules that infallibly demonstrate that some fact about your data or the universe must hold.</p></li><li><p id="ea4db13927504e0ca8b09cee3a7d5fb0">The two error types in hypothesis testing:</p><ul id="e9be697117094b08a93db69f5946a316"><li><p id="c6430e374c8446448e3a181f21dddce8">Type I error occurs when you reject the null hypothesis when it should be accepted.</p></li><li><p id="a6eead8f158d48b28ae86116c2952fd7">Type II error occurs when you accept the null hypothesis (or fail to reject the null hypothesis) when it should be rejected.</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="e11a73b000964bba858d6e0a74dfa985">A smaller p-value means that there is stronger evidence in favor of the alternative hypothesis.</p></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'