b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="b7fc652555dd4e58905c7bf58c6e2395"><head><title>Module 7 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="ee98a74d107443c2ab35131527c5dabd"><li><p id="a6ca8602a04345339c3c3ea40d5fa4ad">Data collection is the process of gathering and organizing data that can meet defined business and analytic objectives. Data collection also consists of attending to issues of validity, reliability, and ethics, such as provisions for informed consent from participants. </p></li><li><p id="de36cc05241b455a8d741e52196fbe4f">Data scientists need to develop a sound study design for execution while ensuring the validity and integrity of the inference. There is a range of study design options, from an exploratory analysis of data that is organically available to highly planned efforts. The manner in which data is collected is arguably more important than the availability of that data itself.</p></li><li><p id="ace63c5bd9f14f8fa5299469dafca237">Validity is the development of sound evidence to demonstrate the intended test interpretation.  In an observational study, the threat to validity concerns whether the observed changes can be attributed to the exposure or intervention and not to other causes and whether we can generalize that exposure more universally causes the outcomes.</p></li><li><p id="a1eaebe7347848e6b7ecafa46ddc6709">Threats to internal validity are problems in drawing correct inferences about whether the covariation between the presumed treatment variable and the outcome reflects a causal relationship.</p></li><li><p id="fac13816060e4ad78dcee369a3ae2650">Threats to external validity are problems that threaten our ability to draw correct inferences from the sample data to other persons, settings, treatment variables, and measures.</p></li><li><p id="d185e22d175c4a01bf82aebfb0ed21ca">Statistical bias results from violations of external validity or internal validity of a study. Common statistical biases that you need to be aware of and take into account during the data understanding process are:</p><ul id="a1485483338e4bc78dca2bb7279c09f0"><li><p id="e0539c3032dd4a06ab7f0dc73324bda4">Selection Bias: a threat to internal validity occurs when there is a mismatch between the data selected for the study and the subject matter that the data scientist wants to make inferences about.</p></li><li><p id="c9435825003b4364ad88ddee78006a64">Self-selection Bias: If the response rate of a survey is not perfect, it is likely that certain characteristics of those individuals are related to the reason why they responded to the survey.</p></li><li><p id="d4c400efaa4149db8cec76b8406237a1">Confirmation Bias: This type of bias occurs when we favor evidence that confirms our personal beliefs, values, and hypotheses.</p></li><li><p id="f26796e43a134ecb8fa722d0149193bf">Information Bias: The data collected has a misclassification bias and is not accurate. One way to control information bias is to implement blinding.</p></li><li><p id="be5b533d61bb4a8e925c4f3dbfcea153">Confounding Bias: occurs when incorrect inferences are made about the subject matter while failing to account for a potentially confounding variable.</p></li></ul></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'