b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="bc86b2c06c584fada885798b85a0df59"><head><title>Overview-Data Governance</title><objref idref="d0f8e9f76375441192f2c1f342e6f228" /></head><body><p id="cbbb3585de56407fb6a66b3654734edc">Data governance defines how data is accessed and managed within an organization. It is important because it facilitates effective data management and has positive implications for the quality, security, and integrity of data used for analysis. An organization that handles data efficiently understands that data governance impacts data quality and the decisions that can be made from the data available to the organization. This unit focuses on data governance as a component of data management, and how it influences the development of analytic solutions in an organization and decision making. Any organization that stores and utilizes data should have a data governance strategy for internal data or data stored within the organization and external data.</p><p id="c5e8049115f84e40915153754d7a94dd">Data governance is beneficial because it provides a reliable and consistent view of enterprise wide data, it ensures that there is a plan for improved quality of data, maps the location of data in the enterprise reducing the scourge of data silos, and improves data management overall. </p><table id="ffa027fafa2146f381bf81d596b4fa8b" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i3a1f1abfbed648e2bb2751460294362f" /><caption><p id="d3edcf5bf9834d0db328886b4cafed57" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="d415de477c5b4d5194b63d492760acc2">Reading: <link href="http://eprints.staffs.ac.uk/2804/1/A_Conceptual_Framework_for_Designing_Data_Governan.pdf" target="new" internal="false">Data Governance in the Cloud .</link></p></td></tr></table><p id="f6d50bd971574dbda54140a93fe7cbf5">Data governance is the responsibility of an entire organization although it is administered by the data management team; all users of data in an organization are considered stakeholders of the organization&apos;s data. <link href="http://www.datagovernance.com/" target="new" internal="false">The Data Governance Institute</link> defines a stakeholder as an individual or group that make or is affected by data driven decisions within an organization. In addition to data governance policies, data stakeholders will have an influence on the state and use of data. As a quick reminder, the data science team works with different individuals in an organization to define business and analytic objectives during the data science project lifecycle, as well as determining the requirements for the analytic solution. So why is data governance important to a member of a data science project team? </p><p id="bdb102bad59c451eaca60127eb60d406">Data governance is not just policy making for data, it is more than that; it influences business strategy because data is now (more than ever) considered as an asset to an organization. An organization that has embedded data governance principles into its data infrastructure or data management framework will abide by data standards (industry set, or company defined). </p><p id="adf00e6524ee4d4ea75c32347ad0e488">Data governance best practices for organizations are met when data has integrity, and data related decisions and controls are transparent and can be audited. Another best practice that is gaining ground in industry is the push for organizations to collect and store data that is unbiased. Unbiased data looks different to each organization and industry but the general idea is that the data represents all members of a population that could be served by an organization. This best practice will positively influence the development of ethical models and algorithms for analytic solutions. </p><table id="d7b7339c0a64401e8d8efa0a3994302a" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i975cf8f4d1eb40f887575bedef9748bd" /><caption><p id="ddf12172d85b460187f14b004c2e1999" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b8cdbea96a1b4a8e867c04c573aeda2d">Reading: <link href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/full/10.1098/rsta.2016.0117" target="new" internal="false">Data Governance and its implications for ethical models </link></p></td></tr></table><wb:inline idref="newf9c14ddfce7240989dca05a140a009ce" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'