b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="be50f4c7ce7b4382a1231a706241783f"><head><title>Module 6 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="d66c57278a4248bdb0033d600528967b"><li><p id="d30fc4f62dd94a858249ae6129b39012">It is necessary to establish a design for the project as it can help identify various bottlenecks of the project. This documentation makes the developers begin thinking about the various risks and challenges involved in the data science project. Some key design considerations that developers should address include assumptions that they will be making throughout the project, the various constraints involved, and the system environment. A clear understanding of the data flow and design must be developed. This can be done by using various flow diagrams like domain model, component, interface design, activity, entity, class, and sequence diagrams. The developers are also prompted to consider the many risks and difficulties that the data science project may present.</p></li><li><p id="e3ae866324c34403913bc9516006bcfd">Every business makes sure the software development life cycle is maintained to start the project because it is very crucial. Each of the tasks can be assigned to certain team members, and deliverables falling under each task could be documented along with the deliverable dates. This module has introduced you to an efficient software development life cycle - Agile Scrum, with components  below:</p><ul id="b81ed4a3e4074e9db362ae7d7dd105cb"><li><p id="ebcf2f2936ab482ca4842a39f89f71c5"><em>User stories:</em> A high-level definition of a work request.</p></li><li><p id="e83a092a5611459bb901a409e26bf943"><em>Sprints:</em> Short spans of work where teams work on tasks determined in the sprint planning meeting. Once the sprint is over, you review the product, see what is and isn\xe2\x80\x99t working, make adjustments, and begin another sprint to improve the product or service.</p></li><li><p id="ca736599797543d9948561d1a926d443"><em>Stand-up meetings:</em>  These are daily stand-up meetings where participants are required to stay standing, helping to keep the meetings short and to the point.</p></li><li><p id="eb18f11f31cb4d19b716b5d3b5c0af6d"><em>Agile board:</em> This is a tracking system that helps your team track the progress of your project.</p></li><li><p id="ae4d5ef4964144398497ac67d1a0e3c7"><em>Backlog:</em> This is the set of outstanding project requests that are added through your intake system. Managing your backlog is a vital role for project managers in an Agile environment.</p></li><li><p id="eb1895bc160b48e6b547434cab5a889e"><em>Sprint retrospective:</em> This is a meeting where the team gathers to discuss what went well and what didn&apos;t.</p></li><li><p id="e267fd609f0e445290674ec34342f386"><em>Demonstration:</em> This is when the team demonstrates a working product to the stakeholder.</p></li></ul></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'