b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ca5be992fa6b4b88a378dc48c8759002"><head><title>Where do data come from?</title></head><body><p id="ebcfe49451a74cf79aaf95523e70f2b6">Data collection is the process of gathering and organizing data that can meet defined business and analytic objectives. The data collection process in the data science lifecycle can be compared to the data collection process in scholarly research. Data collection should be conducted systematically to ensure that the data are valid and reliable. Data collection also involves attending to issues of <em style="italic">validity</em>, <em style="italic">reliability</em>, and <em style="italic">ethics</em>, such as provisions for <em style="italic">informed consent</em> from participants. We will explore these issues in upcoming modules.</p><p id="ea29c66deb5b4a4782e37a76260519c4">As a professional who works with data, it is important to know where data come from and think about the analytical approaches that one will take to analyze data. Before going further into data analysis, we want to understand where the data that are provided to us come from or what approaches have been used to gather data for the study. We need to ask these questions to guide us in thinking about what process generated the data and the type of data that we may be working with or collecting. In general, there are two key types of data:</p><ul id="cd5e661b86264af799789be83baf79db"><li><p id="c8c2ad334e3745c4ba133860c0cc1434">Organic or process data</p></li><li><p id="ff1ac085f8694b348d5f544ab8fd8ec4">Data collected from a designed study</p></li></ul><p id="a85c4d3e65dd480c86fe81dfefdd74fa"><em>Organic or process data</em> are data that are generated by an automated computerized information system or extracted from images, video, or audio recordings. This type of data is generated organically as a result of some process continuously or over a period of time.</p><p id="e1624be370ea493d929f94d9559a4452">Examples of organic or process data:</p><ul id="fc251e28fc424531ab863ecb0798da26"><li><p id="b714621ffd64413cbffad2d4cf73aefd">Financial or stock market exchange transactions</p></li><li><p id="f3d104631ac9422d95944ec40c087c4f">Web browser history</p></li><li><p id="d423bcc89fd740f1b489ad6571de6fa0">Web or mobile application activity history</p></li><li><p id="d7fa7baecb384faeb00deb4174744a67">Netflix viewing history</p></li><li><p id="a31be969e7784381ac68d356a3edc148">Surveillance camera video recordings</p></li></ul><p id="ab3565fc46de496499173f0d7b510a11">The term \xe2\x80\x9cbig data\xe2\x80\x9d refers to these types of datasets comprising organically produced data from automated processes over time in massive quantities. . Data scientists mine these data to study trends and discover interesting relationships. But processing such massive quantities requires significant computational resources.  Thus compiling and processing such massive quantities of data efficiently and getting them ready for analysis are exciting research and practice areas in and of itself.</p><p id="afb3545e6a424ad5be7abb914a9ab8cf"><em>Data collected from a designed study</em>\xe2\x80\x93 as the name suggests\xe2\x80\x93 derives data from specific studies designed to address particular research topics. The main difference between this type of data and organic data is that data collected from a designed study are collected based on a certain guided agenda by theory, prior knowledge, literature, etc., in order to test particular hypotheses or to attempt to answer predetermined research questions.</p><p id="b261e58391af436c9381d5669b322cbe">Here are examples of data that can be collected from a designed study:</p><ul id="b002b50df35f418a86e9892a4f06211a"><li><p id="f7990db2794f4decac2788428182b533"><em>Questionnaires and surveys.</em> Questionnaires are used to collect data from a group of individuals. Questionnaires can be administered on paper or online. In general, it might be easier to distribute questionnaires online as there are efficient tools that can analyze the collected data. Questionnaires can have open-ended, closed-ended, rating, Likert-scale, or multiple-choice questions. Data cleaning is still a consideration with questionnaire data as errors can occur. For example, responses to open-ended questions can contain misspellings, among other errors.</p></li><li><p id="ebf88d499fdd42bab31f820b21cba640"><em>Interviews.</em> Interviews are open-ended question-answering dialogs between an interviewer and one or more interviewees. Interviews are guided by an interview protocol designed to provide instructions for the interview process, the questions to be asked, and the space to take notes during the interview.</p></li><li><p id="caa48272b7424ac2af3a290b67936b22"><em>Observation</em> is the process of gathering open-ended, firsthand information by observing people and places at a research site. Data collected during these observations can support or complement the data collected during interviews and from questionnaires.</p></li><li><p id="cb8693ef8f12420582696196945f5bc3"><em>Focus groups</em> can be used to collect shared understanding from several individuals as well as to get views from specific people. A focus group interview is a process of collecting data through interviews with a group of people, typically four to six. The researcher asks a small number of general questions and elicits responses from all individuals in the group. Focus groups are advantageous when the interaction among interviewees will likely yield the best information and when interviewees are similar to and cooperative with each other.</p></li></ul><p id="ea6670ad9155459cbffb74421da518d5">As you may have noticed from the provided examples, this type of data arises from a design data collection rather than organically from an automated process. So instead of knowing what a user\xe2\x80\x99s Netflix viewing habits are over time, we might want to ask a group of individuals that are sampled from all the Netflix viewers and then interview or survey them about their opinions on a particular topic such as a new pilot feature or a newly added movie.</p><image id="a61edfd384b946728b802e523718c70b" src="../webcontent/image-ca5be992fa6b4b88a378dc48c8759002-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="340" width="650"><caption><p id="d0a5238676b74f05a3d3dd8d26bfe6b0">Figure 1: Drawing a representative sample from the population. (Source: <link href="https://www.voxco.com/blog/population-of-interest/" target="new" internal="false">https://www.voxco.com/</link>)</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="adb3ba568c8e4091b9f8905a52685276">In figure 1, we have a population of interest but we draw a representative sample of individuals from that population because it is usually difficult to measure everyone from that targeted population. There is another way to leverage process data in a designed study: we specifically design a way to extract a subset of the massive quantity of process data collected that can serve the purpose of the study design and research objectives.</p><p id="b98527f50fff4e7393a715a17699f7df">You can appreciate the key differences in the data collected through a designed study. Such data are very rigorously designed data collections that people might be interested in looking at, as opposed to just large data sets that arise organically.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'