b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="d01319063f22438e9dcc5d684f637143"><head><title>111-Introduction to Natural Language Processing</title></head><body><section id="b97f067556624e1ca18726f31c6a5c9a"><title>Introduction to Natural Language Processing</title><body><p id="ad50bc35f5ed4ff2a64b699446b9b899"> </p></body></section><p id="d3f9414a3a144b15b7af2bcba7ee2106">Natural Language Processing (NLP hereafter) is a subfield of computer science aiming to  build  systems that:</p><ul id="c4781152b6af46e198354ef522081db2"><li><p id="e4b30ec7967e401d9523c61c2dff3cdf">Enable human-computer communication</p></li><li><p id="b1577d29500547928c64be52badb8157">Enable/enrich human-human communication</p></li><li><p id="d53fb1427a6242dc9a68ed83cabed40e">Perform tasks requiring the use of human language faculty, more efficiently and more correctly.</p></li></ul><p id="e2b703ec9f8345d5ad7dbfca83b8c2ad">Here are some applications of NLP in these three areas:</p><ul id="ad054b6b1097435f8a5e59a5b34e7089"><li><p id="bdf705ff42264367a2c70fd2716eafd4">Human-computer communication</p></li><li><ul id="e09686a79b9f49b8a48784255615940c"><li><p id="ce8b617791f3400a943a0653a1c7561e">Dictating email messages</p></li><li><p id="b7fb7b31f7d24124a2b8c4751442ee31">Listening to email messages</p></li><li><ul id="f4e2567274b94e76a9b1e7835812bc91"><li><p id="a6bf1fb187ab4caea54a980af879cb2e">With proper pronunciation, tone, and stress!</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="b5993770901b4f49be1a32807033c828">Using human language to give commands to the operating system</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="f7efddda621d4be3a91301d011e673e7">Human-human communication</p></li><li><ul id="a1e8c97c5b2c4c678f6c975e58a2a4ed"><li><p id="d57d07ca313e4b08821ea5fda0bab8cb">Real-time text and speech translation</p></li><li><p id="f1da5d3a74d84dd798716efbe78245d3">Summarizing meeting conversations</p></li><li><p id="d0e32fa4c59445248689bf129ace66ce">Enabling communication with people with hearing/vision impairments</p></li></ul></li><li><p id="e5f26fbf7e324f3fbbc9871bbe7b6898">Improving the efficiency of tasks requiring human language faculty </p></li><li><ul id="fb29eb5603cc4fa883a95aaea7b75664"><li><p id="f2fc4bdbbb304da6bea18c067076d2c6">Correcting typing/grammatical errors</p></li><li><p id="f9f5d0b317bd44c58be0dd85d160e8ad">Question answering</p></li><li><p id="c861ad69e7744dca8e5728ce656fd34a">Answering e-mails automatically</p></li><li><p id="ecef1a75ebfb4ada8aec9320173654f2">Searching large document databases</p></li></ul></li></ul><p id="fcd1f4e46ed94dc69a69c94fbf0f52e9" /><p id="ff8c406f976b47d4881688b40d1a53d9">Here are some (and definitely not a comprehensive set of) applications of  NLP in a diverse set of areas: </p><ul id="bf909027a95a4620921da7cdc8adcc90"><li><p id="fda8fb6b99364584a838439553691eb7">Information extraction (IE), especially \xe2\x80\x9copen\xe2\x80\x9d IE:  Given a text (or a collection of texts), find out <em style="italic">who</em> did <em style="italic">what</em> to <em style="italic">whom</em>, <em style="italic">where</em>, <em style="italic">when</em>, <em style="italic">how</em>, <em style="italic">why</em>, <em style="italic">with what</em>, <em style="italic">in exchange for what</em>,  etc.</p></li><li><p id="feb3bf7f4a65415381a057206dcd1374">Document classification: Classifying a document into topic areas (e.g., news, sports, business, entertainment, sports, etc.), classiying an email as spam or not or as important or not</p></li><li><p id="dcd20b378bd643a997f384dfd096cd17">Question answering beyond finding the documents relevant to the question and instead delivering the actual answer.</p></li><li><p id="c035b96c2b1f4095baf78e3262b28071">Conversational Agents (e.g., Siri, Alexa, Google Assistant): Holding a typically multi-stage turn-taking goal-driven conversation with a user, going beyond question answering and helping other tasks such as making appointments, helping with shopping or entertainment options, etc.</p></li><li><p id="e2b74bd512a04033be10b6a1a95ec697">Image (and eventually video) understanding:  Expressing the pictorial or video content in human language (e.g., image captioning or verbalizing a football match action in a TV program setting), </p></li><li><p id="dcf8df420edb4cc88016286e8fac5dce">Text (including text on images) and speech translation with additional applications in video call transcription and translation, real-time lecture translation, generating speech output in the right accent and the right lip rendering for much more natural looking video generation.</p></li><li><p id="f1ff06b756154b8d87de1c14db38a9c5">Sign-language translation, and scene-to-speech for the visually impaired (which would be akin to video understanding above)</p></li><li><p id="e1f58bb4e32642f8b44847d00795391a">Summarization:  Generating a short summary of the salient points of a document or a set of documents.</p></li><li><p id="c20c108013834a6cbdd3a971108cd7ee">Opinion and sentiment analysis:  Extracting political or personal sentiments from news pieces, tweets, product or movie reviews.</p></li><li><p id="f671e7e2a2a74c508a62807d3f981d70">Essay evaluation: Evaluating an essay (say in an SAT exam setting) for proper structure, sentence, and vocabulary use.</p></li><li><p id="a34a581fb0d34e39b483c05548763f1b">Fake news or fake review detection:  Automatic fact-checking of news especially in real-time viral settings on social media; verifying that product, restaurant, or movie reviews in online shopping or recommendation settings are genuine and not generated by bots, etc.</p></li></ul><p id="fd062dc620d34926bf6f2e13e5f09257" /><p id="c56e59d5ebe5498d99909d64fe243e40"><em>Bird\xe2\x80\x99s Eye View of NLP</em></p><p id="ba8e1e13c870417aae5b74019e4d9bfe">The following figures give a bird\xe2\x80\x99s eye view of NLP and various functions or tasks that partake in building and evaluating NLP applications.</p><p id="b4d6120ff6f6479db2356f04c0499fcd" /><image id="a4f6370f1c2445d48f0e8bcfbcd15b7a" src="../webcontent/image-d01319063f22438e9dcc5d684f637143-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="324" width="459"><caption><p id="a48acc902912489284ed98cbdf49cc1c" /></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="c72501d121634c34ab5c34a174240877">From Eduard Hovy\xe2\x80\x99s \xe2\x80\x9cThe Past and 3\xc2\xbd Futures of NLP\xe2\x80\x9d presentation</p><section id="a72207244d5348eeb487bca4447b8efc"><title>Fundamental functions in NLP</title><body><p id="d6ed1e8e637b402aa82373c78afdb70e"> </p></body></section><p id="b446a4b740984b618b538c840b4378ac">There are three high-level functions that NLP tries to to automate:</p><p id="e2734395db264c5ebb74b79f773f4412" /><ol id="f3402247931d446aa3aeb080a55bd9e7"><li><p id="b4cb301c8c44410695071805e3d9c9ca"><em>Analysis</em> (or \xe2\x80\x9cunderstanding\xe2\x80\x9d or \xe2\x80\x9cprocessing\xe2\x80\x9d \xe2\x80\xa6) where the  input is language (text or speech) , output is some <em style="italic">representation</em> that supports useful action (e.g., translation, or robot movements) in response.</p></li><li><p id="bd4a431d22c24143babb436351c9611b"><em>Generation</em>:  input is a representation of an utterance and possibly a representation of the context and  the  output is text or speech that captures the semantics and the intent encoded in the input representation (e.g., generating the target language sentence in machine translation)</p></li><li><p id="bd6136b5963a4797b87d6e4fbb3ed5f4"><em>Acquisition</em>:  obtaining the representation and necessary algorithms  from  data (e.g., learning to translate from aligned translated sentences)</p></li></ol><p id="b52b500149bb42eca2834f43d99d0143" /><p id="e714aacf537446e29fbfdf1f04a77f4c">The representation that these employ depend on the actual task being solved:  they can be explicit such as morphological analyses of words,  syntax trees or part-of-speech symbol sequence of sentence which capture the linguistic structure of words or sentence.  They can also be very opaque like sentence embeddings that a a neural machine translation system computes as it analyzes an input sentence.</p><p id="e814aa421951454daa3c8010bfb48fa1" /><section id="ada07c9d8566499e8ed8f799d46e23d7"><title>Relation to other fields</title><body><p id="bdfc5c810f704f1fb3fd6b830ef9b6bb"> </p></body></section><p id="acc87aa621e4444c90f159d313ed4749">NLP is closely related to the following areas of computer science and other fields Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Artificial Intelligence Statistical modeling, Information Theory, Human-computer interaction, Software Engineering, Linguistics,  Ethics, Cognitive Science, Logic, Social sciences, political science, and psychology.</p><p id="b4cb01ca8e024ee78f5e63458c9fbe18" /><p id="af0a7055601f49b8acbd4c03bd25ef53">Currently almost all functions of implemented in NLP applications make heavy use machine learning, especially deep learning, involving transformers, large scale neural language models and the like.  These all necessitate large-scale data sources such as annotated and unannotated text, speech corpora and large scale computing resourses to train.</p><p id="b158bb3bc6c74d85928b142a1067cce4" /><p id="a975f138db2d4c3b93e811c417f0c713" /><p id="b3115274bddc47e2a8ad6088fd9f49ee" /><p id="e00ced06865f42cd8d36ee3de1ce3646">\xe2\x80\x94-------------------------------------------------------------------</p><p id="d6a09502863d40e1b6428bb0f46f040b" /><p id="fde712927f414b6e86e3ed004d632bdd">OLD STUFF</p><p id="a55d5a9aca0f4991ad8c5c2c5477f5b4">Natural Language Processing (hereby referred to as NLP) is a field that deals with the interaction between natural human-spoken languages and computers. It builds on techniques and insights from several different disciplines, principally theoretical linguistics and computer science but with some input from mathematical logic and psychology.</p><image id="fed2b07a3738498c8bf5dd4bb424d12c" src="../webcontent/image-d01319063f22438e9dcc5d684f637143-2.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="401" width="351"><caption><p id="fa57ad03b8c84492bfe1500c06dd8536" /></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="dcb39d573fa74f31ad6eadf15bb488ba">Figure 1. What is Natural Language Processing?</p><p id="bdeb8755896e46ab8cc0bffa109fe14c">In the context of Data Science, NLP builds primarily on Information Theory and Computational Linguistics. Information theory is concerned with the measurement, storage, and transmission of information. In NLP, it helps capture the statistical properties of text. It encompasses unsupervised methods like topic modeling or clustering as they are faster, cheaper, and more generalizable. Computational linguistics is concerned with understanding written and spoken language from a computational perspective, and building artifacts that usefully process and produce language, either in bulk or in a dialogue setting. It suggests certain supervised labelings and/or data structures motivated by formal models of language (often involving complicated representations). We use linguistic representations when information theory doesn\xe2\x80\x99t provide features that are discriminative enough for the solution. For instance: The usage of part-of-speech labels to disambiguate a word in a sentence.</p><p id="d84cbb5d6f784018a2381e686352513d">In the past few decades, natural language processing has become embedded in our daily lives: automatic machine translation is ubiquitous on the web and in social media; text classification keeps our email inboxes from collapsing under a deluge of spam; search engines have moved beyond string matching and network analysis to a high degree of linguistic sophistication; dialog systems provide an increasingly common and effective way to get and share information.</p><p id="cc14e237c8e44dd393cff0ec01246ed7" /></body></workbook_page>\n'