b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="d45a40acd14849788466c1143a044ad5"><head><title>Module 8 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="e9e1fa9cb50a4a1987fbaf5ece9de64d"><li><p id="a101d0ae368b40bbb9b2b49295670983">Data scientists have virtually unlimited access to data and analytical techniques with which to analyze that data. As data scientists, we should be thinking about whether we should do something just because it is technically possible. </p></li><li><p id="cdb952e2525347049595766a37fdd106">Informed consent is based on the Fair Information Practice Principles (FIPPs) as part of the Privacy Act created in 1974. Informed consent states that when a study is being done on a human subject, this individual must be informed about the experiment, must consent to the experiment voluntarily without any coercion, and must have the right to withdraw consent at any time.</p></li><li><p id="cd7f5f6d5f3e4011bbca48bb464668d3">Data governance defines how data is accessed and managed within an organization. It is beneficial because it provides a reliable and consistent view of enterprise-wide data. It ensures that there is a plan for improved quality of data, reduces the scourge of data silos, and improves data management overall.</p></li><li><p id="c8e3059563fd4333a2c382dc81a1d9ce">Accountability is about all the little decisions made by a group of people who created a system at each step of the way. There is both ex-ante and post hoc accountability, sometimes called anticipatory versus remedial. We need to think about accountability before something goes wrong - to design a system for someone whom <em>we are responsible for</em>.</p></li><li><p id="cc09320b7d2a4799905ef50b0553a3b6">Data scientists try their best to make predictions about the future based on the information in the present. In an important sense, all of a data scientist&apos;s work is bound up with information about the past. Data science involves making predictions and classifications and separating one group from another. The prevalence of different subgroups in the data will directly impact how much each of those groups affects the final result. As a data scientist, it is important to watch out for this bias toward what is most prevalent or most &quot;normal&quot; about a given dataset.</p></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'