b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="d746710bc6284e18acd95e112c8252f9"><head><title>Step 5b: Framing Common Forms of Analytical Objectives</title><objref idref="c652b19601414ebebcfaed9f52cd17e0" /></head><body><p id="c6fd34a8c6dd4c028931f7dea953f52d">Now that you have studied the elements of a properly framed analytical objective, we shift towards explaining three basic archetypes of hypotheses that will cover a fair amount of projects one encounters in data science. They are provided here as purely illustrative example instances of the general template on which you can base your own formulations.\r</p><p id="ae436f1ba98e4eba82dfb852d085acc7">Not all framings of analytic objectives will include every individual element, as some of them may not be necessary depending on the situation. In industry settings, the problem and task may be merged, and the added valuable functionality may be evident from a model that performs its function well. In academic settings, the overarching interest may be that of advancing state of the art in research, and hence the statement may either not include an explicit business objective or state it as a problem solution vision.\r</p><p id="b69dca72ca1f43d1988c2b76bc12e13f"><em>Constructive</em></p><p id="adb4b48d4c41404b87afa7bd9051e343">A constructive analytical objective states that it is, in principle, possible to develop a desired functionality from the available methods and data without the need to fully optimize its performance yet. One can think of it as a proof-of-concept or prototyping endeavor.\r</p><example id="ec41bf6c23094a939b0a73e25a937d1d"><title>Industry Constructive Objective</title><ul id="a34f0bd8a7cd458dbedfbcc11af4b607"><li><p id="b55c66a192b84a7a9e132afb062a0c5d">In order to increase sales from the company\xe2\x80\x99s online store\r (<em style="italic">Business objective</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="fa58ec2d5854460ca0e19bbb2d4f4f81">...we work towards increasing the click-through rate of its advertising through targeted content\r (<em style="italic">Problem</em>)</p></li><li><p id="d1f2eb027a6e494a93e933d0577fd216">...by classifying website visitors into youth, middle-age, and senior demographics (<em style="italic">Task</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="e8d71e39f8c948e4ae72be17c26e7814">...using supervised learning models on curated internal datasets\r (<em style="italic">Method</em>)\r</p></li></ul></example><example id="ab8607f6c0f94602be7e3115a70a3ab0"><title>Research constructive objective:\r</title><ul id="e38535de85c74d87af9a80261756af96"><li><p id="c37e3047d66b4078bb04efa8ddf8fd13">(Business objective omitted due to project being primarily research)\r</p></li><li><p id="d2b1cfc5aa8943078241eb2099e0364a">In order to enable more effective search of audio collections\r (<em style="italic">Problem</em>)</p></li><li><p id="cceb975f52774c87b3f44171ebd6ae93">We demonstrate the feasibility of a system that retrieves audio pieces from short natural language descriptions of their sounds\r (<em style="italic">Task</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="b284548c33ef473abc529ee35bd0c1fb">using neural models on a dataset of short clips of classical music and their descriptions\r (<em style="italic">Method</em>)</p></li><li><p id="c4052a38200445e7ba998d8c5535a8e2">towards developing suitable multi-modal audio-textual encoding\r (<em style="italic">valuable functionality</em>)</p></li></ul><p id="d81b0ef8c67f4364aa257b6bb59c1069"><em>Benchmarking</em></p><p id="b6ef512589d44f11a903f636751e435c">In scenarios where the feasibility of an analytical task has been established, projects may be targeted toward improvement over the state-of-the-art in some performance metrics by using innovative methods/features/data. This is typically the case if one works on leaderboard-type datasets where there are models.\r</p></example><example id="c6f1528d7a78470bba64e23294e70349"><title>\rIndustry Benchmarking Objective</title><ul id="e3e27be7c68e4ecf94a7124c8049c085"><li><p id="f2ac76a6fa77405faee89a36a5df2841">The client is a logistics company that wants to speed up its automatic package sorting\r (<em style="italic">Business objective</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="db95c92c18b1403e8a0f99023b9f1789">We focus on the problem of handwritten address recognition from shipping label scans \r(<em style="italic">Problem and Task</em>) </p></li><li><p id="ede3750e238e4754b30b213d269165a4">We want to combine neural image recognition with language models on company-internal data\r (<em style="italic">Method and Data</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="f7308189dbc84fa593f44351fb0a4324">To improve performance beyond the current model based on standard convolutional neural networks without language information\r (<em style="italic">Valuable functionality</em>)</p></li></ul></example><example id="bd19acaaad944ea7884f4eeff6bd86df"><title>Research Bench-marking Objective</title><ul id="ef2fb513c56c4e35ac3aaf00e14c9516"><li><p id="ca7acf951f434454bc93eba7a596a7ac">(Business objective omitted due to project being primarily research)\r</p></li><li><p id="f7af56ad2bcd46c68b618cba5db633d7">For the task of span-based question answering from text\r (<em style="italic">problem and task</em> merged because span-based question answering is a common leaderboard task) \r</p></li><li><p id="f1c8ad5f748340e8a604bab83f88431f">We want to combine graph-based knowledge bases with neural attention models\r (<em style="italic">Method</em>)</p></li><li><p id="d9043e103a184729ae0441315f4c7501">To improve over state of the art performance on realistic news text\r (v<em style="italic">aluable functionality and data</em>)\r</p></li></ul></example><p id="e2a730c8c3c743f4b11b324b558728e4"><em>Exploratory\r</em></p><p id="f6e8e189ab894d25bf0b8b6c966dc26e">Exploratory objectives are typically formed when data is available that is related to a problem of interest but needs to be surveyed before it can be used in projects pursuing constructive or benchmarking objectives.\r</p><example id="be5db4ae3bb74defae4c2b56967a5670"><title>Industry Exploratory Objective\r</title><ul id="e467fee0ab96446ba6d7095ed677f361"><li><p id="c783bc8a12424f2faa2394b988819338">The client runs a complex semi-automatic manufacturing pipeline and wants to make it more efficient\r (<em style="italic">Business objective</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="e39ef35ffdd442d6a8936a7b183c3ea7">Specifically, he would like to see whether some parts of the process statistically interdepend so that bottlenecks and critical components can be identified\r (<em style="italic">Problem and Task</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="b34fcf2d68864e5186c4ad2af1dda3ec">We want to conduct a qualitative survey and basic statistical analysis on a dataset of production machinery sensor readings provided by the client \r(<em style="italic">Methods and Data</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="b3db790fda154077bc89464c0f993d06">Towards identifying correlating events across the production process that can be used for process optimization\r.</p></li></ul></example><example id="f2b2fec38b824ef781a1e447792292bc"><title>Research Exploratory Objective</title><ul id="ff7fe0f5d9624ac4a57f9f2c95540c9f"><li><p id="a36f80c12b924534bebddb64424046c0">(Business objective omitted due to project being primarily research)\r</p></li><li><p id="ec2444dc7ba248c7979b4cd4f464b249">The development of AI dialogue systems suffers from a lack of clear training signal of how satisfied the user is with the chat bot\xe2\x80\x99s replies\r (<em style="italic">Problem</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="e4228472596b49ed8988491a4b81da34">We want to conduct a sparse labeling of conversation quality and produce basic topic models for a dataset of chat protocols\r (<em style="italic">Methods and Data</em>)\r</p></li><li><p id="bc2c8e7d3658404aa7d77b43b6fd17ca">In order to develop a per-topic quality scoring rubric for the eventual annotation of a larger dataset. \r(<em style="italic">Task/Valuable Insight</em>)\r</p></li></ul></example><wb:inline idref="newfccb38c8c8c34354a043bf87ab97ff98" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'