b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="dee5ac8bd6ce4339a686c56ca2f4a871"><head><title>Module 1 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="f163c5a1f706478ba282922e02b00566"><li><p id="c7e7e61e013848718e7b0860dd40b5a0">A data science project does not begin with building models; one must consider the needs of the client and set objectives to meet those needs. A data scientist must approach a project with a methodology. Similar to scientific research, a data science project follows frameworks that will guide the problem identification process. A data science team will work with a client to understand the business need(s). Those needs will are then translated to data science tasks.</p></li><li><p id="c46badd874fd4b16ad2dd7d712f5a408">Business objectives will be defined by the company to help meet business needs. These objectives are stated fairly concretely and often have time periods associated with them, after which they will be considered reached (in case of success), not reached (in case of failure). Given a business\xe2\x80\x99s needs and objectives, one can now evaluate whether data science methods can be used to facilitate the company&apos;s efforts to meet them.</p></li><li><p id="be2a23b5a09d43509be33b24a1019983">A data science team will engage with the client to understand the situation in sufficient depth and establish effective communication with the company\xe2\x80\x99s domain experts. Once the team has familiarized themselves with the problem as well as the available data and resources, they will work with the client to develop a solution vision. Finally, the data science team will identify a set of analytic objectives that, if achieved, will facilitate realizing the solution and reaching the business goal. </p></li><li><p id="c77b6b4bfbc1438d970313939efa3784">This module introduced you to the Evidence Value Proposition framework (EVP). The EVP is a suitable framework that can be used to ensure that defined business objectives are met and has been developed to help determine the desired analytic objectives and provide evidence that the objectives can be met with the appropriate data and technology.</p></li><li><p id="bb493dcd8e2e42feb55445b1420e416a">When engaging with potential clients seeking analytical solutions, it is important to assess the organization\xe2\x80\x99s readiness.</p></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'