b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="df1f84f174834537937e6b696f3dbc71"><head><title>Applications of Natural Language Processing</title><objref idref="d4b57b57c3e64624b297ab84a405cfff" /></head><body><p id="d9efa72a63e145fa9d94c7f059edfb4c"><link href="https://www.ibm.com/watson/natural-language-processing" target="new" internal="false">Natural language processing</link> has numerous practical applications within today\xe2\x80\x99s world, such as question-answering systems or language translators. Here are a few of the more well-known applications:</p><p id="c36f4bd5dd8044048737a35f246f83dc"><em>1. Sentiment Analysis</em></p><p id="e861521367b9475cbf921ea3d79fe256">As the name suggests, sentiment analysis is used to identify the sentiments in a fragment of a natural language text. Expressions like sarcasm, threat, exclamation, etc., are often very hard to be recognized by the computer. A use case of sentiment analysis is companies identify the opinion and sentiments of their customers based on online reviews and feedback.</p><p id="dac9d747010742498b58dcf9b07ba828"><em>2. Information Extraction</em></p><p id="b3827bd36b104986bbcb926bf722bd57">Information Extraction is the task of extracting pre-specified types of facts from written texts or speech transcripts and converting them into structured representations (e.g., databases). An example is when your email extracts only the relevant data of a meeting invite for you to add to your Calendar.</p><p id="e327abb0eb1a4e19a7c491e983145a3b"><em>3. Machine Translation</em></p><p id="fc34a77837c44a138f22f4031a7bc674">Machine Translation is the procedure of automatically converting the text from one language to another language while keeping the meaning intact. In earlier days, machine translation systems were dictionary- and rule-based systems, and they saw very limited success. However, starting in mid 199o\xe2\x80\x99s first due to statistical models based on large parallel corpora and then to deep neural networks coupled with special processing hardware such as GPUs and TPU (Tensor Processing Units), machine translation has become fairly accurate in converting text from one language to another. I</p><p id="a239c1dbddfe4e309639da8d5119976d"><em>4. Natural Language Generation</em></p><p id="d78959bf04414035a48e25be62441f60">Natural language generation (NLG) is the process of producing a human language text response based on some data input. This text can also be converted into a speech format through text-to-speech services. NLG also encompasses text summarization capabilities that generate summaries from one or more documents while maintaining the integrity of the information. Natural language generation systems have evolved over time from static text generation with the application of hidden Markov chains, recurrent neural networks, and transformers to enable more dynamic text generation in real time.</p><p id="bf8ce4b32f2b44af8bb194fb4cc252e1"><em>5. Topic Modeling</em></p><p id="fd2b9750dad3495da5e485d533aea8ca">Topic modeling refers to the task of identifying topics that best describe a set of documents. These topics are not predefined and will only emerge during the topic modeling process, which makes it an unsupervised approach. We will delve into the implementation of one of the popular topic modeling techniques known as Latent Dirichlet Allocation (LDA) in Project 5.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'