b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e1242c23f38a4bc28f78be470b6ca11a"><head><title>Study Design</title></head><body><p id="aa68640490764bc1995a17c502bde4b7">To connect the study\xe2\x80\x99s objectives with the data gathered, data scientists need to come up with a sound study design for execution while ensuring the <em>validity</em> and <em>integrity</em> of the inference. There is a range of study design options, from the exploratory analysis of data that is organically available, to those very highly planned efforts for collecting and analyzing data aligned to a specific question. Study design encompasses everything in preparation for data-driven research. A study can fall into multiple categories of study designs.</p><table id="ea65057f5f31473e907d94f189c3b657" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="iac20302137374eabab11272277498f4e" /><caption><p id="f74d9b6d53cc4f0f8bee6eee3decb437" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="bc760cf6086f4e1f84376dd130159a8e">Exploratory</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b3a57bea840141aa875a37e92346fff1">Confirmatory</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e2886ac439884740b0cb45867edb6f86">Bottom-up (without a pre-specified question)</p><p id="fac2898311cb4ac199807363ec9abd73">Can lead to knowledge discovery or new theory</p><p id="da8979131a4f4cf8995ee25d98a6eafd">Uses inductive logic and the logic of discovery</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e618ab993fb74f1590d195d5176c6857">Top-down (with a specified falsifiable hypothesis)</p><p id="f425eadd0e5940939b2be683fa361c2f">Tests an existing theory</p><p id="b80ad70792444704804cb82dcd604354">Use deductive logic, the logic of justification, and reconstructed logic</p></td></tr></table><table id="d8b5a7aaa32c4cc19642e493617cb75b" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i0d4c8cd945f844c788ce963c857019c0" /><caption><p id="fb7b19e0b32b403aa981dac072c8f412" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e13a68f84e5943b89234497dc3130fc2">Comparative</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b1734793a694491593b273be035fb1fa">Non-Comparative</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ed6f738518cb4a4e81cb4a43fb45c790">Contrasts one subject with another based on certain measures.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b17273d6ea8d4dbda20d26947621bdd4">Estimates or predicts absolute outcomes of the certain subject matter without explicitly making a comparison with its counterpart.</p></td></tr></table><table id="d41aaaca2c79407c9b30f091dac3f63e" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="i8ea6a87e5c6a4e648d9e11cf46c73bc8" /><caption><p id="dfecf48a9be3406f9261054dfbd3185f" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="f025b87804724fffaf13aa0b7a9115f3">Experimental</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="ecaa7be03ed049f8a4c9e4ecbc02c9c8">Observational</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e1750ff7305a4baba8b9bb6c72bcad30">The purpose of experiments is to compare responses of subjects to some outcome measures, under different conditions. Those conditions are levels of a variable that can influence the outcomes. The data scientist has the experimental control of being able to assign subjects to the conditions.</p><p id="eb692dc743c64d6d800b9c5f3123ecf5">To conduct experiments, there is often a plan of manipulation or assignment of the subjects to treatment. These are called experimental designs.</p><p id="f44a3d8df16d45cdbade08c7839a6d85">Good experimental designs use randomization to determine which treatment a subject receives.</p></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="e577a74085de43e393ceaab32d876e0d">The purpose of observational studies is to draw inferences about the effect of an \xe2\x80\x9cexposure\xe2\x80\x9d or intervention on subjects, where the assignment of subjects to groups is observed rather than manipulated (e.g., through randomization) by the data scientist.</p><p id="b325a6d8eb944240987832b22d5c04a0">Observational research involves the direct observation of individuals in their natural settings. As such, who does or does not receive intervention is determined by individual preferences, practice patterns, or policy decisions.</p><p id="dc58c08bb26b4e24a7dc7987b8b5c2c7">It is therefore important for readers of observational research to consider if alternative explanations for study results exist.</p></td></tr></table><p id="ce7d2dad9ea5416fa3eeabc3068cc4fd">Establishing causal inference is central to science. However, it is not possible to establish cause and effect relationships <em>definitively</em> with a nonexperimental study, whether it be an observational study with an available sample or a sample survey using random sampling. With an observational study, there is a strong possibility that the sample is not representative of the population. With an observational study or a survey, there is always the possibility that some unmeasured variable could be responsible for patterns observed in the data. With a well-designed experiment that randomly assigns subjects to treatments, those treatments should roughly balance any unmeasured variables. Because a randomized experiment balances the groups being compared on other factors, it is possible to study causal inference more accurately with an experiment than with an observational study. Observational studies are more passive and self-selected as subjects are exposed to a condition rather than being assigned. However, when the random assignment in experimental design is <em>impractical</em> or <em>unethical</em>, observational studies are the next best bet.</p><p id="f0d12f48fffc44e8bddd77c7e0f7a094">In general, more data is better because more data yields more information. However, the manner in which data is collected is arguably more important than the availability of that data itself. If the data that is being collected has too little information to inform about the questions of interest, then the resulting conclusions may not be very informative. <em style="italic">Power analysis </em>is a process by which we can assess whether a given study design is likely to yield meaningful findings. <em style="italic">Bias</em> is another issue that can result from an unfair sampling of a population, or when measurements are systematically inaccurate on average. In the next section, we will address the issue of bias and validity of a study. </p></body></workbook_page>\n'