b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e260bc12b0e940a2a88262a8aec11970"><head><title>Step 1: Actually Understanding the Business Objective </title><objref idref="c652b19601414ebebcfaed9f52cd17e0" /></head><body><p id="e1b3ad60ff8d446abbcdcfcaa752ac10">The ability to study and understand a project\xe2\x80\x99s business objective in sufficient depth in order to maximize the benefit from leveraging data is a critical skill for data scientists. This skill can be thought of as having three aspects: </p><ol id="c5f5680402cd44a892ccdc95c32e3799"><li><p id="dfbab93a7d264ec7bdb74cd210f0c5ec">Engagement with the client and research about the <em>specific circumstances</em> of the client\xe2\x80\x99s business. </p><p id="b0412770993f4be49e11e88f8f32ea73">First, one engages with the client by learning about their business or organization, its customers/clients, the market and its competitors, and the general state of the art in achieving business objectives of its kind. Often this may involve a workshop-like event between the business unit and the data science team, which may lead to a regular communication schedule (e.g., calls, in-person meetings, reports). </p></li><li><p id="bae649ef1dbe4e12a3404c08875868a8">Engagement with the client and research around the <em>general domain</em> in which the client\xe2\x80\x99s business operates .</p><p id="b78cc330021140ff9bc1bb27ee34fd97">Second, preparation will often require additional research around the client\xe2\x80\x99s general domain and market using the internet, but also from subject area books and academic publications. A data scientist does not need to become an expert herself in the respective area or market, but she should be convinced that the domain is sufficiently understood and that she can intuitively explain why and how the business wants to reach the objective, as well as engage with the client\xe2\x80\x99s experts in a serious conversation about the topic without frequently stumbling over misunderstandings. </p></li><li><p id="d15ad26cb0a1494c9a3bc4c358f5898b">Spending<em> continuous efforts </em>to maintain alignment of the ongoing project with changes or new information in both the general domain and specific circumstances.</p><p id="c28b8e3ba3e347f59c95e2bd1e56f6de">Third, once the project has progressed to the design and implementation of the analytical models and experiments, the alignment to the business objective must be maintained. A common pitfall is that, once an intriguing machine learning aspect of the project is discovered (e.g., a dataset suitable for deep neural networks), it may appear to be more rewarding to invest resources there and neglect tasks that appear mundane or laborious (e.g., data collection, cleaning, or error analysis) but are equally important for the business objective. In extreme cases, for example, this can lead to the application of overly complex methods to unsuitable datasets, ultimately resulting in project failure. Another bad outcome is the development of models that solve problems the client does not actually have. One of the purposes of this course is to make you appreciate that a data science project\xe2\x80\x99s success needs to be gauged in typically two ways: experimental outcomes as measured by technical performance metrics and their contribution to the greater effort of reaching a business objective.</p></li></ol><p id="a94e130258ee42abb549c7371bba8972">Familiarizing oneself with different substantive domains in order to deliver good data science work takes patience and attention to detail. It is a lifelong learning process but is also one of the most rewarding aspects of this profession. It is not uncommon for data scientists to have some formal education or professional experience in specific disciplines (e.g., medicine, biology, finance, or business), which enables them to do highly effective work in that area. Similarly, trained data scientists may decide to specialize in a certain field because the depth of their expertise makes them sought after consultants, or because they consider it personally satisfying.</p><wb:inline idref="newec77e3afe5524c8c8ea4cc9b653cb082" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'