b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e4295ef073cb4dc097af7e2f6481a307"><head><title>Errors</title><objref idref="fb91d7452cca428ebc8f86c4062f67ff" /><objref idref="cc3af471b1ea43abb5a426beefa36779" /></head><body><section id="a1ac8b726a4b4cfaaa4b0cfda61762fc"><title>Overview: Errors at All Phases</title><body><p id="b5c6a6018800438fa4b046d43ce48dda">A quick survey of both scholarly and practitioner literature shows that errors can make or break the analytic development process and render your analytic solution of little use to your client. Errors can start from the business understanding phase when a data science team does not set the appropriate analytic objectives due to misunderstanding the business context and needs. This misunderstanding to bloated costs and scope creep (changes, continuous or uncontrolled growth in a project\xe2\x80\x99s scope, at any point after the project begins). A data science team might also encounter errors during the data understanding phase, such as issues with data that is not prepared adequately or, even worse, collecting data that is not relevant to the analytic solution. Errors in the data understanding phase can occur due to inexperience within the data science team and an attempt to deliver a solution prematurely.</p></body></section><section id="fa5d7b0a3b8444b5b801032e2265a662"><title>Errors in Model Understanding</title><body><p id="e801f05aa777404990b9e71345da540a">The model understanding phase also presents errors that we should explore as we are learning about the different data science patterns and techniques that can be used to solve data-related problems. Errors in this phase may show up when training and validating models. Errors will reveal if the expected performance of a model will be sufficient for deploying to production. The models below are errors that you will encounter throughout your career as a data scientist. As we learn about different techniques, we will further explore how to assess models based on certain error estimates.</p></body></section><section id="b19fcfbf63ab4ec2a701ca1981833b6a"><title>Types of Model Errors</title><body><ol id="a136b184438f43dcb7760754cf35351a"><li><p id="f775509e52b547ebaaca13582d5608f7"><em><em style="italic">Training Error </em></em>is derived by computing the classification error of a model on the exact data that was used to train the model. The training error is defined as the average loss that occurs  at the end of  the training process. It should be noted that the training error will usually be lower  than  the test error.</p></li><li><p id="ea966e949a9645839f556ba61fe00257"><em><em style="italic">Test Error </em></em>is derived by computing the classification error (the loss) of a model on the test set. It is important as it gives insight into the number of errors to expect when making future predictions, and it is used for model selection. No part of the training data set should be part of the test data, as this can affect the accuracy of the test error.  As seen below, the test error may decrease as the model complexity increases up to a certain point and then may start increasing.</p><image id="a889d845f2ee4608aa387b705d059bf8" src="../webcontent/image-e4295ef073cb4dc097af7e2f6481a307-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="200" width="300"><caption><p id="c1c2abe1d6034d7a9cb66bd022196aea" /></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></li><li><p id="fe86c0b09e764edc8d8d5c2f191bf21c"><em><em style="italic">Reducible Error</em></em> is the error resulting from a mismatch between the ground truth and the model estimation, or the estimate of the true relationship between x and y. The reducible error is the element that we can improve. It is the quantity that we reduce when the model is learning on a training dataset, and we try to get this number as close to zero as possible.</p></li><li><p id="ccc8e8200b98488cadb8678fe92f53e6"><em><em style="italic">Irreducible Error </em></em>is the noise term in the true relationship that cannot fundamentally be reduced by any model. When x can not determine y because there are other predictors that might improve the prediction error, you can incorporate those variables. The irreducible error is the error that we can not remove with our model or with any model. The error is caused by elements outside our control, such as statistical noise in the observations.</p></li></ol></body></section></body></workbook_page>\n'