b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e776dc54066f4fbf879c0769e784befb"><head><title>Informed Consent</title><objref idref="ae2e88fbb3374db1bfbacacf64426cfa" /><objref idref="c3ee2d039f65426c97dbeab02f0d5344" /><objref idref="b48e34fb35fb42ba94a0bbf195513d89" /></head><body><p id="a1697eb5d36b4cbbbd44f853a6a4c3e0">Ethical practices matter in data science because of their impact on human well-being and society at large. When it comes to <em style="italic">human subjects research</em>, the concept of <em style="italic">informed consent</em> is critical because it involves the <em>right</em> of the individual to know that they are being studied and the <em>right</em> to know how they are being studied. In this module, we will explore the concept of informed consent. First, we will explore what human subject research means, then we will learn about the link to the evolution of informed consent.</p><section id="dd58e41bd75c4e0695076456c7b8d84e"><title>Human Subjects Research</title><body><p id="b715d0dd99244fe8953739f5e99e934b">Begun in 1932, a <link href="https://www.cdc.gov/tuskegee/timeline.htm" target="new" internal="false">study</link> conducted by the United States Public Health Service (USPHS) at Tuskegee University and funded by the Centers for Disease Control (CDC), investigated the cause and development of untreated latent syphilis. Some 399 African American men in Alabama who had syphilis were recruited and matched against 201 uninfected subjects who served as a control group.</p><image id="eaf74e1e63b2429bb3a98efb6a1ae175" src="../webcontent/image-e776dc54066f4fbf879c0769e784befb-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="481" width="650"><caption><p id="a2d9055cb6954906a43907431f99c21a">Figure 1. Scenes from the Tuskegee Syphilis Study. (Source: https://www.rmpbs.org/)</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="cf3c2ace1ef7498e818b552e722861aa">The subjects were instructed to make regular visits to the clinic, where they would be given a health exam, care for minor medical issues, and a hot meal. The participants were enrolled without their informed consent to a \xe2\x80\x9cspecial free treatment,\xe2\x80\x9d which was actually intended to study the neurological effects of syphilis.</p><p id="bfe91e96167346e0a6005da59c732680">By the 1950s, when it became clear that penicillin, an antibiotic drug, was a safe and effective treatment for syphilis, the subjects were either prevented from knowing about it or denied such treatment. No subjects were treated with penicillin. The study continued until 1972, when the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW) terminated the experiment after accounts of the study appeared in the national press, driven by some whistleblowers. At that time, 74 of the test subjects were still alive. An investigatory panel appointed by HEW in August 1972 found the harm being done by the study was \xe2\x80\x9cethically unjustified\xe2\x80\x9d and stated that penicillin should have been used to treat the men. As a result, the National Research Act mandated that all federally funded proposed research with human subjects be approved by an <em>institutional review board (IRB)</em>. The IRBs monitor a process called informed consent. Informed consent states that when a study is being done on a human subject, this individual must be <em>informed about the experiment</em>, <em>must consent to the experiment voluntarily without any coercion</em>, and <em>must have the right to withdraw consent at any time</em>.</p><p id="e33078952c834cc597e7cb970ed64efb">In the case of the Tuskegee Study of Untreated Syphilis in the African American Male, the subjects were not informed about the study of neurological effects of syphilis. In addition, they were misinformed about possible treatments for syphilis and were told that syphilis could not be treated. The subjects did willingly consent to the experiment, but their consent was not properly informed, and it was not clear if the researcher told the subjects that they had the right to withdraw their consent at any time.</p><p id="a7e6a5b19e8e4fcaa42dc06bfab3f62a">The case here is that the researcher was evaluating the benefit to society or science versus the harm to the participants. A fundamental principle of informed consent is that the party facing potential harm has the right to decide on their own the balance between the benefit to society, as well as any compensation they are receiving from the experiment, and the risk of harm they face. Since full details of the potential harm and benefits are often very complex, it can be nontrivial for the human subject to be fully informed of them. For this reason, an IRB would come in, determine if the study is just and ethical, and ensure that the informed consent principles are appropriately followed.</p></body></section><section id="f22d7f2a4a214f4880656816e9a79210"><title>Informed Consent</title><body><p id="a70bb80071fa481c9e3daefa9eb777fe"><em style="italic">Informed consent</em> is based on the Fair Information Practice Principles (FIPPs) as part of the Privacy Act created in 1974. It is important to note that, progressive as it may appear, there are still limitations to the principle of informed consent. Informed consent was developed in the context of research that would be conducted on human subjects to collect data <em style="italic">prospectively</em>. In today\xe2\x80\x99s data science practices and applications, <em style="italic">informed</em> is usually something that is hidden in numerous pages of fine print, and users are required to say \xe2\x80\x9cI accept\xe2\x80\x9d before the process can begin. From an ethical point of view, setting aside the law, there is a consensus that claiming that somebody has been informed because they were given many pages of fine print to read without an actual opportunity to read them is an unethical means of obtaining consent. The concept of <em style="italic">voluntary</em> is also questionable, as consent is being obtained precisely when a user already intends to use a service or technology. Users, in these cases, are typically not given the information well in advance, providing them with adequate time to understand the risks or terms prior to consenting.</p><p id="f854bc8f8e9647b3820c03ba5e1a7b29">There is also a question of what the data will actually be used for once consent has been obtained. For example, a user may consent to give data about themselves to a merchant for a specific service, but it does not mean that the data is authorized to be repurposed. Not all repurposing of data is unethical. On the contrary, repurposing data can bring significant benefits to society in the case of medical data of one patient being studied to help future patients. One caveat here is that, in many cases, what is intended to be studied comes after the data has been collected. Physicians and medical researchers may not know the questions to be asked when data is being collected; they simply know that more information would help. This type of research is called <em style="italic">retrospective data analysis</em>.</p><p id="becc83151843400d9df389d40b3ed44b">In terms of informed consent, the problem here is how to inform subjects exactly what they are consenting to while at the same time making it comprehensive enough to include potential research questions that one might ask. So, again, this is a crucial question for conducting meaningful and ethical data science research. </p></body></section></body></workbook_page>\n'