b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="f1fd5eae72a14a8485c16fb93f4d15dc"><head><title>Case in Point: MotoManager and the Evidence Value Proposition</title><objref idref="b06d4e6407ac4dd2b30b6244bb1f3509" /><objref idref="e9e19ee410aa4e5c847c62559c95be7b" /></head><body><youtube id="dfb00c3ba646416b97f6a8e049fd1501" src="Er_0NYqqp1Y" height="300" width="500" controls="true"><cite id="i69ec2ca588db46b99eef1cad399eea8d" /><caption><p id="c3cec8959bbb48c38e6fdf771449733a">MotoManager Case-in-Point</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></youtube><p id="a6afcc48e43546b095ebfd5b050a1ea4">Here is an example of an AI consulting firm that used the EVP framework to meet the business needs of a popular automotive services provider. </p><p id="a31a1b167e9048fabdd7bd59259b3dec">Mr. Tire-Monro Muffler and Brake (a subsidiary of Monro Inc.) is a top-50 automotive part and general repair services provider in the U.S., with over 320 locations nationwide. In general, the automotive services industry struggles with customer retention. Companies record many one-time-only transactions (frequently with a deep-discount coupon) but fewer transactions from repeat customers (who typically provide much more revenue per year per customer). Lack of customer \xe2\x80\x9cstickiness\xe2\x80\x9d leads to a) less potential revenue and b) less data about customers in general, which could potentially be used to offer specific products and services to individual customers. Attempts to increase customer acquisition and retention via email marketing and television and online advertisements did little to increase the proportion of repeat customers. </p><p id="ff58f38de88a44529e4cc5184f862207">Monro Inc. (the parent company of Mr. Tire) approached <link href="https://www.cognistx.com/motomanager" target="new" internal="false">Cognistx</link> (an AI applications company) to develop a data-driven solution to improve customer acquisition and retention. The video above provides a brief summary of how Cognistx engaged with Mr. Tire to develop MotoManager, a mobile app that was deployed by Mr. Tire. This solution led to measured increases in customer acquisition and retention, as well as increased revenue. </p><p id="f080835cceeb43f18f7ca0cd3e12b3a9">The Cognistx data science team met with the business leaders of Monro Inc. to gain an understanding of the company\xe2\x80\x99s business needs related to customer retention. The data science team identified and interviewed all stakeholders from the business and technical teams at Monro Inc., including the Data Management, Information Technology, and Service Management teams. The IT managers provided information about the company\xe2\x80\x99s data asset management structure, including data governance, data architecture, and data security management. Accessible and reliable data is important to the solution vision process; a company without adequate data management can not support an analytical solution that might meet its business needs.</p><pullout id="c1518b1166e04417a0822931b07de55e"><title>Additional Reading</title><p id="a9c15b3fcbdf4c6680396fa344f6960c"><link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_management" target="new" internal="false">Data Management in the Enterprise </link></p></pullout><p id="c4d336d2bb224ac0aa63ed5e21b2fdbd">Finally, service managers were interviewed on customer service difficulties that could be addressed by the proposed solution. The service managers also identified the hardware and software gaps at various stores around the country. Once the interviews were completed, the Cognistx data science team formulated business objectives that would meet Monro Inc.\xe2\x80\x99s business needs. The business objectives included:</p><ul id="f7c8d932ae4e4b2ab9dc1b663a00e832"><li><p id="b1e84640866f40a58f2ae2f3db0d45fe">Creating an application that provides customers with a customized service experience for their automotive needs.</p></li><li><p id="cab4b499df96476abccf00ee7ff6cbfe">Offering customers $50 coupon to download Monro Inc mobile app.</p></li><li><p id="d2ef7aceb182428dbdc34132a15dbf14">Onboarding customers to the application with the creation of customer profiles.</p></li><li><p id="e2f1b513c3be4b52bafd46a3ea1bd801">Providing tailored customer service management to very important (VIP) customers.</p></li><li><p id="f9c7f60035ff46a3838def3b5458a830">Classifying customers as VIP customers based on defined characteristics.</p></li><li><p id="e52df350364f4d2587c072f746903cc6">Creating a loyalty program to increase repeat customer transactions.</p></li></ul><p id="b87d22ff072849bf916be0f14c278fdf">Business objectives should be measurable to ensure that business needs are met. The metrics used to assess the success of the project were:</p><ul id="dd88a260bef14062a8eec6fc6da295d3"><li><p id="ab467e9cdd2a4b7ba2fb5073345d9ea9">The number of people who installed the app and on-boarded upon receiving a $50 e-coupon.</p></li><li><p id="ed04e5a4a1b54e2a8f698ab10cd0c08d">The number of times an on-boarded customer visited a store close to them.</p></li><li><p id="bad2ec23971b4f0792889b74c9bbd30e">The number of transactions completed with the app.</p></li><li><p id="e8b36b420534452f89dab4549d6b688c">The total amount of revenue generated via the app compared to total cost of  maintaining the app.</p></li><li><p id="f7398361b78c4212be37f1e955435ce2">A model that can predict a repeat customer from among on-boarded customers with an accuracy of 85%.</p></li></ul><p id="bd51f217d3024feba7d2075d298c5196">The metrics were both technical (precision and accuracy of the model) and business-related (calculate return-on-investment).</p><p id="b1b689701b3d4309a0fcdcef25dcbf8a">Based on the business objectives, Cognistx developed an AI-enabled application for Monro Inc. called MotoManager. MotoManager captures a comprehensive profile of a customer through the onboarding process. Monro Inc. also sends a $50 coupon incentive to current and potential customers, and his coupon can be retrieved when a customer installs the application and completes their user profile. The MotoManager app uses customer data to provide customized reward incentives for booking services and making purchases from a customer\xe2\x80\x99s local Mr. Tire store. As of 2019, the app has had 53,000 users, and Monro Inc. has reported significant increases in customer engagement and retention. The company has generated over $14 million US dollars from app-based transactions.</p><wb:inline idref="newd3b4c909f2b148e8b1fd6fa40d81b2a6" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'