b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="a14ec0e430c44ecaab7d39e4f1e8681d"><head><title>Module 4 Summary</title></head><body><ul id="fef62e33e513401c8f116a1eea2e8dfd"><li><p id="f4da32d4b7ba4641a4a0599e5f719c5d">This module focuses on the foundation of a documentation set which is the vision document. This document not only provides a summary of the project but also clears up any confusion and ensures that you, your colleagues, and others are all on the same page.</p></li><li><p id="c4a2172e69a7445196ecd81a63300074">The project&apos;s high-level scope and purpose are represented in the vision document. It is essential as it introduces the domain of the problem that needs to be addressed and provides a rough timeline of the tasks involved in achieving this objective.</p></li><li><p id="e7169e5ce88e4fb58deb29197057ff27">To develop a vision for the project, the project team develops a vision document and related artifacts. The vision defines the high-level objective of the entire project and presents clarity with respect to the problem statement, scientific hypothesis, and scope of the proposed solution.</p></li><li><p id="db7229a6719b4547abc49f6042f2ffcb">Different components of the vision document aim to answer questions such as: What is the real-world problem that you are trying to address? How do you come up with an overarching framework for your proposed solution? If working on a technical data science solution, one can formulate your hypothesis along with one of the following themes: Is it possible to build such a framework? Is the proposed solution \xe2\x80\x9cfast /good enough\xe2\x80\x9d? Can the proposed solution significantly outperform the state-of-the-art baseline measured by a certain metric?</p></li><li><p id="fcfa2bf3338e4bc3891047dc08f3e8de">Next, the vision document focuses on the traceability part of the solution by highlighting the system features you plan to implement from the proposed solution to the problem. Finally, the scope will outline the boundaries of your project, with a focus on what will be delivered at the end of the project timeline.</p></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'