b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="b782864200d54040a4a10d38f4d40bb5"><head><title>Introduction to Data Science Ethics</title></head><body><p id="b7b06ae147924b029306614ba2605174">For much of human civilization, people did the best they could to thrive under challenging circumstances. These were times when there weren\xe2\x80\x99t many rules to follow, so people did and took what they could and weren\xe2\x80\x99t exactly ethical, but arguably this ethic was necessary to survive difficult times. That is also where we see the situation of <em>the tragedy of the commons</em>, mentioned in the previous module. Now that we also saw that the tragedy could be overcome\xe2\x80\x93 that is when we can begin to produce a better civilization for all. In this improved civilization, we no longer do things just because we can, or feel we have to. We now have to follow rules of ethics that give us more benefits collectively than they cost us. </p><p id="d15634daae9c480d89bafc0097ddd226">We have virtually unlimited access to data as data scientists today, and we have unprecedented analytical techniques with which to analyze that data. So the question we should be thinking about is whether we should do something just because it is technically possible? Are there things that are possible to do, but which we can agree would not be right to do? This may sound strange, but it is a question that modern science has already begun considering, and continues to do so.</p><p id="d63ece20000f458aa166197714fcae85">Think about how data science creates impacts and the tremendous excitement about how data science applications provide better ways of doing things in society. Think about the power you have as a data scientist and how that power influences people\xe2\x80\x99s lives, potentially for the better. <em>With that great power comes great responsibility</em>. It is crucial as data scientists that we be responsible when exercising that great power.</p><p id="cf234853907f41979d58d14d3112e7c1">The difficult thing about being an ethical data scientist is not about understanding ethics. It is the connection of how to apply ethical principles to data science practice. It is about doing \xe2\x80\x9cgood\xe2\x80\x9d or ethical data science.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'