b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="c404c7e9a5ba45dca1c9e763351aa76f"><head><title>Roles in the Data Science Lifecycle</title><objref idref="b5ce3b23d0264eb09b6773ff9d16a698" /></head><body><p id="bc79b3c6bcf94e639fbb276b64df9388">As we have seen, the data science process involves multiple steps that require the expertise of team members in defined roles. The data science team is the talent that will help develop the analytical solutions that meet the business objectives of a data-related problem. Certain organizations can provide the structure and support for the different responsibilities within the process. In smaller organizations, personnel in the data science process might wear multiple hats to ensure the efficient execution of tasks and the development of solutions. Below, you will find the roles of a typical data science team. This list of roles will vary depending on the domain and size of the organization.</p><ul id="c251bcf737ec4dd28f93e7fba38dee11"><li><p id="f17721e7337c4729a69c3b8b8cfc3fa7"><em>Data Scientist</em><em><em style="italic">.</em></em> This role involves solving business tasks using machine learning model development and statistical techniques. This individual identifies trends and patterns within the data and makes predictions based on trends. The data scientist will write code to support the data analysis and model-building process.</p></li><li><p id="ef62096d5c7a479c8115a602a312c11c"><em>Data Engineer</em><em><em style="italic">. </em></em>The Data Engineer specializes in data structures and algorithms, as well as in working with data in databases and other large repositories.</p></li><li><p id="d109b00467ec4a1e9c8af9ccca794175"><em>Solutions Architect.</em> This is a customer-facing role that ensures end-to-end customer deployment for company-related data services. The Solutions Architect interacts with clients to design, coordinate, and execute solution prototypes.</p></li><li><p id="abd94e37ae4a478086fd75fe51374c95"><em>Machine Learning (ML) Engineer.</em> The ML engineer performs modeling tasks that are different than the tasks the data scientist performs in that the ML Engineer is further away from the domain side of the project. The ML Engineer spends a considerable amount of time programming and creating ML solutions but also needs to have strong statistical skills.</p></li><li><p id="e5ca1340cafd43fb9864aa967b0beb1a"><em>Data/Business Analyst.</em> A data analyst has data gathering, analysis, and visualization skills. Like the data scientist, she provides insights from data to inform decision-making. She develops key performance indicators and utilizes business intelligence and analytics tools. Compared to data scientists, however, data/business analysts are typically firmly rooted in the business domain and are not necessarily as proficient in programming and advanced machine learning.</p></li><li><p id="e43c33dd422d4d44a30603f9b9c35075"><em>Software Engineer. </em>The Software Engineer handles the alignment between the business objectives and solution and is responsible for integrating the implemented data-driven system into the appropriate applications within the enterprise.</p></li><li><p id="a3cc5fa10acc4b3c91d253e0f6109acc"><em>Domain Experts.</em> Also known as subject matter experts, domain experts are the actors who know the most about the problem on the business side. Their role is to define the framework for the data science project, and hence they are a key participant in the process. A domain expert will translate business needs and characteristics to the data scientists and eventually judge the solution as successful or not by assessing whether the business objective has been achieved or not.</p></li></ul><wb:inline idref="newc78505cf11624b6084d389a38c4e36f7" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'