b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="c9b78b407208412f953b358734abe7c2"><head><title>Requirements Gathering - Requirements Gathering Technique</title></head><body><section id="b5f4dae553c34cd6b0278a52eb84c23d"><title>Requirements Gathering Technique</title><body><p id="e4fc87ebce1c492ca4940a452270bcc4"> </p></body></section><p id="de5ec3478e7e4da3bea36b34d42e2040">The process of discovering the requirements of stakeholders and systems is called Requirements Gathering. The requirements-gathering process involves the following:</p><ol id="ffbc2b5950994f4a85634132bb5ff95e"><li><p id="f04c501563b54e45ab497c85c0380958">Eliciting user and system needs.</p></li><li><p id="d4abc5c69d2d4e69a54d6a3e5b01e14b">Defining the formal requirements from those needs.</p></li><li><p id="ff2c952310b748ce922e6a2ac9aabc1c">Evaluating the success of the requirements-gathering process.</p></li></ol><p id="a2d913573afd4351a5387adcbd16e588">The data science project team will understand the needs of the system and stakeholders set by the business team and end-users (elicit needs/expectations) and then analyze and align the expectations to the business and analytic objectives to define the requirements for the project.</p><p id="aaac8aea423643429b7a7b0a3dfba926">Requirements gathering should be performed systematically to ensure that information is extracted from diverse sources. This will ensure that little to no bias is introduced during the process and that all user and system needs are represented and met. It is important to note that different scenarios and circumstances require a specific requirement-gathering technique.</p><section id="dec03fdb75ab470a91584bdd6465e89f"><title>Requirements Gathering Techniques</title><body><p id="f269aa685cfa4de9b30850e7ca9cb082"> </p></body></section><ol id="ee02e64d9f76428e90e8ed1643a56372"><li><p id="b281e5a6f3d94c6b985492514490382c"><em>Interviews</em>: Interviews allow the project team to investigate the needs of the stakeholder thoroughly. Interview questions are usually open-ended, allowing the respondent to provide information about various aspects of the business and identify performance gaps specific to their roles. Bear in mind that this can be time-consuming; to ensure that an interview yields the right information, an interviewer should develop questions that answer the right questions and, in certain cases, probe for answers to get useful information related to the business, system, and user. Interviews can be conducted in a one-on-one setting or a group setting.</p></li><li><p id="d1033c2f1343457d88488f1e3a72cf3b"><em>Brainstorming</em>: Brainstorming sessions involve gathering ideas from multiple stakeholders. In a brainstorming session, a facilitator monitors the session to ensure all possible solutions are identified and that all parties contribute to the process in a reasonable amount of time. This technique can yield new ideas and themes that would otherwise be difficult for the analyst to produce. A brainstorming session should have five to eight representatives from each shareholder group, including management, users, and support staff.</p></li><li><p id="b844699a57e04a27ace58948a70aadee"><em>Questionnaires</em>: The project team will distribute predefined questions to stakeholders in the company. The feedback from the questionnaires will be analyzed and used to define the project requirements. Non-technical system users and stakeholders can complete a well-designed questionnaire with little or no guidance from the project team. Due to budget, time, and scheduling constraints, this technique can be used when interviews are impossible.</p></li><li><p id="f4313aa903d9428c8fca13a539dea2ff"><em>Document Analysis</em>: This information-gathering technique involves reviewing existing documentation to elicit needs. Document analysis can be the first step in the requirements-gathering process and can be used to create questions for questionnaires or interview sessions. Document analysis is a supporting technique and can serve as a completeness check for requirements.</p></li><li><p id="c9a4d5169fb44b9e8102e275efc910a5"><em>Facilitated Workshops</em>: The workshop is facilitated by a neutral party, usually an outside consultant whose task is to collect information from stakeholders. This workshop is also known as a Joint Application Design session. These workshops should be structured yet interactive; facilitated workshops can lead to discovering underlying issues within the business. A successfully executed workshop can result in the development of requirements. Participants of a workshop include a Scribe who records the discussions taking place during the session; an Executive Sponsor who has the authority to make decisions about the project; the sponsor will set the vision of the project and resolve conflicts; the appropriate client stakeholders, Subject Matter Experts, and Silent Observers.</p></li></ol><section id="dadd5c528312429aa472330aca505103"><title> </title><body><p id="c97e8aa82fc5421f9a6c5a09edcf5dbe"> </p></body></section><section id="b76195454f4b435a8bcefbecae7d31e9"><title>Risk Types and Examples</title><body><p id="cdbe77d411e5459388fff710bcd6c357"> </p></body></section><p id="de99bca188a04c77b3e88caa5e91328e" /><p id="b4f2887b272545e6a87a150b49fd3a0d">This section will help you find all the risks pertaining to your project in a holistic way. They can serve as a rationale behind the decisions that you make during the design process. You will not necessarily include risks in the requirements document, but considering these risks helps your team discover and gather important requirements for your project. You would want to think about these risks and document them during the requirements-gathering process.</p><p id="dbce69ee0a0a4081800432923bd89fad" /><ol id="b4ec136b7dcc4ae484e1815e8bf14211"><li><p id="b9f09bdb36c645e78e2301fabfedc421"><em>Business Risks</em></p></li></ol><p id="d5f16bc7d9534b8fab17fcc5f249eedd">These are risks concerning the realization of benefits or limiting losses. The project sponsor is usually responsible for such risks, but it is valuable to give these a thought for your capstone project. </p><p id="a234b0f0b1b746f59e8c376c431b876a">The risks arising out of the question \xe2\x80\x98Are we building the right thing?\xe2\x80\x99 are classified in this category.</p><p id="b439760aa0e54c419f71b1cf9c555575">Example: </p><ul id="cce1e06dd5354c70b26ff35f5b64666b"><li><p id="a654c6b8a368444980fef781543b45f5">The product or service might face difficulties in being deployed at the sponsor site or accepted in the open market.</p></li></ul><p id="de288993a490432ea24be36d16d6cea9" /><ol id="d9acfb6ab4ca4b3db203b6110bc69143"><li><p id="b967d822ab444bff88604c634a4ce954"><em>Product Risks</em></p></li></ol><p id="fc57583d062b4fcbacc76fc82a1087c3">These are risks concerning the users, operators, and bystanders that could be negatively affected by the use or deployment of the project outcomes. Such risks would materialize only after the product has been delivered. These risks are important for safety and reliability. For the capstone project, you should consider the effects of wrong predictions or unexpected system behavior on users.</p><p id="bf70d38196e34f76a4acb7379c183b8b">Examples: </p><ul id="ff756eb8cf7e405eb80d620d16da0b2e"><li><p id="af08250c1c244003bb0bf08d6f5dd877">How will inaccurate prediction model results affect the user?</p></li><li><p id="f1508e99cb6b407ab0614315a9a89adf">How will we prevent the product from overheating when used for a long period?</p></li></ul><p id="a44356a4f4c74d9c9244371044dbe587" /><ol id="b8a962236a6e4c2a867eba8048569ecf"><li><p id="fb288257419f4d63b3732c1f4335ef00"><em>Project (Process) Risks</em></p></li></ol><p id="bf3e538970e04c16a1573e00d7d22fa7">These are the risks concerning the technologies or data that could have a negative impact on the requirements, cost, or schedule.</p><p id="f2aebe06edd84d6bbe9e5a4263deec5f">Examples: </p><ul id="ea948e64f0194e8fb75d06988c98f230"><li><p id="b07b9d22390f42c99732134a0b049067">The risk of using a new high-performance framework with poor documentation.</p></li><li><p id="b12eaff64ef54460ae3907213564a35d">The risk of unavailability of data.</p></li><li><p id="d3dc497915814e979e5aba80bdd04abb">A technology does not work as expected.</p></li></ul><p id="c143fffc0c1041fc982d94c2fe832b43" /><ol id="fde3fa2929cf460bb32ff7ced706729a"><li><p id="c239a78b6714489e9a97072396512fc7"><em>Regulatory Risks </em></p></li></ol><p id="be453967b2ff4a53b763a09ad1469e09">The risk of a change in regulations and laws that might affect your project. You can consider risks due to data privacy regulations for your project.</p><p id="f24d8f6dc2db40008ec2b18d70eda719" /><p id="e83e9cfefe3140558af690870d64297e">Some risks that you might not need to look at during the capstone project but might help you in the future.</p><p id="ff314e224a374b328ee8868e35d6b182" /><ul id="ebeae64ddfb646e183c49faf56bee2b8"><li><p id="c05cbd6b5da54ef69716c882be0e87b0"><em>Political risks </em>concern political decisions, events, or conditions that will significantly affect the profitability of a product. </p></li><li><p id="adff9b52d1c64db984e4b66948f9b417"><em>Operational risks </em>are risks resulting from inadequate or failed internal processes, people, and systems or from external events. For example, computer hacking, fraud, and failure to comply with policies.</p></li><li><p id="a7845402e90f48e3b1126818868f91a2"><em>Deployment risks </em>refer to the costs associated with deploying a solution or product. This can include hardware and software expenses, installation costs, personnel costs, and other expenses such as training and maintenance. Understanding the deployment cost is important because it can impact the profitability of the solution or product, and it can also help to determine the overall value proposition.</p></li><li><p id="a01fb0f4e5954abebc8bba373e4addd3"><em>Selling risks </em>refer to the risk associated with selling a solution or product. This can include the risk of not being able to sell the solution or product, the risk of selling it at a lower price than expected, and the risk of not being able to recover the deployment cost. Selling risk can be mitigated by conducting market research, understanding the target audience, and developing a comprehensive marketing and sales strategy.</p></li></ul><p id="a25e94ab3f624eea8b2ef2f6aa65aa8b" /><p id="f6247176ece6452d870afd86d76e8711" /></body></workbook_page>\n'