b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="d56d3bb42c074de99f204348d13e6fc2"><head><title>Introduction to Exploratory Data Analysis</title><objref idref="e08c8adde1bd4b95a76dd5bdd546543a" /></head><body><p id="b7771261da62445f9d5a5979fcbf3eb5">We&apos;ve seen that statistical methods are descriptive or inferential. The purpose of descriptive statistics is to summarize data and to make it easier to assimilate the information. The exploratory data analysis (EDA) process comprises visualizing data to allow a data scientist or a data analyst to explore datasets to gain insights from the data. EDA uses non-graphical techniques and graphical techniques to explore the data. Non-graphical techniques include using summary statistics to describe the data, and graphical techniques are used to describe the frequency distribution of the dataset. Both techniques can be used to show the skew of the data distribution and the extreme outliers. </p><p id="dca014ef224441c9b55291a4bc96e618"><em>Summarizing Data</em></p><p id="a8f7473e9c0640699db153a0c8d51ccb">Summarizing data is dependent on the types of data present in your dataset. It is difficult to describe a large data set in its raw form and use specific techniques to summarize and describe the data, including <em style="italic">Describing Central Tendency and Assessing Measures of Spread and Relationships</em>.</p><p id="eb6c77eca73e472c98b63686f3ef45af">One can use the location in the data space, the shape of the distribution, and the spread of the data in a dataset to understand its aggregate properties. some of the concepts below can seem like a review of a first course in Statistics, but one should pay attention to the reason for using these techniques in exploring the data. Furthermore, these concepts are important when using statistical inference to draw conclusions on an unknown population parameter.</p><p id="db32b1d4e1f5496b80cbda22e35ff3dd"><em>Location</em>. During the EDA process, one describes the data using a central value. The <em style="italic">Mean</em>, sometimes called the arithmetic average, is one such value and is the sum total of all observations divided by the number of observations in the data. The whole population of data may have a population mean value \\(\\mu\\), or if you are only exploring a (smaller) sample, you can talk about a sample mean \\(\\overline{x}\\) In addition to the standard arithmetic mean, there are also other central values such as the geometric mean, and harmonic mean.</p><p id="c25d8a06c5834723b4af9fa49496996e">The <em>Median</em> is the mid-value of a dataset. To compute a median value, one first sorts the data in ascending order. The median value in a dataset with an odd number of elements is the value in the middle. For example, for the (sorted) set {1, 3, 5, 7, 9}, the median will be 5. On the other hand, s the median of a dataset with an even number of elements observations is defined to be the average of the two middle values. For example, for the (sorted) set {1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11}, the median is defined to be the average of 5 and 7 = 6.</p><table id="cdc75d279c744910adb279671bda5719" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="icb7b1702f98c434e95b26a4048386442" /><caption><p id="f8b1f75ec59b4bd99cfc2fa09193b0ce" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b2e3677e88304b21b2720dd0a5a1b8d5"><em>If the mean and median of your data set differ greatly, you should check that variable for outliers!</em></p></td></tr></table><p id="ec55d5c44c744214a42307c17ece7622"><em>Mode</em> is the value that occurs most frequently in the dataset. A uni-modal variable is one that has just one mode, and a bimodal variable has two modes. If your data has more than two modes, it can be referred to as multi-modal. The mode is quite useful when summarizing categorical variables.</p><p id="c36114e12b1d4620adc2a1e4b3918b13"><em>Percentile</em>. You may remember this nifty word from your GRE scores or height and weight data from your health records. The percentile tells you the position of a value in the dataset. If someone is 175cm in height and she is in the 10th percentile of height measurement for her gender, it means that among all the height data collected for that gender, she is taller than 10% of those values. The 50th percentile is considered to be the median. <em style="italic">Quartiles</em> are values that split the data into quarters.</p><p id="d3bb056e3bcf4c44920d3a4396c92e3a">The are several measures to describe the spread, variability, or dispersion of a dataset </p><p id="d26c2d8f1d294e148580c6ea3ffc6298"><em>Range</em> of a set of values in a dataset can be calculated by subtracting the minimum value in your dataset from the maximum value. Notice that the range only considers two values and ignores all other values of a variable.</p><p id="ae4ed949a40d4c1da1c3dc88388b4605"><em>Mean Absolute Deviation</em> is the average distance between each value and the mean of a dataset., that is </p><p id="e2e6b27badbf40bfb984d5f7c0863a25">\\[\\sum_i\\frac{\\mid x_i - \\mu\\mid}{N}\\]</p><p id="a03e741887b14cbfa0c3fab79f660359">where \\(N\\) is the number of values and \\(x_i\\) is the \\(i^{th}\\) value in the data set.</p><p id="a64a4b01f8b64ef2b4833e6139e012c6">This measure of dispersion can tell you how values are spread out in a dataset and determine whether the mean is a useful indicator of the values within the data. The larger the mean absolute deviation, the more spread out the data. When working with time series forecasting methods, one uses the mean absolute deviation to measure the performance of a forecasting model. <em>Variance</em>, typically denoted by \\(\\sigma^2\\), is defined as the averaged square deviation of the values in a data set from the mean that is </p><p id="f6db704b12d24a5f8e94829e2bcb574c">\\[\\sigma^2 = \\sum_i\\frac{(x_i - \\mu)^2}{N}\\]</p><p id="e21566ce0289424888b51ed53198e5ee"><em>Standard deviation,</em> \\(\\sigma\\), is simply the square root of the variance. It is the most commonly used measure of the amount of variation or dispersion of a set of values.</p><p id="a80139dbc1ee4b06a86cc92443fc08a8">A low standard deviation tells you that the values are close to the mean, and a high standard deviation means there is a spread. As one performs exploratory data analysis and even while developing models, the importance of the standard deviation can not be overstated. Despite its mention as a way to summarize data, the standard deviation is also used to \xe2\x80\x9cmeasure the confidence in statistical conclusions\xe2\x80\x9d and to draw statistical inference conclusions on data and hypotheses.</p><p id="e545b24e4ca946839f2ea95c75874384"><em>Interquartile Range (IQR)</em>, similar to the range, does not consider all observations when looking at the spread of values in a dataset. IQR describes 50% of values in your dataset when arranged in ascending order. The IQR is the difference between the values in Quartile 3 and the values in Quartile 1. You can use this measure to identify a value that is an outlier.</p><p id="f2cb6124026c410482ca05b84717024f"><em>Shape</em>. Now that you can explain the measures used to explore data by describing its central value and its spread from the mean, and identifying outliers, let us describe the distribution of a dataset and assess whether it is normally distributed. Normally distributed data is useful when making statistical inferences. How can we assess the distribution of our data:</p><p id="cc35b4d81a77446c88ace06df3364095"><em>Skewness</em> measures the degree to which the distribution of data lacks symmetry. A dataset with <em>0</em> skewness is considered normally distributed. Data does not always have a skewness of 0; however, if you have found skewness to be between -0.5 and 0.5, you can ascertain that your data is symmetrical. If skewness is between -1 and -0.5 or 0.5 and 1, then your data is moderately skewed. If skewness is &lt; -1 or &gt; 1, your data is highly skewed.</p><image id="a43d6dcff78b4c569d54c15e7bfa4647" src="../webcontent/image-d56d3bb42c074de99f204348d13e6fc2-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="473" width="650"><caption><p id="c7dc2d92cbb24f559fcc51d1ce6fa60c">Figure 1. Symmetrical Dataset with Skewness = 0 (Source: BPI Consulting LLC)</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="f4a84b843d704cf591bde35933ff9adc">Kurtosis looks at the outliers within the distribution. This measure of shape will describe the distribution of data by showing whether the tails of the distribution are more or less extreme than the normal distribution.</p><p id="e44c78af389040d39d330a21a38da7b1">Covariance describes the linear relationship between two variables in your sample or population data. Covariance can be negative, meaning your variables have a negative linear relationship, zero (0), meaning the variables have no linear relationship, or positive, meaning a positive linear relationship exists between the variables.</p><p id="da846b8aa4c34edf8080287af4f2e7fb">Correlation or correlation coefficient describes how strong the association between two variables, x, and y, is in terms of how closely the data follow a straight line trend. It is a different measure than covariance because it describes both the direction and strength of the linear relationship between the variables. The correlation value lies between -1 and 1: \\(\\left | r_{XY} \\right |\\leq 1\\)</p><p id="a1836b46d7cc47329408b7c20e436285">The correlation equals 1 if \\(x_i=y_i\\) for all \\(i\\) and equals -1 if \\(x_i=-y_i\\) for all \\(i\\).</p><p id="ffb10d5bf68a4fe38e9de3ee9f9c3e78">More generally, if the scatterplot of x and y is a straight line, then the correlation is either 1 or -1. If the line slopes upward, there is a positive relationship between x and y, and the correlation is 1. If the line slopes down, there is a negative relationship, and the correlation is -1. The closer the scatterplot is to a straight line, the closer the correlation is to 1 or -1.</p><p id="aa50d45dd4dd4dca9d2620f377c8d919">A high correlation coefficient does not necessarily mean that the line has a steep slope; rather, it means that the points in the scatterplot fall very close to a straight line.</p><image id="e3a1049d19414f20b047ad38ba5457a8" src="../webcontent/image-d56d3bb42c074de99f204348d13e6fc2-2.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="464" width="650"><caption><p id="a80131b728554b7299f47635183aed4b">Figure 2. Scatterplots for Four Hypothetical Datasets.</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="aaab3f451a844f1da4c4410281ebb62e">Figure 2 gives additional examples of scatterplots and correlation. Figure 2a shows a strong positive linear relationship between these variables, and the correlation is 0.81. Figure 2b shows a strong negative relationship with a sample correlation of -0.81. Figure 2c shows a scatterplot with no evident relationship, and the correlation is zero. Figure 2d shows a clear relationship: As x increases, y initially increases but then decreases. Despite this discernable relationship between X and Y, the sample correlation is zero. the reason is that, for these data, small values of Y are associated with both large and small values of X. This final example emphasizes an important point: The correlation coefficient is a measure of linear association. There is a relationship in Figure 2d, but it is not linear.</p><p id="de3bca88980846589a70153a91d158cc">One important note on correlation is that <em style="italic">two variables having an association does not mean there is a causal relationship between them.</em></p></body></workbook_page>\n'