b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="d9763f7f0f1b4885bdc5466dfa04429f"><head><title>Working in a team: Exploiting Agile Scrum</title></head><body><p id="aaa432654d15472aa112f508d01411cc">Many different frameworks can be used to adopt an efficient software development life cycle for your data science project. These methodologies have been tested and have established pros and cons so that teams don\xe2\x80\x99t have to spend too much time choosing among them. Agile Scrum is quite popular in major technology companies. It is important to remember that many factors affect the decision to choose a framework, including the time to complete a project, the number of team members, the cultural setting of the organization, etc. However, these frameworks are not rigid and can be modified to suit the team\xe2\x80\x99s interests and style of working.</p><p id="a9494988dd2d4296a5a13f77d360df6c">Let\xe2\x80\x99s dive into how Agile is usually implemented in the industry and how to apply it to a data science project.</p><p id="a96c2a1886a84ea98066ca3fed9aa13a">Let\xe2\x80\x99s first understand the roles in the <em>Agile Scrum</em> framework:</p><ul id="ffcca163569f4bdb8e061645c0d0adb8"><li><p id="a4e9f5d22a7249758d4e34d3a2e32d50"><em>Scrum Master. </em>The Scrum Master ensures that each sprint stays on track. In a project team, one of the team members can assume this role. In general, the Scrum Master need not be the most senior person or the team lead. Usually, a Scrum Master also helps to remove or resolve any issues or challenges that may come up.</p></li><li><p id="dd8c60d28a734542895333932aa4335e"><em>Product owner.</em> The role of the product owner is to define the goals of each sprint, manage and prioritize the team backlog, and be the voice of the customer. This role ensures that the team prioritizes work that will be useful for a user. In a project team, anyone in the team can take up his role.</p></li><li><p id="e1bedc0d5fc6494099766d5ebe54e6a8"><em>Team members. </em>The people on this team are the ones who execute the work in each sprint. These teams, usually of three to seven people, can be composed of different specialties and strengths, or they can be teams of people with the same job roles.</p></li><li><p id="b0916f6f76404aca963c03226ec6fda6"><em>Stakeholders.</em> This is an informational role only. The stakeholders should be kept up-to-date on the product and sprint goals, have the opportunity to review and approve work during a sprint and provide feedback during the sprint retrospective.</p></li></ul><p id="b3d573c6807944ae87407f5d568b002a"><em>User stories:</em> A user story is simply a high-level definition of a work request. It contains just enough information so the team can produce a reasonable estimate of the effort required to accomplish the request. This short, simple description is written from the user\xe2\x80\x99s perspective and focuses on outlining what the stakeholder wants (their goals) and why.</p><p id="b6c4c52b5bb6464b8fcaa5cb4ee44032">For example, if you are building an application that guides a user with directions, here is an example of a user story:</p><ul id="b3c35d7b2350480ebba4ec4d49a2fe59"><li><p id="ad38d58d8fc54a1a887566b1187995d4">As a user, I want to be able to navigate my way using the directions so that I can reach my destination. </p></li><li><p id="e2be4978f03541aeb1c05508984c24ad">As a user, I want to be able to change the destination so that I can reach a new destination.</p></li></ul><p id="afabba5a769d4bdeadf568cb3425da16"><em>Sprints: </em> Sprints are a short span of work, usually taking between one to three weeks to complete, where teams work on tasks determined in the sprint planning meeting. As you move forward, the idea is to repeat these sprints until your product is feature ready continuously. Once the sprint is over, you review the product, see what is and isn\xe2\x80\x99t working, make adjustments, and begin another sprint to improve the product or service. This feature helps you build products that generate value for the stakeholder.</p><p id="a348dbf435934e8eae3f547f26f22879"><em>Stand-up meetings:</em> Daily stand-up meetings (typically under 10 minutes), also known as \xe2\x80\x9cdaily Scrum meetings,\xe2\x80\x9d are a great way to ensure everyone is on track and informed. These daily interactions are known as \xe2\x80\x9cstand up\xe2\x80\x9d because the participants are required to stay standing, helping to keep the meetings short and to the point. Regular sync-up helps in mitigating any new challenges early on.</p><p id="c3a135ff69c948a7ab428fb7ecf40234"><em>Agile board:</em> An Agile board helps your team track the progress of your project. This can be a whiteboard with sticky notes, a simple Kanban board, or a function within your project management software (like JIRA). If you love sticky notes, you can, for instance, consider MURAL to build your board virtually, and all pending activities can go onto this board.</p><p id="c916654875af421ebd05b6ed8f9fb57b"><em>Backlog: </em>As project requests are added through your intake system, they become outstanding stories in the backlog. During Agile planning sessions, your team will estimate story points for each task. During sprint planning, stories in the backlog are moved into the sprint to be completed during the iteration. Managing your backlog is a vital role for project managers in an Agile environment. In a project team, this will be the team\xe2\x80\x99s collective effort. </p><p id="fbbbf6307cb4458287d8b9a3c564e00a"><em>Sprint retrospective: </em> This is a meeting where the team comes together to recognize what has worked and what has not worked. The team makes efforts to make sure the concerns are dealt with to ensure the smooth completion of the project.</p><p id="cff2be21d72c43b89dfe2d5d27df049f"><em>Demonstration: </em>This is when the team demonstrates a working product to the stakeholders in order to show them the value generated from the project and to keep them happy.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'