b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e1edee00fa474fb6a12db539b7ac9ca2"><head><title>Unit 2 Rework</title></head><body><p id="d13f142360324692926804f4bdb42e56" /><p id="d5f87d25cd0a4ddca87aac55bed6a203">Learning Objectives</p><p id="d36407f87ad84e97a944572eb613c2a0">Describe the business value proposition for a project: what problems it attempts to solve, the generality and novelty of the proposed solution, and how the success of the proposed solution will be measured. </p><p id="b7c48a55dd1a42b4aabf20f24f7fd6e7">Anticipate how the problem, requirements, and associated data may change over time, and how those changes will affect the relevance and accuracy of data-driven solutions.</p><p id="b91f1fd4b70f4206b9761f6aacfef0cc">Formulate functional and non-functional requirements for an envisioned data-driven solution to a business/research problem.</p><p id="dc4b82cc1fd348aeba76d91793782ba5">Recognize information inside an organization as potentially usable in the design and development of data-driven solutions.</p><p id="c353f8a0d27143fa84465f900abdf334" /><p id="a200eef027354942bbd2cfe88982bfa7">Overview:</p><p id="ccd66cbf7d5f45ccb6c29505e39976c6" /><p id="f1164688975e4ac1be6e1478283541a6">Having introduced the data science lifecycle in the previous unit, we will now discuss the more concrete steps that you should take in your own data science project. Similar to traditional software development projects, Data Science projects should also be guided by documentation to support the different steps taken while embarking on the project. The documentations provide a framework for envisioning the project, gathering requirements, designing the solution, and planning concrete milestones. In this unit, we explore each of the four flavors of the framework, their importance, benefits, and best practices.  </p><p id="ea663015720b489883e74a4db91c1ede">As you have learned in a previous unit, gaining an understanding of the business need and formulating project objectives (business and analytic) are best practices for successfully meeting client expectations. Once the project objectives have been defined, the project team will identify the needs and constraints of stakeholders and the current system or environment related to the business need; this is referred to as the <em style="italic">Requirements Gathering Process</em>.</p><p id="f31502631d834dca86f1698e90ac20f5"><em style="italic">Requirements gathering </em>establishes communication between the solutions development team (referred to as the project team in this unit) and the business stakeholders. The objective of the requirements gathering process is to define the system inputs, processes, outputs, and interfaces. When properly done, requirements gathering will positively influence the outcome of a project. Requirements gathering can also help the project team to visualize the intended solution.</p><p id="ef6303f499db49c0be077a180b207783">The requirements gathering process involves input from the <em style="italic">system users </em>and <em style="italic">system owners</em>. A system user interacts with the solution, and a system owner (who can also be a user) is an official who is responsible for decisions made about systems within their organization. In this unit, we will refer to these roles as <em style="italic">stakeholders</em>.</p><p id="e98e4f7766744827b27181beba90fafb" /><p id="e01cd38d22e44be492fa5a0993b648d2" /><p id="c20713bec04242b1986db2b98dfb20ca" /><p id="e448381488884d9c935791f9ec24084e" /><p id="d729cf8dff74427d938e4af1c1d70193" /><p id="fa0869f8f3ce4d18aca2506187dba1df" /><p id="ef8076b87b544bd6af3ab6616c53c368" /><p id="b34a397c97694500ad8fa5a824058ec0" /><p id="d0ee71fadf6d468ebe088e3b5c6ce99b" /><section id="addfe7c4aa044a57b65d21694a873bf2"><title>1 Developing a vision for the project</title><body><p id="bf1f4ccc392e462cb3864c4c2df26be5"> </p></body></section><section id="f63514442ac54f719c40169c8efb4567"><title>Overview:</title><body><p id="b2a02b7b86564054984813364a33fccc"> </p></body></section><p id="f78a655dc1c74445b3197bf6e14df6cb" /><p id="d089441db520442e8559febdc993677d">The vision document is the starting point of your documentation set. Besides giving an overview of the project, this document helps remove ambiguities and puts everyone, including your collaborators and others, on the same page. Documenting these details helps direct every effort in the future towards the same goal. This is essentially helpful when there are many collaborators, which is usually the case in the industry. Without a clear vision, the project can go off the rails with changing collaborators or leadership. Take the example of the <link href="https://ieeexplore-ieee-org.cmu.idm.oclc.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?tp=&amp;arnumber=1502526" target="new" internal="false">Virtual Case File study</link>. The FBI blew more than $100 million on a case-management software it will never use. One of the reasons for failure was an unclear vision for the project.</p><section id="f565ee02b663465eb394b007171a75aa"><title>Developing a vision</title><body><p id="d431ecb020cb4a4781f38b78f3fb39a3"> </p></body></section><p id="fd5d202e8e934262aa388dcf43bf0e09" /><p id="a90d02e12625461dad3fd97619cbfb10">To develop a vision for the project, the project team works with stakeholders to develop a vision document and related artifacts that represent the high-level scope and purpose of the project. The vision document communicates the motivation for the project - what problems does the proposed undertaking attempt to solve, and for what data set(s)? What is novel or unique about the proposed method? How will success be measured and evaluated? What is the anticipated impact (business or research value) if the project is successful? An explicit statement of the problem, proposed solution, and high-level features of the project can establish clear expectations and reduce potential risks.</p><p id="b9f5f0525018498e9334e9c65f9decef" /><p id="da55c778449d42b9b8769c93ca476ff9">Before diving into the implementation of the project, the vision must be developed. The vision defines the high-level objective of the entire project and presents clarity with respect to the problem statement, scientific hypothesis, and scope of the proposed solution. It is essential as it introduces the domain of the problem that needs to be addressed and provides a rough timeline of the tasks involved in achieving this objective. It provides context to succeeding developers about why exactly this project is necessary.</p><p id="e4261213c29340be8fd65f7d3b973a59" /><image id="d2fc0236e1fa42e38da54cc47246b151" src="../webcontent/image-e1edee00fa474fb6a12db539b7ac9ca2-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="234" width="468"><caption><p id="c4adee9b885645dca579b38ae7c0dc68" /></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image><p id="aea9c68f6da841478aa0fc1143db21e6">Source: IMB, Engineering Lifecycle Management</p><p id="cc7452ef642a45c3b3d88ae1b0940f69" /><section id="a4e4de3fe04e4bc491768111674a030e"><title>The vision document</title><body><p id="e9845875bfc5496590f0d6fdc70d1df5"> </p></body></section><p id="df9809ac3e3844508884cf07c555bb9e" /><p id="d243b3b71d2d4bc0bcdbe2830f557c4e">The important components of a vision document is described as follows.</p><p id="c113abc67e184726941bb34c00210915" /><p id="f826d8a96c6443b9b9fbade5e0b0337f"><em>Problem Description</em>. First, you need to determine the real-world problem that you are trying to address. You should also look into the literature to identify existing solutions and their limitations. Your goal is to propose an improvement to these solutions in some ways so as to yield tangible social or business impacts.</p><p id="d6cf65a115c1442bb38290c4dd52f4b6" /><p id="db4483d725404a339afdd33edd74f764"><em>Proposed Solution</em>. Next, come up with an overarching framework for your solution. An example solution formulation could be \xe2\x80\x9cA framework that supports declarative description of a configuration space and automatically evaluates all the options, finding the best given some measure and labeled dataset.\xe2\x80\x9d Compare your solution with the existing solutions identified previously \xe2\x80\x93 what makes your solution better?</p><p id="dc8ddea5cc9c47649e2b45bd63a3edea" /><p id="e98f3a32ab3242d4ab29cef6f7909483"><em>Scientific Hypotheses</em>. Now you need to formalize the scientific hypotheses underlying your proposed solution. Keep in mind that hypotheses need to be <em style="italic">testable</em> assumptions. For example, if you make the assumption that the majority of your users are teenagers, but your platform doesn\xe2\x80\x99t collect users\xe2\x80\x99 ages, then your assumption is not testable. Then, develop a plan to validate your hypothesis as you develop your solution. With respect to a technical data science solution, you can formulate your hypothesis along with one of the following themes:</p><ol id="ce911c05e9194226ad59d292dfaf9680"><li><p id="ed2c63df2e2d483bba685e67f194ab94">\xe2\x80\x9cConstructive\xe2\x80\x9d: It is possible to build such a framework</p></li><li><p id="f92311a9d34e4306b43761ef81cbd3b3">\xe2\x80\x9cFormative\xe2\x80\x9d: The proposed solution is \xe2\x80\x9cfast /good enough\xe2\x80\x9d</p></li><li><p id="e869d7207f9c4bf891c6f15508b1d473">\xe2\x80\x9cEmpirical\xe2\x80\x9d: The proposed solution will significantly outperform the state-of-the-art baseline measured by a certain metric.</p></li></ol><p id="bf8bb337539f496396234330703b64e2" /><p id="a7aa41d70dba4569988520e9b769b0ec"><em>Major Features</em>. For the next step, you should describe in more specific terms how the system features you plan to implement form the proposed solution to the problem (e.g. a list of major features or components of your solution). This is really important from a &quot;traceability&quot; perspective as it&apos;s easy to miss major features as you dive deeper into the project. Here are the important requirements for the proposed features:</p><ol id="f0e417e09f8c426e93d92962a7a7dd14"><li><p id="c22b118cfa22473786d56dbd0e7127b9">Features should not be technical constraints. For example, \xe2\x80\x9cthe system will use an Amazon AWS load balancer to manage traffic\xe2\x80\x9d is a bad example, while \xe2\x80\x9cthe system will use a cloud-based load balancer to manage traffic\xe2\x80\x9d is a good example.</p></li><li><p id="da4a7b77210c4b86b48ff7e738198344">Features should be distinct, in the sense that no two features should overlap.</p></li><li><p id="d278134e49d94e1fb7bb2500d8f434ce">Features should be traceable, with a unique name or identifier so that they can be traced across different documents and project stages.</p></li></ol><p id="d981196d39fd4eca873449a98a87c214" /><p id="a8247b76ce2542d2bb2b9ca5ebae4a1d"><em>Scope</em>. At this point, you will want to outline the boundaries of your project, with a focus on what will be delivered at the end of the project timeline. If there is something your project will specifically not do, you should note it here. For example, be clear about how much (or how little) data will be covered, whether your solution will meet certain run-time requirements in terms of responsiveness, whether your solution will be deployed as a web service or application or exist only as a code repository / Jupyter notebook, etc.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'