b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\r\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="ac4605b2a7c54814adae760db0cd03d3"><head><title>Overview</title><objref idref="aaaf4d4a01484fd3aff18868f882e298" /><objref idref="f884b110ee3f48bfaf5a73e27e20b647" /><objref idref="b4647f50264b4b139d2d7cee1646eecd" /><objref idref="f1ca21f4076b4f2fb719d5f7ecbb78e3" /></head><body><p id="bc3c7d525d614709beabfde261f308cc">\rYou are almost through with completing the task that will meet the analytic objectives that you set in Unit 1. You have come far in the process of understanding how to define a problem, set analytic and project objectives, define requirements, perform exploratory data analysis, and build models, all to meet your objectives. The journey is not over!</p><p id="aecb069bbfe44d6fb3fb4cd80bb97c11">Every step of the way, you have examined how your solution will affect the decision makers and those affected by those decisions. If your solution is for healthcare, you are likely to be on the other side of that model&apos;s results. All that to say, the work you do as a data scientist has far reaching implications that require care and accuracy.</p><p id="a88b4c65e6c1466db203164934427b65">The following modules explore the tradeoff between the accuracy of our models and interpretability. We define accuracy and interpretability in light of a model&apos;s performance and the relationship between the inputs and output. Once it is all said and done, will your model be able to answer questions? Can decision makers make the right decisions?</p><p id="ad3355746a404c0c9558c2d34e4f0fc4">The more accurate a model, the less interpretable it is; should we then make all models interpretable as this is most helpful in industries such as health and insurance?</p><p id="b20b3f83e4e14d8b88722fd39e8a12a3">You will find even after this course that you will be making tradeoffs between model accuracy and model interpretability.</p></body></workbook_page>\r\n'