b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="c92fcac6686c4fd096dec4a854a271f2"><head><title>Step 3: Focusing on a well-defined Task </title><objref idref="c652b19601414ebebcfaed9f52cd17e0" /></head><body><p id="f8d21e8fa8f2469595fb68dc8a649fed">Once the team has identified the precise problem for which data should be leveraged, it is advisable to explicitly characterize the task to be done at the analytical level. To do this, one casts the \xe2\x80\x9cheart\xe2\x80\x9d of the problem into one or more categories of typical data science tasks: </p><p id="eba3187b5eca48ff82de87186aaba40c"><em>Classification</em>: Individual instances in the dataset have a categorical (i.e., non-numerical) label associated with them or will be labeled as such. The goal of the project is to develop a system capable of categorizing data points using these labels. A common variant of classification is sequence labeling, where individual data points are not independent but form a series. Typical examples of classification are sentiment analysis of text and labeling images as depicting certain objects (animals, cars, etc.).</p><p id="ef710c576d21451e8b260faf23701e22"><em>Regression</em>: Individual instances in the dataset have a numerical label associated with them whose magnitude carries a specific meaning. The goal of the project is to develop a model capable of predicting this target score for individual data instances. Like classification, regression is often applied to dependent series of data points. Typical examples of regression include predicting measurements in medical or demographic data over time.</p><p id="dd906bebad174e3fade01891562fda2f"><em>Retrieval &amp; Ranking</em>: The dataset can be thought of as one or more collections of data points and queries. In response to the query, one or more \xe2\x80\x9cideal\xe2\x80\x9d data points should be retrieved and presented in \xe2\x80\x9ccorrect\xe2\x80\x9d order. A typical example is a  search engine returning a ranked list of results in response to a query. </p><p id="bdbdae2e13c242cfaa2610aa5e31eedc"><em>Recommendation</em>: The dataset consists of users and items, as well as information about the preferences of users for specific items. The task is to find items to recommend to users towards the maximization of some utility. Typical examples are movie recommendations on Netflix and product recommendations on Amazon.</p><p id="ccddd738ce2a4456b9d53aff7ee5af72"><em>Clustering</em>: The dataset is assumed to have some latent structure which should be discovered by partitioning the data points into groups that are close to each other in variants of the feature space. A typical example is the exploratory analysis of unlabeled data.</p><p id="b668059c501d4adcab60238e9ed087d2"><em>Anomaly Detection</em>: The dataset is assumed to have some latent structure that should be discovered in order to identify instances that do not adhere to the pattern. A typical example is the detection of fake customer reviews in online retail data.</p><p id="d6e86c38264a457eb0f6e25725ede717"><em>Domain-specific tasks</em>: Aside from the generic task types explained above, some domains have developed specific task patterns and associated evaluation metrics that should be used if the analytic goal is sufficiently specific. This is particularly true of natural language processing and image analysis. For example, machine translation will commonly be characterized as a text generation task, and models will be evaluated using a specialized metric called the <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BLEU" target="new" internal="false">BLEU score</link>. Similarly, models that segment a part of an image containing a specific object may be evaluated using average precision in conjunction with an \xe2\x80\x9cintersection over union\xe2\x80\x9d threshold. </p><p id="fb8c096d9e3243b99658f81c79db5269">It should be noted that some of these categories overlap somewhat in that the methods associated with them can be used in different ways. For example, ranking problems can be solved using classification or regression methods. Still, if the primary nature of the problem is that items must be ranked, it should be evaluated using ranking experiments and metrics, even if it is doing classification \xe2\x80\x9cunder the hood.\xe2\x80\x9d </p><p id="ab38641610544610b46f3ac2a88c1c9f">The purpose of identifying the type of task at this stage is not to firmly restrict the project to a narrow instrumentarium, but to characterize it for purposes of planning and communication. Specifically, a possible quantitative evaluation and the metrics used therein will typically closely correspond to the problem&apos;s primary nature. </p><p id="f6091e57e513492d8e23df0794b300df" /><wb:inline idref="newd35b6c9ed09e4d47bf3b515bec15e5cc" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>\n'