b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="d2206ec065de492685ff42d30117262f"><head><title>Be Mindful of the End Goal</title></head><body><p id="e508c18995684780b2763eed51b16a9b">Metrics are employed to objectively evaluate the performance of machine learning models. When selecting a metric, you should always have the end goal of the machine learning application in mind. </p><p id="f28694152b674c608b29cf0feea4292b">In practice, we are usually interested not just in making accurate predictions but also in using these predictions as part of a larger decision-making process. Before picking a machine learning metric, you should think about the high-level goal of the application, often called the business metric. The consequences of choosing a particular algorithm for a machine learning application are called the business impact. Despite being called \xe2\x80\x9cbusiness impact\xe2\x80\x9d, not losing track of the end goal is important in any scientific domain. This can be the high-level goal of avoiding traffic accidents or decreasing the number of hospital admissions. It could also be getting more users for your website, or having users spend more money in your shop. When choosing a model or adjusting parameters, you should pick the model or parameter values that have the most positive influence on the business metric. Often this is hard, as assessing the business impact of a particular model might require putting it in production in a real-life system.</p><p id="dd30f9e1a43046bb95c16693d3cc5384">In the early stages of development, and for adjusting parameters, it is often infeasible to put models into production just for testing purposes, because of the high business or personal risks that can be involved. Imagine evaluating the pedestrian avoidance capabilities of a self-driving car by just letting it drive around, without verifying it first; if your model is bad, pedestrians will be in trouble! Therefore we often need to find some surrogate evaluation procedure, using an evaluation metric that is easier to compute. For example, we could test classifying images of pedestrians against non-pedestrians and measure accuracy. Keep in mind that this is only a surrogate, and it pays off to find the closest metric to the original business goal that is feasible to evaluate. This closest metric should be used whenever possible for model evaluation and selection. The result of this evaluation might not be a single number\xe2\x80\x94the consequence of your algorithm could be that you have 10% more customers, but each customer will spend 15% less\xe2\x80\x94but it should capture the expected business impact of choosing one model over another.</p><p id="dff0b596e68145a488e1f114044f06e9">This section covers a number of common metrics used in classification, regression, and clustering problems. It is imperative that you understand which metrics are suitable for which use cases because your choice of metric (which should be decided prior to model training) will have an impact on the entire subsequent pipeline. or example, you may get different best models in the model selection process with different metrics.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'