b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="e61fc247f8404e7f873a97cc8b70a6e6"><head><title>Developing a Vision</title></head><body><p id="bd0b4c1ad4b84a279489e6e262498fea">To develop a vision for the project, the project team works with stakeholders to develop a vision document and related artifacts that represent the high-level scope and purpose of the project. The vision document communicates the motivation for the project - what problems does the proposed undertaking attempt to solve, and for what data set(s)? What is novel or unique about the proposed method? How will success be measured and evaluated? What is the anticipated impact (business or research value) if the project is successful? An explicit statement of the problem, proposed solution, and high-level features of the project can establish clear expectations and reduce potential risks.</p><p id="f2cfde9448d14fae8fe98fd332042cea">Before diving into the implementation of the project, the vision must be developed. The vision defines the high-level objective of the entire project and presents clarity with respect to the problem statement, scientific hypothesis, and scope of the proposed solution. It is essential as it introduces the domain of the problem that needs to be addressed and provides a rough timeline of the tasks involved in achieving this objective. It provides context to succeeding developers about why exactly this project is necessary.</p><image id="d61de3e9fd174a049d14335c0ca4c610" src="../webcontent/image-b320853fdfba42e1934f40150b6cecbd-1.png" alt="" style="inline" vertical-align="middle" height="325" width="650"><caption><p id="ebe0c85d383048c7a4e0fb6590e2b523">Figure 1. Engineering Lifecycle Management (IBM)</p></caption><popout enable="false"></popout></image></body></workbook_page>\n'