b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="f91876280e8743c1b110a49649a89162"><head><title>Module 3 Summary</title></head><body><p id="cdac7411a7a14c0cac521d7c7211cc36">The data science lifecycle structures the activities of the data science team. It should not be considered to be linear as there must be iterations of questioning and research involved in each phase. The framework consists of several major stages:  The framework involves input from various members of the data science team, as well as the client, as stated below: </p><ul id="c4d5ec6d3b8e4581a73a3655a8a18730"><li><p id="b8bb220952f142cabc437944183ec726"><em style="italic">Business Understanding</em> involves framing the objectives and assessing data science readiness. The client and data science team are involved in this stage to ensure that the analytic solutions meet the business objectives.</p></li><li><p id="a5dc6a70e001420681b57b9d039f3bea"><em style="italic">Data Acquisition</em> involves gathering data from various appropriate sources. Data preparation techniques are employed to ensure the data is useful for analysis.</p></li><li><p id="f77dd6999b00468db57fcee9d797f20a"><em style="italic">Modeling</em> involves choosing the appropriate model for the problem (we see why business understanding comes first!) even though it is often mistaken as the first stage of the process. Modeling typically consists of feature engineering, algorithm selection, model training, and evaluation.</p></li><li><p id="a71c660f5fc6483fa7608d2a7e1c8694"><em style="italic">Deployment</em> involves the implementation of the solution developed in the operating environment of the business. One should always remember that a business needs to measure the impact of the deployed solution to ensure the success of the solution.</p></li></ul><p id="e5a399e0ae98454a8eab687991eceaf9">The data science lifecycle can seem daunting at first, but a data scientist will not complete all the tasks alone. A productive team will consist of individuals with complementary skills filling various roles that can ensure the project is successfully executed.</p></body></workbook_page>\n'