b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="Hardware"><head><title>Hardware: An Overlooked Aspect of Data Science</title></head><body><p id="d35e5eab1d7b47e29648ea3867ba2428">At the beginning of a  data science process on any task, it is important not just to understand the dataset and the tools available but also the hardware resources available to you for the task at hand. Most data science tasks rely on using statistical or numerical techniques to process the data and/or optimize some discrete/continuous optimization task. In doing so, you\xe2\x80\x99ll need to assess if a task is feasible with the hardware you have and what hardware to use to make the most of the computational budget you\xe2\x80\x99re given to solve the analytic objective.</p><p id="e1c52fc9c79a4924bfc25e82b5fc01af">In this chapter, our goal will be to give a brief tour of what hardware resources one should look at when deciding what hardware to get for a specific task. While it will not be overly exhaustive, our goal here is twofold:</p><ul id="f28fba5648294549a1d22e83c1f41c19"><li><p id="d055f7076de84bd6bedfbfde4a285ce6">First, you will want to spend time to make sure that the tools you use actively use the computational resources you are given. Taking the time to understand if and when you can scale down any cloud computing resources you are using can save you time and money in performing any computational task, which then can be a boon as you assess different statistical techniques and their performance in your analytic objective.</p></li><li><p id="c39476ed439c4b3dbff4147cf93ee73c">Second, you will want to assess how you are using the various libraries common to data science. Compared to more traditional single-threaded and multi-threaded applications, data science libraries tend to require users to focus on operations, unlike those more traditionally used, such as conditional indexing and matrix multiplication. In this chapter, you\xe2\x80\x99ll find motivation for learning these libraries to the depth necessary to perform these tasks, as they form the basis for highly performant and highly readable data science code.</p></li></ul></body></workbook_page>\n'