<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Inline Assessment MathML 1.4//EN" "http://oli.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_inline_assessment_mathml_1_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="newec77e3afe5524c8c8ea4cc9b653cb082"><title>New Formative Assessment</title><page id="ef077a9ebd334ef9a1bb6a40b69bc028"><title>Page 1</title><question id="newec77e3afe5524c8c8ea4cc9b653cb082_1a"><body><p id="ff23de0814a145b1809531d0644ed405">What does the data science team need to do to understand the business objective?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="false" select="single" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">The team should strive to understand the client’s explanations, but also make a professional effort of researching the business and the field/market it operates in.</choice><choice value="dfec01df3447478885df2431ce919de8">The data science team should always have a member who is formally educated or professionally trained in the client’s area of work.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="aaf9b60e11c64c8ea8ccd37cc05a51c2"><skillref idref="e88201aeaee84291892b9c8dc10a1c70" /><response match="yes" score="1"><feedback><p id="e766b25d824c4e2f9f1fee386bd9fbb0">Correct: The data science team must assist the business in translating the business needs to data science tasks.</p></feedback></response><response match="dfec01df3447478885df2431ce919de8" score="0"><feedback><p id="e24bee5e5ddb4af4b61d8a3905f26d2f">Incorrect: A data scientist does not need to become an expert in the respective area or market, but should be convinced that the domain is sufficiently understood and that she can intuitively explain why and how the business wants to reach the objective.</p></feedback></response></part></question><question id="c10c5afe68694bbcbd87299180e48fdf"><body><p id="c1a1367719594c369af280d0edb3dea0">You are part of the data science team for a project and the analytic objectives are set. A model that predicts the lifetime value of a customer is needed; the data science team begins to build the model. Which statement is true?</p></body><multiple_choice shuffle="true" select="single" id="bd8c5fe30ae34757ada43c7f71545c30" labels="false"><choice value="d4f3359b9dae406dbc973c9f36ccd79d">The project is prone to failure as the team will likely develop a solution that does not meet the client&apos;s needs.</choice><choice value="f3abfe3654e4488aa6279d29219f978b">The data science team will meet the business need and save time and cost.</choice></multiple_choice><part id="b04cb34bda0149c0921629e0e340253a"><skillref idref="ee23003b2e8f40aa8f6874861e56fad2" /><response match="d4f3359b9dae406dbc973c9f36ccd79d" score="1"><feedback><p id="bb5addb4a42a487fbaf154ddde40c322">Correct: The data science team although equipped to build models, will miss essential steps including data preprocessing.</p></feedback></response><response match="f3abfe3654e4488aa6279d29219f978b" score="0"><feedback><p id="eaa77ca603d74fceba75a6bc2a039c99">Incorrect: The data science team will neglect the important steps including requirements gathering and data preprocessing. </p></feedback></response></part></question></page></assessment>
