b'<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>\n<!DOCTYPE assessment PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Assessment MathML 2.4//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_assessment_mathml_2_4.dtd"><assessment xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" id="newdd2459b171104b18844c4a43c6be314d" recommended_attempts="1" max_attempts="1"><title>Quiz 10</title><page id="eaaa91771d9945af9760d4a638bc402e"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><multiple_choice id="newdd2459b171104b18844c4a43c6be314d_1a" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="cb8a925e89e440f4a7672c6683cf898e">Delivery Lead Time is defined as the time it takes for a customer to make a request to a server to the time taken to get a response from the server. Which of the following does Delivery Lead Time come under below metrics?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ans" labels="false"><choice value="yes">Resource Metric</choice><choice value="no">Data Metric</choice><choice value="c493d5e03f144b13ae948e3d93b8ade2">Model Metric</choice><choice value="c50d9ae5fc4c453e9c3a0804ae37b064">Business Metric</choice><choice value="adf460bbd9ef455088bcbd33315b090d">None of these options</choice></input><part id="cd9d8111415d45b6b457ab07aa370f77"><response match="yes" score="10"><feedback><p id="f9553f33cbd84c70bd02f4c6f4b55b1f">Correct. A resource Metric, also called a system metric, focuses on infrastructure instead of model and data. Some of the resource metrics include delivery lead time, throughput, CPU/GPU usage, etc.</p></feedback></response><response match="no" score="0"><feedback><p id="f306a6bc45f74c3da2d8cfd27ac502ee">Incorrect. Data Metric measures the distribution and quality of input data to the model. Metrics detecting data drift comes under Data Metrics. Examples of data metrics include mean, median and standard deviation, etc. Resource Metric is the correct answer. A resource Metric, also called a system metric, focuses on infrastructure instead of model and data. Some of the resource metrics include delivery lead time, throughput, CPU/GPU usage, etc.</p></feedback></response><response match="c493d5e03f144b13ae948e3d93b8ade2" score="0"><feedback><p id="b282649f7ce74eb3b98a1872bf0dc008">Incorrect. Model metrics measure the quality of model responses. After deployment, AI professionals measure online model metrics periodically to check the model&apos;s performance. Examples of data metrics include accuracy, precision, normalized discounted cumulative gain, etc. Resource Metric is the correct answer. A resource Metric, also called a system metric, focuses on infrastructure instead of model and data. Some of the resource metrics include delivery lead time, throughput, CPU/GPU usage, etc.</p></feedback></response><response match="c50d9ae5fc4c453e9c3a0804ae37b064" score="0"><feedback><p id="d1c9ce05038b410e995269958bb875e6">Incorrect. A business metric is a quantifiable measure businesses use to track, monitor, and assess the success or failure of various business processes. Not all business metrics can be resource metrics. However, some resource metrics can be business metrics. For example, the latency of predictions can be a business metric if customers&apos; business success depends on low latency applications. Resource Metric is the correct answer. A resource Metric, also called a system metric, focuses on infrastructure instead of model and data. Some of the resource metrics include delivery lead time, throughput, CPU/GPU usage, etc.</p></feedback></response><response match="adf460bbd9ef455088bcbd33315b090d" score="0"><feedback><p id="bcd0a97ea33e429998a87b9b21c09b1d">Incorrect. Resource Metric is the correct answer. A resource Metric, also called a system metric, focuses on infrastructure instead of model and data. Some of the resource metrics include delivery lead time, throughput, CPU/GPU usage, etc.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page><page id="be773661bd4c427585c0d957b7361cba"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><multiple_choice id="ebd020b2e666471baf9974984db2af15" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="ca0f0c16dcfc4f5495ba1495a1146117">Which of the following best describes why AI professionals need to be aware of the research, development, and production environments?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="a739252e3966471894276e8fa3d7dc80" labels="false"><choice value="fa2a210fcde04bca993351db60d343f2">Every AI professional wants to work in all three environments </choice><choice value="d66a22443a254accbf456fb16e93526f">Helps in collaborating with other AI professionals across different environments</choice><choice value="e37f0901de7e47f8a60e0c6f6b22d831">Organizations always expect individuals to be experts in all three environments</choice><choice value="fa243d64fc1a416a981240bbb77ff4a4">All of the above</choice></input><part id="cb296181fade4a77b9b5d330b31e72f1"><response match="fa2a210fcde04bca993351db60d343f2" score="0"><feedback><p id="f995c3d06fc54c6f8a23df92c6d97286">Incorrect. Not every AI professional wants or needs to work in all three environments. For example, a Data Scientist wants to focus on model performance and might not wish and be expected to deploy models in production.</p></feedback></response><response match="d66a22443a254accbf456fb16e93526f" score="10"><feedback><p id="da34ca088d5649cc8f7fc6a58544bf43">Correct. Awareness of the basics in all three environments helps AI professionals easily communicate and collaborate with other team members. For example, awareness of how models are usually deployed in production allows Data Scientists to more easily collaborate with Cloud Architects and Software Engineers in order to deploy a developed model.</p></feedback></response><response match="e37f0901de7e47f8a60e0c6f6b22d831" score="0"><feedback><p id="fd579200e4d34517923a022476b68555">Incorrect. Some startups might expect and appreciate AI professionals who are experts in all three environments. However, some bigger organizations have defined roles and might not expect their employees to be experts in all three domains.</p></feedback></response><response match="fa243d64fc1a416a981240bbb77ff4a4" score="0"><feedback><p id="ce916c3c1528470e91c4206e726f3a96">Incorrect. Awareness of the basics in all three environments helps AI professionals easily communicate and collaborate with other team members. For example, awareness of how models are usually deployed in production allows Data Scientists to more easily collaborate with Cloud Architects and Software Engineers in order to deploy a developed model.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page><page id="c1a5971cc8224734ba4a3fa75512f7d5"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><multiple_choice id="eb90e910d3f1419996788d69a1a56895" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="f911fbcf3e1b4e08aa3c1aa3188be267">What file contains information related to building a Docker Image?</p></body><input shuffle="true" id="ab099d0033894ee5b295a17b2ba7537d" labels="false"><choice value="b9728d426dcb44528086fc3356f11047">Yamlfile</choice><choice value="a3209694c1644f4ca24f609677414fae">Dockerfile </choice><choice value="a342dbcd20194b8bacdd1c52b31d5776">Jenkinsfile</choice><choice value="f49ee9ee92844e95a56256171889c9f0">Docker-compose file</choice><choice value="eab33698c7914506bd2f8bc339528a89">None of these options</choice></input><part id="f66ed266857b44de9ec933d31916a068"><response match="b9728d426dcb44528086fc3356f11047" score="0"><feedback><p id="a4e240f330cc4b9cbf0cf5f20626fe8e">Incorrect. YAML is a digestible data serialization language often used to create configuration files with any programming language. It is a file format like CSV, txt, excel, etc. Dockerfile is the correct answer. A Dockerfile is a text document that contains all the commands a user could call on the command line to assemble an image.</p></feedback></response><response match="a3209694c1644f4ca24f609677414fae" score="10"><feedback><p id="c9510f9447fb4672a5caf5dbc25727ff">Correct. A Dockerfile is a text document that contains all the commands a user could call on the command line to assemble an image.</p></feedback></response><response match="a342dbcd20194b8bacdd1c52b31d5776" score="0"><feedback><p id="f458842c74d14214bf161cd9f90a96a9">Incorrect. Jenkins helps automate the parts of software development related to building, testing, and deploying, facilitating continuous integration and continuous delivery. Jenkinsfile is a text file that contains the definition of a Jenkins Pipeline. Dockerfile is the correct answer. A Dockerfile is a text document that contains all the commands a user could call on the command line to assemble an image.</p></feedback></response><response match="f49ee9ee92844e95a56256171889c9f0" score="0"><feedback><p id="fb10f187473b4a02916a7b5599589aa9">Incorrect. A docker-compose file is a YAML file that specifies how to run docker containers and allows deploying multiple Docker containers at the same time. It still requires Dockerfile to build the image. The main difference: Dockerfile describes how to build Docker images while docker-compose is used to run Docker containers. Dockerfile is the correct answer. A Dockerfile is a text document that contains all the commands a user could call on the command line to assemble an image.</p></feedback></response><response match="eab33698c7914506bd2f8bc339528a89" score="0"><feedback><p id="cf97fe11f54348bba897171356ead6a6">Incorrect. Dockerfile is the correct answer. A Dockerfile is a text document that contains all the commands a user could call on the command line to assemble an image.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page><page id="ef332b1d691e4a2abeb082d79ec82bef"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><multiple_choice id="a293c59b0a84479c86877476d4f051e9" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="c296d65397be47428dda3426271b6827">Which of the following is true when explaining why data versioning is important?</p></body><input shuffle="false" id="d34b54b2e5ad4e8fa04f40cae938e2c9" labels="false"><choice value="e487087ef6ee47c391319ee739ed1b53">It helps in data drift situations.</choice><choice value="b24d29d72ef349ea9904e623402470aa">It makes data-related compliance, auditing, and risk management processes easier.</choice><choice value="b9a63b71c1ac40a4b1f3d173e508eb24">It helps in reproducing model experiments.</choice><choice value="c1a6bab50caa4c58a37b7c93b6ea3e68">All of the above</choice></input><part id="d2db9e01e3e44db7a091896d889eb51d"><response match="e487087ef6ee47c391319ee739ed1b53" score="0"><feedback><p id="d85266547ea14861ae5869b53f48d899">Incorrect. This is not the only correct answer. Tracking data helps to roll back to an old dataset or collect a new dataset and tag it when data distribution changes to rebuild the model and deliver quality results. All three statements are true when explaining why data versioning is important.</p></feedback></response><response match="b24d29d72ef349ea9904e623402470aa" score="0"><feedback><p id="c114043338fe40a5b97c4752e444f564">Incorrect. This is not the only correct answer. Data protection regulations, such as the GDPR, force companies to store certain data sources. Data versioning can save companies time in meeting such requirements. It can also be easier for companies to detect fraud if they have versioned their data. All three statements are true when explaining why data versioning is important.</p></feedback></response><response match="b9a63b71c1ac40a4b1f3d173e508eb24" score="0"><feedback><p id="a063ff58c54144cc9088f9df6b338d7c">Incorrect. This is not the only correct answer. Tracking data changes enables AI professionals to roll back to previous data versions and re-train models to reproduce experiments. All three statements are true when explaining why data versioning is important.</p></feedback></response><response match="c1a6bab50caa4c58a37b7c93b6ea3e68" score="10"><feedback><p id="ac18cec0c6b34ee8bdc46da26264b981">Correct. All three statements are true when explaining why data versioning is important.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page><page id="dda14778652148d2a8fe4fb922580d58"><title>Assessment Page Title</title><multiple_choice id="ad92ab76c8b946088204b7c6b22a1526" grading="automatic" select="single"><body><p id="cdc0521705d44f28b5f6d3a36ef8e663">Let us assume an AI model that learns P(Y|X) where Y is a dependent variable and X is a set of independent variables. What is the phenomenon called when X changes while monitoring the model? </p></body><input shuffle="false" id="cc73f762a2164aecbbed27064c23a892" labels="false"><choice value="d44aeee9bee74974a7dcd514e4ad8b6b">Data Drift</choice><choice value="f791e0521b5147918631f43ea089c645">Concept Drift</choice><choice value="cfe3f935c63c4bcf96ae60b94e2d2fbf">Model Drift</choice><choice value="a98c86ac2c904ce5a1a4ad6f00ad5875">None of the above</choice></input><part id="c644c2f7e5414da1bee7c740dfd99733"><response match="d44aeee9bee74974a7dcd514e4ad8b6b" score="10"><feedback><p id="db1cb82a201e4df09dead64b51efb4ad">Correct. Data drift or feature drift happens when there is a meaningful change in distribution between the training data and production data. Changes in input data distribution will affect model performance over time.</p></feedback></response><response match="f791e0521b5147918631f43ea089c645" score="0"><feedback><p id="fdb81b6651ad4fbfa17d34aa494036d8">Incorrect. Concept drift happens when the relationship between features and/or labels no longer holds because the learned relationship/patterns have changed over time. Data Drift is the correct answer. Data drift or feature drift happens when there is a meaningful change in distribution between the training data and production data. Changes in input data distribution will affect model performance over time.</p></feedback></response><response match="cfe3f935c63c4bcf96ae60b94e2d2fbf" score="0"><feedback><p id="da3449fcb5814ef58b1d1b0b15b198d3">Incorrect. Model drift is a superset that consists of concept drift and data drift. Data Drift is the correct answer. Data drift or feature drift happens when there is a meaningful change in distribution between the training data and production data. Changes in input data distribution will affect model performance over time.</p></feedback></response><response match="a98c86ac2c904ce5a1a4ad6f00ad5875" score="0"><feedback><p id="a9f2eea4d2b8490fbfeca49cf1142dde">Incorrect. Data Drift is the correct answer. Data drift or feature drift happens when there is a meaningful change in distribution between the training data and production data. Changes in input data distribution will affect model performance over time.</p></feedback></response></part></multiple_choice></page></assessment>\n'