<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE workbook_page PUBLIC "-//Carnegie Mellon University//DTD Workbook Page MathML 3.8//EN" "http://oli.web.cmu.edu/dtd/oli_workbook_page_mathml_3_8.dtd"><workbook_page xmlns:bib="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:cmd="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/content/metadata/2.1/" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:pref="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/preferences/" xmlns:theme="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/presentation/" xmlns:wb="http://oli.web.cmu.edu/activity/workbook/" id="b18d448de2514761bc6bda97d9b4bb60"><head><title>Defining an Analytic Objective</title><objref idref="c652b19601414ebebcfaed9f52cd17e0" /></head><body><p id="a06585577cfe42778aae3b934bd8af5e">Once a set of business goals has been identified, one can proceed to formulate <em style="italic">analytic objectives</em> that state how the application of analytical methods to data can facilitate reaching the business goal. An analytic objective can typically be phrased along the following template: </p><p id="d2d7c78e2ef74690810f232ddc5a2b75" /><table id="dbd6ef09acab490a8cc760ebae98d1ff" summary="" rowstyle="plain"><cite id="ia11f77133f5d4ff3b65c9faecf20c547" /><caption><p id="decb1070ab8c495f8a44eecd66ab2ebe" /></caption><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left"><p id="b358ec4e54374ccdb015bdfc9be71f35">As an incremental step towards business objective <em>O </em></p><p id="ecaf85a9eb094c2a8342e44aa9757a7e">We work towards solving problem <em>P </em></p><p id="b486dfc963c747f9895971f126125620">by focusing on specific task <em>T</em></p><p id="b239d109c4244edea8069e07e07b14af">and applying analytic methods <em>M</em> in conjunction with data <em>D</em></p><p id="d5b96a7d67c2406ab224099d2557d889">to create valuable functionality <em>F</em> and/or produce insight <em>I</em></p><p id="fbd0017ff23e433495a0a38c8933163c" /></td></tr></table><p id="cd8fc78ab0644faf9404093f5d965216">This formulation of an analytic objective can also be considered a research hypothesis because it effectively posits that a certain technique improves a metric with regard to a population of problem instances (comparable to a treatment versus a control condition). In fact, in academic settings, the effectiveness of data science methods will regularly be scrutinized using statistical tests and it is good practice to principally strive for similar methodological rigor in industry applications. While data science teams and projects in the private sector may use different terminology and specific technical or other circumstances may differ, this pattern of formulating analytic objectives is a very good point of departure for framing data science work and effectively communicating with clients and domain experts. It is the connecting element between the problem, the technique to be applied, the associated requirements and evaluation, as well as the business objective. Also, keep in mind that projects often comprise multiple analytic objectives that form a larger plan. </p><p id="cd503432287742a196776876fadfe5d4">In order for you to become proficient in working with this definition, we will now move to examining its components. </p><p id="d30ebc77d0fc4cf89ce7f7e68f6a9ac2" /><wb:inline idref="newe24dd5075d2540cd9de815c1d10f3492" purpose="didigetthis" /></body></workbook_page>
